<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-secondary courses related to data science in education - a crowdsourced list of sorts</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/14/post-secondary-courses-related-to-data-science-in-education-a-crowdsourced-list-of-sorts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/14/post-secondary-courses-related-to-data-science-in-education-a-crowdsourced-list-of-sorts/</guid>
      <description>I solicited information baout courses related to data science in education, and ended up with more than I expected. This is a crowdsourced list, with courses spanning data science education (data science as a new context for teaching and learning) and the application of different data science methods to learning analytics and educational data mining:
 Applied Social Network Analysis in Education (Bodong Chen) Learning Analytics: Theory and Practice (Bodong Chen) Carpe Datum (Yoav Bergner) Theoretical Foundations of Learning Analytics and Learning Analytics in Practice (forthcoming) (Nia Dowell and Shayan Doroudi) Data Science Specialization (five courses) (Daniel Anderson) Big Data and Education (Ryan Baker) Core Methods in Educational Data Mining (Charles Lang) Learning Analytics Fundamentals (George Siemens and colleagues) Data Science Education (and Data Science Education for pre-service teachers) (Victor Lee) Foundations of Learning Analytics and Educational Data Science (Alyssa Wise) Building Learning Analytics Applications (Alyssa Wise) Certificate Program in Learning Analytics (four courses) (Shaun Kellogg) Massive Open Online Course on Building Legitimate Predictive Analytics With Learning Design and Theory (forthcoming) (Erkan Er) Data Analysis, Simulation, and Programming in R (James Pustejovsky) Machine Learning in Education (Zach Pardos) Programming and Educational Data Science (forthcoming) (Fernando Rodriguez) Data Visualization (Cynthia D&amp;rsquo;Angelo)  There are also a few compendia of courses:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Informal, Open Introduction to Using R Markdown in Education</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/10/a-free-open-workshop-on-using-r-markdown-for-data-science-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/10/a-free-open-workshop-on-using-r-markdown-for-data-science-in-education/</guid>
      <description>Like many things posted to the #rstats hashtag on Twitter, a recent post requesting resources related to using R Markdown led to a number of helpful ones. The post was in the context of learning R and R Markdown for research- related projects in education.
I shared many of the resources (and the post) with a graduate research assistant and thought about meeting one-on-one to review and walk through them. But, there are a few others at my institution who are also interested in learning R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article on understanding engagement in out-of-school STEM programs using an experience sampling method to study youths&#39; experiences</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/09/new-article-on-engagement-in-out-of-school-stem-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/09/new-article-on-engagement-in-out-of-school-stem-programs/</guid>
      <description>With Jen Schmidt, Patrick Beymer, Neil Naftzger, and Lee Shumow, I recently published an article on youth&amp;rsquo;s engagement in one of nine out-of-school, STEM- focused summer programs. The study uses an experience sampling method (or ESM) to study youth&amp;rsquo;s experiences, in which participating youth were asked multiple, short surveys &amp;ldquo;in- the-moment&amp;rdquo;, rather than one (or more) longer surveys at less-regular intervals. The logic is that such surveys can assess something like engagement in a qualitatively (and subjectively, for youth) different way than a traditional survey can.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article on exploring the validity of assessment items for the NGSS using machine learning</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/07/new-article-on-exploring-the-content-related-validity-of-assessment-items-for-the-ngss-using-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/07/new-article-on-exploring-the-content-related-validity-of-assessment-items-for-the-ngss-using-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>Daniel Anderson, Brock Rowley, Sondra Stegenga, and Shawn Irvin, and I published a paper on the role of a text-based machine learning technique - topic models - can be used to provide content validity evidence for Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS)-related assessment items.
While I have some experience with topic modeling, as well as experience with NGSS-related assessments, the measurement focus of this work was new to me, and so was a great opportunity for me to learn more; Dan and his colleagues conceptualized and carried out this work in an impressive way, and I was happy to contribute to it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Videos in the 2020 STEM For All Video Showcase</title>
      <link>/post/2020/05/06/videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/05/06/videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase/</guid>
      <description>My colleagues submitted videos to the 2020 STEM for All Video Showcase for two projects:
Theory-based Computational Analysis of Classroom Video: https://stemforall2020.videohall.com/presentations/1667
![tca2-screenshot](/post/2020-05-06-videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase_files/Screen Shot 2020-05-06 at 9.19.28 AM.png)
Computer Science for Appalachia: https://stemforall2020.videohall.com/presentations/1730
![cs-for-appalachia-screenshot](/post/2020-05-06-videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase_files/Screen Shot 2020-05-06 at 9.19.53 AM.png)
They&amp;rsquo;re short (three minutes or less) and intended to provide an overview of their respective projects. I&amp;rsquo;m proud of them and the work that went into them. Both projects are finishing their first year this summer, and so there will be (a lot) that I hope to share over the coming years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An update to how U.S. school districts are responding to COVID-19</title>
      <link>/post/2020/04/25/update-to-how-u-s-school-districts-are-responding-to-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2020/04/25/update-to-how-u-s-school-districts-are-responding-to-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, I wrote about an attempt to understand how United States (U.S.) school districts are responding to COVID-19 (link here). A big part of that earlier work was a map depicting the number of districts within states mentioning COVID-19.
With inspiration, ideas, and help from Teya Rutherford, [Daniel Anderson](Daniel Anderson), Alex Lishinski, and Ha Nguyen), the underlying data is more trustworthy and the map is now interactive (and is at the district, rather than the state, level) and is available here (or by clicking the screenshot below):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Education Using R by (and a little beyond) the numbers</title>
      <link>/posts/data-science-in-education-using-r-by-and-beyond-the-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/data-science-in-education-using-r-by-and-beyond-the-numbers/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R is done!
Here&amp;rsquo;s us (with a few of us a bit in the dark), right around when we clicked &amp;ldquo;send&amp;rdquo; on an email with links/attachments for what was a two-year project.
Data Science in Education Using R by the numbers The project involved a lot of steps, and it is possible, particularly because of the way in which we wrote the book in the open, to describe the process by the numbers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How are U.S. school districts responding to COVID? A first look at 12,500 districts&#39; websites</title>
      <link>/posts/how-are-u-s-school-districts-responding-to-covid-a-first-look-at-12-500-districts-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/how-are-u-s-school-districts-responding-to-covid-a-first-look-at-12-500-districts-websites/</guid>
      <description>Like many educational researchers (and teachers, parents, administrators . . . and kids), I have been wondering about how U.S. school districts are responding to the COVID-19 pandemic. There seemed to be a lot of variation, not only across U.S. states, but also within districts within states, and even within districts (and even within schools in districts!).
Exploring how districts in Tennessee (and, soon, other states) are responding to COVID-19 One way I&amp;rsquo;m pursuing this is through a project wherein we are trying to document what every district in the state of Tennessee (and, possibly, soon, in other states) are doing to respond: Whether they are completely closed or they are still providing opportunities for students to learn; what kinds of teaching and learning and/or resources are provided to students (and their parents); and, how districts are supporting students who might very reasonably not have, for instance, reliable Internet access at their home, or a computer that they can use to access resources (not to mention Zoom).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your state still planning to carry out end-of-course testing in light of COVID-19? Crowdsourcing information</title>
      <link>/posts/is-your-state-still-planning-to-carry-out-end-of-course-testing-crowdsourcing-information/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/is-your-state-still-planning-to-carry-out-end-of-course-testing-crowdsourcing-information/</guid>
      <description>State testing My colleague Isabella Velasquez and I were wondering what states were doing with respect to end-of-course testing, and found that no comprehensive (of which we were aware) yet existed. As a result, we decided to try to crowdsource this information.
Has your state announced whether they are postponing end-of-course (or other planned) tests this year in light of COVID-19? Please take a minute or so to add this information to this Google Sheets spreadsheet: https://docs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual KnoxData presentation (via Zoom) on reproducible, scalable research with drake in R</title>
      <link>/posts/virtual-via-zoom-knoxdata-presentation-on-reproducible-scalable-research-with-drake-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/virtual-via-zoom-knoxdata-presentation-on-reproducible-scalable-research-with-drake-in-r/</guid>
      <description>KnoxData is hosting a virtual (Zoom-based) presentation tonight (Thursday, Mar. 19) from 6:30 - 7:30 pm EST on Reproducible, scalable research: an example with drake in R. D
Here is some information on the presentation; more is available on the group&amp;rsquo;s Meetup page.
 We all start out using things like Excel to analyze data. Sometimes we progress to entering commands in languages like R and python, then save our commands into a script and run that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In support of JOSS for not accepting new article submissions</title>
      <link>/posts/in-support-of-joss-for-not-accepting-new-article-submissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/in-support-of-joss-for-not-accepting-new-article-submissions/</guid>
      <description>The Journal of Open Source Software announced last week (via email and on Twitter) that:
 Submissions to JOSS are suspended for 30 days to provide relief to authors, editors, and reviewers dealing with the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic.
 The attached image from the Tweet is an elaboration of this announcement:
I think this is a good idea, and support it. Setting the expectation from the &amp;ldquo;top-down&amp;rdquo; can support individuals&amp;rsquo; decision (necessary or forced) to slow their pace of non-urgent work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Help request - bookdown figure numbers out of order</title>
      <link>/posts/help-request-bookdown-figure-numbers-out-of-order/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/help-request-bookdown-figure-numbers-out-of-order/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R co-author Isabella posted in RStudio Community about a strange issue encountered when adding figure numbers to the book: they are regularly out of order. The post in RStudio Community is here.
As one example, in Chapter 5, the figure numbering begins with 5.1 . . . but then proceeds to 0.1, and then picks up (correctly) with 5.3 through the last figure, 5.10.
After trying to figure out whether there was an issue with that figure (source code for Chapter 5), we looked at other chapters, like Chapter 9, for which the numbering is even more dramatically out or order.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Requesting your feedback: Data Science in Education Using R is almost ready!</title>
      <link>/posts/requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready/</guid>
      <description>The Data Science in Education Using R book is almost ready to be sent to the publisher.
You can view the latest version of the book (as of this morning!) at the following URL:
https://datascienceineducation.com/
The screenshot below shows how to suggest a revision through GitHub; this functionality exists for every chapter of the book.
![](/post/2020-03-11-requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready_files/Screen Shot 2020-03-11 at 10.08.18 AM.png)
If you prefer, you can email us with any suggested edits at authors@datascienceineducation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sickness and gratitude</title>
      <link>/posts/sickness-and-gratitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/sickness-and-gratitude/</guid>
      <description>As this post&amp;rsquo;s title indicates, this isn&amp;rsquo;t a typical blog post for me; it&amp;rsquo;s on (much) a personal note. I&amp;rsquo;ll preface this post by saying that I&amp;rsquo;m fundamentally healthy (and so is my fam): that is sort of the thesis of the post.
Starting in December, our son came down with a bad ear infection that continued through the holiday break (and the new year). He got better - we got sick - and we moved on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More confidently uncertain? Teaching learners to apply Bayesian methods to make sense of scientific phenomena</title>
      <link>/posts/more-confidently-uncertain-teaching-learners-to-apply-bayesian-methods-to-make-sense-of-scientific-phenomena/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/more-confidently-uncertain-teaching-learners-to-apply-bayesian-methods-to-make-sense-of-scientific-phenomena/</guid>
      <description>This is a new area for me, one that I proposed to explore in the ICLS Early Career Workshop:
More confidently uncertain? Teaching learners to apply Bayesian methods to make sense of scientific phenomena
 While analyzing data is an important learning in science domains, existing methods and tools for those learning to work with data have key limitations, particularly concerning scientific modeling. This early-stage research is intended to begin a line of work on students’ data analysis that is not yet widely used in K-12 learning environments, Bayesian statistical methods, with implications for how learners use evidence in science education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New version of konfound (v 0.2.1) for sensitivity analysis available</title>
      <link>/posts/new-version-of-konfound-v-0-2-1-for-sensitivity-analysis-a-technique-to-support-trying-to-make-causal-inferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-version-of-konfound-v-0-2-1-for-sensitivity-analysis-a-technique-to-support-trying-to-make-causal-inferences/</guid>
      <description>A new version of konfound (v 0.2.1) for sensitivity analysis (a technique to support making causal inferences, especially in light of observational data) is available.
This version includes a new technique for non-linear models (i.e., a logistic regression).
Documentation for the package is available here: https://jrosen48.github.io/konfound/
We also updated the Shiny app associated with the package, available here: http://konfound-it.com/
Lastly, here are other blog posts on the topic:
 an introduction to the R package an introduction the Shiny app  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on studying education-focused Twitter hashtags in light of state-based and national policies and practices</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-studying-education-focused-twitter-hashtags-in-light-of-state-based-and-national-policies-and-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-studying-education-focused-twitter-hashtags-in-light-of-state-based-and-national-policies-and-practices/</guid>
      <description>Supported through an SEC Travel Grant, I am presenting on Studying education-focused Twitter hashtags in light of state-based and national policies and practices as a part of the 2020 Spring Seminar Series at the Martin School of Public Policy at the University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY.
A link to the presentation is here: https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1lNMAUGfBvnVsLEL8pbeS5On60v0vZifqeZkXsqkyFYk/edit?usp=sharing
Thank you to Annelise Russell and Spencer Greenhalgh for this awesome opportunity!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New version of tidyLPA (v 1.0.5) for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis using either open-source or commercial software</title>
      <link>/posts/new-version-of-tidylpa-1-0-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-version-of-tidylpa-1-0-5/</guid>
      <description>There is a new version of tidyLPA (v 1.0.5) available on CRAN (see here).
The website, with a lot more information than is on the page above, is here.
Changes include:
 Add function to calculate Lo-Mendell-Rubin LR test Add plot_bivariate() Set default for plot_profiles(add_line = FALSE), because the line does not convey any meaningful information Fix bug re. passing additional parameters to mplusObject() Remove messages about deprecated functions (those which were last used in v &amp;lt; 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a recursive function in R - or, tweets on tweets</title>
      <link>/posts/writing-a-recursive-function-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/writing-a-recursive-function-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Background Recursion has been a topic I’ve heard about, and even read about it, but have never used. Recently, I was analyzing data for the Next Generation Science Standards hashtag on Twitter, and was puzzled to find that some of the Tweets I had accessed were replies to Tweets which were themselves not in the data set.
Fortunately, the rtweet R package returns data on which Tweet a reply is to; using these, it is possible (using rtweet) to access the original Tweet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short activities focused around trying something new - some coding and data science-related examples</title>
      <link>/posts/code-bites-in-r-studio-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/code-bites-in-r-studio-cloud/</guid>
      <description>In research group meetings, we have started with short (5-10 minute) activities focused on trying something new.
So far, these activities have been focused on computer science or data science ideas. This post shares a few of those, which have been somewhat useful (I think!) so far:
 Writing and &amp;ldquo;using&amp;rdquo; a recipe for making pancakes (to explore the idea of an how computers closely follow the instructions they are told, as well as algorithms, conditional logic, and functions) Exploring what one notices about weather/climate-related data Tinkering with a cool agent-based model for frog adaptation Last, today, we used code bites in R/RStudio, with the goal being to create minimally viable (and interesting) content; it worked well, I think, by lowering the motivation-related barrier to writing code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open-source study - Resources related to our study of how students become interested in CS</title>
      <link>/posts/open-source-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/open-source-study/</guid>
      <description>We are beginning data collection today for our study of how students become interested in computer science (our beginning of a project website is at https://picsul.utk.edu/). I&amp;rsquo;ve blogged about the project two times before:
 Thoughts from submitting a grant proposal for the first time  New project on understanding the development of interest in computer science   One idea we have brought to the project is that we want to share as much as we possibly (ethically and based upon the Institutional Review Board applicaiton for the project) can.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article - Identifying multiple learning spaces in a single educational hashtag</title>
      <link>/posts/new-article-identifying-multiple-learning-spaces-in-a-single-educational-hashtag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-article-identifying-multiple-learning-spaces-in-a-single-educational-hashtag/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share about a second article published (today!) on how the regularly-occurring chats that take place through an education-focused Twitter hashtag are distinct from the rest of the time (i.e., non-chat times when people use the hashtag), is by Spencer Greenhalgh et al. in Computers &amp;amp; Education. Here is the abstract:
 The existing work on teacher-focused Twitter hashtags typically frames each hashtag as a single, unified phenomenon, thereby collapsing or erasing differences between them (and any resulting implications for learning).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article - The effects of choice and interest in science</title>
      <link>/posts/new-articles-the-effects-of-choice-and-interest-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-articles-the-effects-of-choice-and-interest-in-science/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share a link to an article published earlier this month on the effects of (learners) being able to make choices and their learning, and how that relates to their interest in what they are learning, is by Patrick Beymer et al. and is in Learning and Individual Differences. Here is the abstract:
 Having choices during learning is often touted as beneficial for student motivation. However, it is not clear whether the motivating factor is choice or the act of pursuing tasks that are of greater interest, which is often afforded by choice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple uses for multi-level models: Examples from recent research</title>
      <link>/posts/multiple-uses-for-multi-level-models-examples-from-recent-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/multiple-uses-for-multi-level-models-examples-from-recent-research/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m presenting on Multiple uses for multi-level models: Examples from recent research today for the College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences Quantitative Methods Brownbag Seminar.
A link to the presentation is here: https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1nY7n4H08fVMRUQxNQl6cy0ilLhX-2j7_PCj0TGPoFsE/edit?usp=sharing</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>KnoxData presentation: An introduction to using R for data science, zero prerequisites required!</title>
      <link>/posts/knoxdata-presentation-an-introduction-to-using-r-for-data-science-zero-prerequisites-required/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/knoxdata-presentation-an-introduction-to-using-r-for-data-science-zero-prerequisites-required/</guid>
      <description>I am presenting on Thursday, January 24th on An introduction to using R for data science (zero prerequisites required!) for the KnoxData group. The Meetup page for event is here.
A description of the event is here:
 R is a freely-available, cross-platform, open-source programming language and statistical software environment that is well-suited to doing data science, but, can have an high barrier to entry. This KnoxData presentation aims to provides an introduction to using for data science, with a focus on developing a foundation in capabilities (and confidence!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First version of a research group handbook</title>
      <link>/posts/first-verison-of-a-research-group-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/first-verison-of-a-research-group-handbook/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a first version of a research group handbook. Part of the joy of working with more students is the need to try to have greater structure around advising, carrying out projects, and meeting.
The handbook (view only via this link) is here on Google Docs: https://docs.google.com/document/d/13YmeUU4lSGWVqZfmCGljnJ4nTbD26TaY7oH3LUWo7Zk/edit?usp=sharing
Feedback is welcomed!
Thanks to Teya Rutherford for sharing the handbook for her research group. Thanks to Bodong Chen for posting his statement of graduate advising.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at the TN STEM Education Research Conference</title>
      <link>/posts/presentations-at-the-tn-stem-education-research-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentations-at-the-tn-stem-education-research-conference/</guid>
      <description>The Making Data Science Count research group has two presentations at the upcoming TN STEM Education Research Conference:
 Rosenberg, J. M.,&amp;amp; Lishinski, A. (January, 2020). Measuring what matters in-the-moment: An experience sampling approach to understanding the development of interest in computer science. Presentation at the 14th Annual Tennessee STEM Education Research Conference. Cookeville, TN.
  Rosenberg, J. M., Hodge, L., Aydeniz, M., Schmidt, A. Lishinski, A., Rich, K., Longnecker, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things I learned in the last year</title>
      <link>/posts/things-i-learned-in-the-last-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/things-i-learned-in-the-last-year/</guid>
      <description>Here are some things I learned in the last year. They are all unordered.
Models and parenting and teaching A collabofriend shared &amp;ldquo;the 5 S&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; for soothing babies with me before our son was born, and this was super helpful to me. But, in the last year, our son became a toddler, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to do, and I struggled. I tried to find resources for how to parent (and discipline, something I haven&amp;rsquo;t been very good at), and found that a simple idea from the authors of No Drama Discipline clicked with me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hey AERA, what&#39;s up with that?</title>
      <link>/posts/hey-aera-what-s-up-with-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/hey-aera-what-s-up-with-that/</guid>
      <description>I like the American Educational Research Association; it&amp;rsquo;s my professional home.
I was pretty surprised to see this letter, advocating against open access to educational research that is funded through federal agencies (i.e., the Institute of Educational Sciences, the National Science Foundation, etc.).
Inside Higher Ed has an article on AERA&amp;rsquo;s (and other professional organization&amp;rsquo;s) opposition.
Basically, this is wrong. I think AERA is on the wrong side of a trend - driven by access to information through the Internet - toward open access.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting a grip on using BibTeX with R Markdown documents</title>
      <link>/posts/using-bibtex-with-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/using-bibtex-with-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>I’m just beginning to learn BibTeX, which is, according to Wikipedia (2019), “reference management software for formatting lists of references”.
It is useful for publishing formats such as R Markdown documents and books created with bookdown, like the Data Science in Education Using R book.
I’m basically using this post to document what I’m learning.
Adding references I started with references, which are saved in plain text documents ending in .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The first, rough (rough!) draft of the (web-based) version of Data Science in Education Using R is available</title>
      <link>/posts/the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</guid>
      <description>The first, rough draft of the (web-based version) of the Data Science in Education Using R book written by Emily Bovee, Ryan Estrellado, Jesse Motstipak, me, and Isabella Velásquez is available from this URL: http://www.datascienceineducation.com/.
I mentioned this in an earlier post introducing the book: the publisher, Routledge, allowed us to stipulate that we retain the copyright for the web-based version, even after the book is published in print (and e-book) format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tiny (Shiny) app: How Many (MCMC) Cores?</title>
      <link>/posts/a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores/</guid>
      <description>Here is a tiny (Shiny) application to help with selecting the number of cores in the context of MCMC estimation.
How many cores? is here: https://jmichaelrosenberg.shinyapps.io/how-many-cores/
Here is a screenshot:
![](/post/2019-12-13-a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores_files/Screen Shot 2019-12-13 at 8.11.18 PM.png)
The source is here: https://github.com/jrosen48/how-many-cores</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R/R Studio from a (Pixel Slate) Chromebook</title>
      <link>/posts/using-r-r-studio-from-a-pixel-slate-chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/using-r-r-studio-from-a-pixel-slate-chromebook/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had a Pixel Slate Chromebook for a little while, and noticed in a recent update that it was possible to install Linux.
This was pretty easy to do (see here). After doing it (it took a few minutes to download Linux, but was otherwise super straightforward), I opened up the command line interface and saw this:
 There are a few things I know how to do through a command line interface; one is to list all of the files and directories available, so I ran the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research group website - Making data science count</title>
      <link>/posts/research-group-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/research-group-website/</guid>
      <description>I created a research group website, Making Data Science Count. I intend to use that website for updates on research projects and research-related updates, and this website for information about me (my teaching, CV, etc.).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking a break from social media</title>
      <link>/posts/taking-a-break-from-social-media-take-n/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/taking-a-break-from-social-media-take-n/</guid>
      <description>Since this past summer, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to moderate my use of social media. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried a number of strategies (like limiting the amount of time I spend each day), but none have been very effective, apart from a fairly dramatic step, deactivating my accounts, which was effective (until I got back on). While my accounts were deactivated, I missed keeping up with and being in touch with friends and family, but I found other ways to communciate (I actually had two phone calls!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It was a job posting on a mailing list, not a blog post on the NARST blog: A response to Mintzes</title>
      <link>/posts/it-was-a-job-posting-on-a-mailing-list-not-a-blog-post-on-the-narst-blog-a-response-to-mintzes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/it-was-a-job-posting-on-a-mailing-list-not-a-blog-post-on-the-narst-blog-a-response-to-mintzes/</guid>
      <description>Since mid-morning this past Friday, members of NARST have been discussing a post and a response to the organization&amp;rsquo;s mailing list.
I&amp;rsquo;ve written before about how I use my blog to communicate; this is an attempt to do that in the context of that discussion.
I&amp;rsquo;ll lay out my argument in advance, in part because it is simple:
Hazari shared a job post on a mailing list. It was not a blog post, and it certainly was not a blog post on the NARST blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R with 7th-grade science students</title>
      <link>/posts/using-r-with-7th-grade-science-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/using-r-with-7th-grade-science-students/</guid>
      <description>Sparked by a collaboration with Bodong Chen, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with a 7th-grade science teacher, Alex Edwards, at Tate&amp;rsquo;s School. We recently wrote about some of the take-aways from our work last year in a publication on &amp;ldquo;Tools and strategies for engaging students in analyzing and interpreting complex data sources.&amp;rdquo;
The article is going to be published in NSTA&amp;rsquo;s The Science Teacher journal (a pre-print of the article is here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at Middle Tennessee State University: Making Data Science Count</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</guid>
      <description>I was lucky to have the chance to present at the Middle Tennessee State University Math and Science Education Seminar Series.
Presentation My presentation was on Making data science count: Exploring the integration of data science into education.
A link to the presentation is here.
Workshop I also carried out a two-hour workshop on An introduction to data science in education using R. A repository for the workshop, including a link to slides, code, and data, is here: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pre-print probs - Some thoughts after posting a pre-print of an article</title>
      <link>/posts/pre-print-probs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/pre-print-probs/</guid>
      <description>I shared my grant proposal I wrote as a pre-print for a number of reasons:
 The not-very-proprietary nature of this project (with its focus on individual investigator development) I didn’t face any risk of unblinding the review process (as the NSF review process already is) I was the only author, and, so, I felt like there was less risk if I made a mistake: I was the one who would face the consequences!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources and ideas for engineers working on the design challenge of teaching elementary students about engineering</title>
      <link>/posts/resources-and-ideas-for-engineers-working-on-the-design-challenge-of-teaching-elementary-students-about-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/resources-and-ideas-for-engineers-working-on-the-design-challenge-of-teaching-elementary-students-about-engineering/</guid>
      <description>I have the opportunity to speak with Dr. Courtney Faber&amp;rsquo;s engineering service-learning course.
In this course, my understanding is that students tackle a design challenge. I was asked to come to class to speak for around 30-minutes around adapting and designing activities for an engineering after school program for elementary-aged students. So, the design challenge is to teach engineering to elementary students about engineering. Cool!
But, I don&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rsquo; have expertise in engineering or elementary education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Base group check-in questions</title>
      <link>/posts/base-group-check-in-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/base-group-check-in-questions/</guid>
      <description>Note. I am adding to this list throughout the Fall, 2019 semester!
Check-out/Exit ticket questions In many classes I teach, I assign students to base groups, groups of around three or four students who sit together (for most of the time) and &amp;ldquo;check-in&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;check-out&amp;rdquo; of class. The goal of base groups is to foster a kind of positive interdependence among students.
The check out questions are typically the same:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science education resources</title>
      <link>/posts/science-education-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/science-education-resources/</guid>
      <description>This list accumulated over the course of two classes and so I thought to start to archive resources here for posterity. Right now, these are unordered and have come from student recommendations and other sources:
Lessons and related resources  https://nextgenscience.org/resources/examples-quality-ngss-design (examples of NGSS-aligned units and lessons) http://datanuggets.org/ (datasets from scientists for use by learners) https://www.scientificamerican.com/education/bring-science-home/?page=1 (ideas and resources for investigations) https://ngss.nsta.org/Classroom-Resources.aspx (over 800 vetted lesson plans) https://www.ngssphenomena.com/ (phenomena for planning for NGSS-aligned teaching and learning) https://orise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responding to the President&#39;s comments </title>
      <link>/posts/responding-to-the-president-s-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/responding-to-the-president-s-comments/</guid>
      <description>I love Israel. My spouse can testify to this: After my last trip, with a group of doctoral students and faculty from Michigan State University, I talked about it (and especially the hummus) for months after. I want to go back. Just yesterday, I put mint I cut from my yard into my water bottle, like I saw Israelis do. I have a camp stove that I bought when I first traveled to Israel, when I was 18, that I used less than a month ago on a camping trip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New project on understanding the development of interest in computer science</title>
      <link>/posts/new-project-understanding-the-development-of-interest-in-computer-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-project-understanding-the-development-of-interest-in-computer-science/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to share that I was recently awarded funding to carry out a new project, Understanding the development of interest in computer science - an experience sampling approach. This is for the project I wrote about here.
Here&amp;rsquo;s an excerpt from NSF&amp;rsquo;s summary (a bit more is [here] (https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1937700&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false)):
 This project explores STEM interest development at the undergraduate level in computer science. It is a study of national importance that will focus on substantial differences in who pursues an interest, a major, or an occupation in computer science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts from submitting a grant proposal for the first time</title>
      <link>/posts/thoughts-from-submitting-a-grant-proposal-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/thoughts-from-submitting-a-grant-proposal-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>Note. I drafted this right after submitting the proposal but didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing it until now - almost two months later! I kept the language (around the timing) the same, as, there is still no better time than now to share&amp;ndash;though, earlier would have likely been better as the process was more fresh on my mind.
This past week, I submitted a proposal for a grant independently. I thought that there would be no better time than now to just down some thoughts, reflections, and perhaps a few lessons learned from the process of submitting a grant independently, as follows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Data Science in Education Using R (forthcoming 2020)</title>
      <link>/posts/introducing-data-science-in-education-using-r-forthcoming-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introducing-data-science-in-education-using-r-forthcoming-2020/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R I&amp;rsquo;m super excited to share that I will be writing a book, Data Science in Education Using R. The book will be published by Routledge sometime in mid-to-late 2020, and, importantly to us, Routledge agreed to let us keep the copyright for a web-version of the book, meaning that we will publish the entire contents of the book in an open and freely-available format (along with the print and e-book versions, which will be available for sale).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on the use of mixed effects models to the KnoxData group</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-the-use-of-mixed-effects-models-to-the-knoxdata-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-the-use-of-mixed-effects-models-to-the-knoxdata-group/</guid>
      <description>data-science-ish I presented yesterday on Data Science-Ish: The Use of Mixed Effects Models for Analyzing Complex Data at the KnoxData group.
Abstract Here is an abstract for the talk:
 Mixed effects (or multilevel) models are extensions of linear models (regressions) that are commonly used in experimental research and policy and evaluation contexts, but are less widely-used by data scientists. In this talk, I aim to introduce mixed effects model as a data science-ish statistical method that can be useful and is easy to estimate and interpret.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent publications on an online experiment platform, creatively focused technology fluency, and a computational science simulation</title>
      <link>/posts/recent-publications-a-virtual-experiment-platform-a-creatively-focused-technology-mindset-and-students-use-of-a-computationa-science-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/recent-publications-a-virtual-experiment-platform-a-creatively-focused-technology-mindset-and-students-use-of-a-computationa-science-simulation/</guid>
      <description>I realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about a few exciting manuscripts that I have co-authored or authored that have been published in the past year! The following pubications are on the design of virtual experiment platform, a creatively focused technology mindset, and students’ use of a computational science simulation, respectively.
 Blondel, D. V., Sansone, A., Rosenberg, J. M., Yang, B. W., Linennbrink-Garcia, L., &amp;amp; Schwarz-Bloom, R. D. (advance online publication). Development of an online experiment platform (Rex) for high school biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on &#39;Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education&#39;</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</guid>
      <description>This past week, I presented a workshop, Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education. for Educational Psychology and Educational Technology PhD students (and a few others) with Emily Bovee.
Here is the description:
 R is a freely-available, cross-platform, open-source programming language and statistical software environment that is well-suited to data analysis and data science, but, can have an high barrier to entry. This workshop provides an introduction to R in education, with a focus on developing a foundation in capabilities (and confidence!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little Bitty Steps Toward a More Open Education Research</title>
      <link>/posts/little-bitty-steps-toward-more-open-educational-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/little-bitty-steps-toward-more-open-educational-research/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of productive discussion around open education research (or science).
Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed some examples of what I think are good open education research.
Though I think of these as good examples and models for the rest of us to follow, I think some of them are not always appreciated as such. This matters because open education research can then seem like something that is not relevant or too onerous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at AERA 2019 - Understanding changes in interest in STEM, student engagement profiles in science, and transparent and reproducible research</title>
      <link>/posts/presentations-at-aera-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentations-at-aera-2019/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to be presenting this week (and early next week) on some ongoing work at the American Educational Research Association (AERA) 2019 Annual Meeting in Toronto, Canada.
Predictors of Momentary Student Engagement Profiles in High School Science Classrooms Sat, April 6, 10:25 to 11:55am, Sheraton Centre Toronto Hotel, Second Floor, Provincial Ballroom North
 Schell, M. J., Beymer, P. N. Albert, K. M., Rosenberg, J. M., &amp;amp; Schmidt, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at NARST 2019 - An exploration of NGSSchat through social network analysis</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-at-narst-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-at-narst-2019/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Reid presented An exploration of #NGSSchat through social network analysis on behalf of myself and our co-authors at the NARST 2019 conference (in Baltimore, MD).
The presentation is available here. A repository with the code to reproduce the analysis presented at NARST, as well as a copy of our in-progress paper, is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on &#39;Making Sense of Recent Advances in the TPACK Framework&#39; at the English International Congress (at UTN in Ibarra, Ecuador)</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-making-sense-of-recent-advances-in-the-tpack-framework-at-the-english-international-congress-at-utn-in-ibarra-ecuador/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-making-sense-of-recent-advances-in-the-tpack-framework-at-the-english-international-congress-at-utn-in-ibarra-ecuador/</guid>
      <description>I had the opportunity to present at the English International Congress at the Universidad Tecnical de Norte in Ibarra, Ecuador.
Presenting at the Congress was a great, fun experience and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the opportunity.
Resources My presentation was on Making Sense of Recent Advances in the Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge Framework and is available here.
The special issue on TPCK/TPACK Research and Development: Past, Present, and Future Directions that I was involved in as a guest editor is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on engaging students in science at the ‘Crossing Boundaries for STEM Education’ regional meeting and mini-conference</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-engaging-students-in-science-at-the-crossing-boundaries-for-stem-education-regional-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-engaging-students-in-science-at-the-crossing-boundaries-for-stem-education-regional-meeting/</guid>
      <description>I was excited to have the opportunity to present on Engaging students in science: Findings from an experience sampling method approach at the East TN STEM Hub &amp;lsquo;Crossing Boundaries for STEM Education&amp;rsquo; regional meeting and mini-conference. I liked presenting there, alongside colleagues in biology, engineering, computer science, and my home department at UTK. It reminded me of one of my favorite events at Michigan State University&amp;ndash;the Create for STEM mini-conference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on The Role of the Twitter Hashtag #NGSSchat in the Context of Science Education Reform Efforts at ASTE 2019</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-on-the-role-of-the-twitter-hashtag-ngsschat-in-the-context-of-science-education-reform-efforts-at-aste-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-on-the-role-of-the-twitter-hashtag-ngsschat-in-the-context-of-science-education-reform-efforts-at-aste-2019/</guid>
      <description>With Joshua Reid, Matthew Koehler, Christian Fischer, and T.J. McKenna, I presented on The Role of the Twitter Hashtag #NGSSchat in the Context of Science Education Reform Efforts at ASTE 2019.
 The presentation is here: https://joshuamrosenberg.com/aste-19.html And a pre-print and link to the data (and code for the analysis and a whole lot more) is here: https://osf.io/9ex7k/  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a CV in markdown so it can be rendered as HTML, a PDF, and a Word document</title>
      <link>/posts/creating-a-cv-while-using-blogdown-pdf-html-and-word-doc-oh-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/creating-a-cv-while-using-blogdown-pdf-html-and-word-doc-oh-my/</guid>
      <description>My goal: To write a CV in one format and in a way so that it can be rendered in multiple formats I have been trying to write my CV once and have it be displayed/rendered as HTML (for this website), a PDF (for sharing), and a Word document (also for sharing - as some folks require it to be in this format).
I have something that seems to work and so thought I would share what I did as a first attempt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on Data Science Education Dilemmas (and Opportunities)</title>
      <link>/posts/presentation-data-science-education-dilemmas-and-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/presentation-data-science-education-dilemmas-and-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>I had the opportunity to present on Data Science Education Dilemmas (and Opportunities) to STEM Education faculty at UT. It was a short, informal presentation, but served as a chance to pull together some ideas.
A link to the presentation is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R Markdown and papaja with a LaTeX class to submit a conference proposal: A few notes</title>
      <link>/posts/using-r-markdown-with-a-latex-class-a-few-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/using-r-markdown-with-a-latex-class-a-few-notes/</guid>
      <description>With my colleagues Emily Bovee (who had the idea for the project and is the first author) and John Ranellucci, I worked on a conference proposal for a conference that provided either a Word Document template or a LaTeX class. Since I had just used (that’s a generous way to put it - I really had struggled through it) LaTeX, I proposed that we see whether we could (continue to) use R and R Markdown, which we used to analyze the data, to prepare the manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Modeling&#39; science teaching and learning - a few notes on the first day of class</title>
      <link>/posts/a-few-notes-on-the-first-day-of-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/a-few-notes-on-the-first-day-of-class/</guid>
      <description>My first day of class (at UTK) was last week. I was excited that the first day went well; it was a good start to teaching in a new setting (and to teaching a class that is new - to me). Like anyone in my position, I spent a lot of time thinking about the first class. Some notes here in the case that others might find them relevant/at all useful:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A quick introduction and tutorial on a cool social network analysis model for influence</title>
      <link>/posts/social-network-analysis-model-for-influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/social-network-analysis-model-for-influence/</guid>
      <description>Social network is increasingly common in education (Sweet, 2016). Very often, social network analysis is used to create sociograms, or depictions of a network. I did this in a paper I recently co-authored (here is a pre-print), we worked hard to create this figure:

Such figures (we thought–and I think) look nice and they are often useful for understanding the characteristics of a network and the relations that are part of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted? An update!</title>
      <link>/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</guid>
      <description>In August of last year, I wrote a post that involved looking at when educational psychology jobs (mostly, but not only, academic jobs or those related to research and teaching) were posted to the excellent Ed Psych Jobs website. As that post made (in part) the (anticipated) point that most jobs were posted in September (in which 16% of jobs were posted there) and October (14%) (followed by August, with 11%), I thought that it may be helpful to see how accurate that was over the past year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of a data visualization (made with ggplot2)</title>
      <link>/posts/an-evolving-data-visualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/an-evolving-data-visualization/</guid>
      <description>Last summer, I taught the MAET Year 2 Summer Cohort with Danah Henriksen. After teaching the class, Danah realized she had taught five cohorts of (awesome) students and that we had some information available from pre- and post-course self-reported surveys to understand how students grew in terms of their confidence in using different educational (and other) technologies.
That research idea evolved into a study with Rohit Mehta that involved, among other findings, a visualization of average pre-post values for specific technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My dissertation defense (and some links to resources)</title>
      <link>/posts/an-open-ish-dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/an-open-ish-dissertation/</guid>
      <description>I am defending my dissertation to my committee tomorrow. I have tried to make it as open as possible. One way I have done this is writing and then saving the manuscript (and code for the analysis) in a public place (here).
That repository is on GitHub and includes a PDF of my dissertation and the R Markdown files used to generate it. It also includes the PowerPoint presentation for tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s defense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning R (for data analysis and data science): Where to start</title>
      <link>/posts/learning-r-where-to-start-crowdsourced-recommendations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/learning-r-where-to-start-crowdsourced-recommendations/</guid>
      <description>A friend of a friend (also in educational research) posted that he was interested in learning R.
I had a couple of ideas but knew that others might have better ideas. So, I posted (on Twitter) looking for recommendations and received some excellent talks, links, and other resources.
Here they are, in Tweet form (you may have to click on the links in tweets to see some of the resources and content)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some books, NAP reports, and other newer resources related to science education</title>
      <link>/posts/some-resources-on-science-teaching-and-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/some-resources-on-science-teaching-and-learning/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ll be starting a position in STEM Education at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, beginning this August. As part of this position, I&amp;rsquo;ll teach science teaching methods (and science and STEM education research-related) courses. Hearing about the first course I&amp;rsquo;ll teach sparked me to gather these.
So, this is a loosely-organized collection of some resources&amp;ndash;especially some new(er) books and National Academies Press (NAP) reports&amp;ndash;related to science teaching and learning. I leave &amp;ldquo;oldies but goodies&amp;rdquo;, like Taking Science to School (2007), the Framework for K-12 Science Education (2012), and America&amp;rsquo;s Lab Report (2006) for example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some ideas about getting started bike commuting </title>
      <link>/posts/getting-started-bike-commuting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/getting-started-bike-commuting/</guid>
      <description>This post includes a few things about getting started bike commuting. The thesis is something like: If you have a bike and a safe route, you can probably commute right away, and then add-on other things (like a rack, fenders, or different tires) over time.
The most important thing - a safe route! The most important thing is a safe route! In my experience, roads with bike lanes, or&amp;ndash;even better&amp;ndash;greenways (for runners, walkers, and bikers) are best, followed by neighborhood roads, followed by city roads with street parking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AERA 2018 presentation: Patterns of engagement in a flipped undergraduate class (slides, paper, &amp; code)</title>
      <link>/posts/aera-presentation-patterns-of-engagement-in-a-flipped-undergraduate-class-antecedents-and-outcomes-information-slides-paper-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/aera-presentation-patterns-of-engagement-in-a-flipped-undergraduate-class-antecedents-and-outcomes-information-slides-paper-code/</guid>
      <description>I’m presenting a second paper at AERA on patterns of (outside of class) engagement in a flipped undergraduate class with my colleagues You-kyung Lee, Kristy Robinson, John Ranellucci, Cary Roseth, and Lisa Linnenbrink-Garcia. The presentation is at 8:15 am (Sunday, 4/15) in the Millenium Broadway Hotel (Room 7.04) and is on a session on emotions, engagement, and technology (with some very interesting papers presented by co-presenters in the session!).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AERA 2018 presentation: How engagement during out-of-school STEM programs promotes the development of interest (slides, paper, &amp; code)</title>
      <link>/posts/aera-presentation-how-engagement-during-out-of-school-stem-programs-promotes-the-development-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/aera-presentation-how-engagement-during-out-of-school-stem-programs-promotes-the-development-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to present a paper on how engagement during out-of-school STEM programs promotes youths’ development of interest with my co-authors Patrick Beymer and Jennifer Schmidt.
The paper is in the session “Data-Intensive Approaches to Studying Engagement in Education: Exploring Their Current Potential”. My co-presenters in the session include Eric Weibe and James Creager, Sophia Hooper, Erica Patall, Ariana Vasquez, Keenan Pituch, and Rebecca Steingut, and Eric Poitas, Tenzin Doleck, Lingyun Huang, Shan Li, &amp;amp; Susanne Lajoie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An R package for sensitivity analysis (konfound)</title>
      <link>/posts/an-r-package-for-sensitivity-analysis-konfound/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/an-r-package-for-sensitivity-analysis-konfound/</guid>
      <description>knitr::opts_chunk$set( comment = &amp;quot;#&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, collapse = TRUE ) With Ran Xu and Ken Frank, I have worked on a Shiny interactive web application for sensitivity analysis as well as an R package for carrying out sensitivity analysis using R.
That R package is now available on CRAN! A link to the CRAN page for it is here and the website for the package is here.
Here is the description:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Explorations in Markov Chain Monte Carlo - comparing results from MCMCglmm and lme4</title>
      <link>/posts/explorations-in-markov-chain-monte-carlo-mcmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/explorations-in-markov-chain-monte-carlo-mcmc/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run. If you run this code, parts may not work (depending upon the version of the packages used and, potentially, other factors).
Introduction I’ve been interested in Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) for a little while, in part because of a paper by Tom Houslay and Alastair Wilson (2017) that shows how using output from models the way I have been can lead to results that overstate the impact of effects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the top rail-trails in each state using mixed effects models</title>
      <link>/posts/find-the-top-rail-trails-in-each-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/find-the-top-rail-trails-in-each-state/</guid>
      <description>Outside of education, one of my interests is cycling, and one of my favorite ways to cycle is on rail-trails, pathways and greenways that are converted from former railroad tracks.
In a side-project (and because the data source can be used for teaching and learning about complex, nested data), I collected information from the TrailLink website. I’ve blogged about this data here and here to find out what the best rail-trails in Michigan are and to find out what the characteristics of the best rail-trails are, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing tidyLPA (an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis)</title>
      <link>/posts/introducing-tidylpa-an-r-package-for-carrying-out-latent-profile-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introducing-tidylpa-an-r-package-for-carrying-out-latent-profile-analysis/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to introduce tidyLPA, an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA). This is the result of a collaborative project with Jennifer Schmidt, Patrick Beymer, and Rebecca Steingut, and is the result of a long period of learning about cluster analysis (see here) and, recently, model-based cluster analysis. Here, I introduce and describe LPA as a particular type of model-based cluster analysis.
Note: This post has been updated to reflect the latest version of tidyLPA</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming presentations at AERA, SITE, and NARST</title>
      <link>/posts/upcoming-presentations-at-aera-and-narst/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/upcoming-presentations-at-aera-and-narst/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to present (or contribute to presentations) associated with a number of ongoing projects at the AERA, SITE, and NARST conferences later this semester. If you are at one of the conferences (or presentations) and would like to get in touch, please do! Here are the titles and some other information for the presentations:
Beymer, P. N., Rosenberg, J.M., &amp;amp; Schmidt, J. A. (2018, April). Investigating the effects of interest and choice: An experience sampling approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny interactive web application to quantify how robust inferences are to potential sources of bias (sensitivity analysis)</title>
      <link>/posts/a-shiny-interactive-web-application-to-quantify-how-robust-inferences-are-to-potential-sources-of-bias-sensitivity-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/a-shiny-interactive-web-application-to-quantify-how-robust-inferences-are-to-potential-sources-of-bias-sensitivity-analysis/</guid>
      <description>As part of a revise and resubmit decision for a paper (that was just accepted to the Journal of Youth and Adolescence (pre-print here)), we (Patrick Beymer, Jennifer Schmidt, and I) were asked by the editor to carry out sensitivity analysis for findings. Our understanding was that, in this context, sensitivity analysis means one of two things - or both:
 How results hold up under different specfications of an analyses How much bias would have to be present to invalidate an inference  Over the past year or so, I had learned about sensitivity analysis from a class and then work with Ken Frank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outcomes from a self-generated utility value intervention in science (in IJER)</title>
      <link>/posts/new-article-on-a-utility-value-intervention-in-ijer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/new-article-on-a-utility-value-intervention-in-ijer/</guid>
      <description>The Scientific Practices project, was focused on engaging middle school students in scientific and engineering practices (such as developing and using models, constructing explanations of phenomena, and analyzing and interpreting data). As part of this longitudinal project, we carried out field experiments to understand the impact of specific features of the curriculum.
In this paper published in the International Journal of Educational Research with Mete Akcaoglu, John Ranellucci, Christina Schwarz, and I examined whether asking students to generate ideas about how what they were learning about could be useful in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modifying an R function to iterate (using purrr) and use non-standard evaluation (using rlang)</title>
      <link>/posts/modifying-an-r-function-to-use-non-standard-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/modifying-an-r-function-to-use-non-standard-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run.
Background Research in classrooms and schools can be complex because of all of the factors that matter. A question that often comes up when we say that we observed some pattern in data is, but did you control for X?
In the context of working on an approach to find out how impactful an omitted variable would need to be to invalidate an inference, we had to modify a function that worked for a single sensitivity analysis to work for many and to be easier to use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New post on engaging students in “data practices” in online science classes (in the MVLRI Research, Policy, Innovation &amp; Networks blog)</title>
      <link>/posts/mvlri-blog-post-on-data-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/mvlri-blog-post-on-data-practices/</guid>
      <description>I have worked to design activities for students to work with authentic data sources in their science classes through a collaboration with Michigan Virtual School and the Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute.
As a part of this project, which was supported by their dissertation research fellowship, I hosted a webinar. I also wrote a post for the Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute Blog: Research, Policy, Innovation &amp;amp; Networks blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of &#39;What’s Worth Teaching: Rethinking Curriculum in the Age of Technology&#39; in Teachers College Record</title>
      <link>/posts/review-of-what-s-worth-teaching-rethinking-curriculum-in-the-age-of-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/review-of-what-s-worth-teaching-rethinking-curriculum-in-the-age-of-technology/</guid>
      <description>I was recently requested to submit a review with Charles Logan for the book What’s Worth Teaching: Rethinking Curriculum in the Age of Technology by the incredible scholar Allan Collins. A link to the review and book on the Teachers College Record website here. A pre-print of our review is also available here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two data packages: Rail-trails and an assessment of student achievement</title>
      <link>/posts/two-open-datasets-rail-trails-and-an-assessment-of-student-achievement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/two-open-datasets-rail-trails-and-an-assessment-of-student-achievement/</guid>
      <description>Because of interest and the need for better examples (for teaching and for use in tools under-development), such as prcr and tidyLPA, I worked to create two data packages, data easily available through an R package.
A benefit of the data being in an R package is that it is even easier to access than other formats (in R): Just load the name of the package and type the name of the data frame, or, if the data is included as built-in data in another package (one that is loaded), just type the name of the data frame.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MVLRI webinar on engaging students in authentic &#39;data practices&#39; in online science classes</title>
      <link>/posts/mvlri-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/mvlri-webinar/</guid>
      <description>I will be hosting a webinar on Engaging students in authentic “data practices” in online science classes with Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute, the research organization associated with Michigan’s state-wide online school. The webinar is today (10/18) at 2pm EDT and is available via https://connect.mivu.org/mvlri
Here is a bit more information on the webinar:
 Not only in science and science education but also our everyday lives, data are powerful, but opportunities for students to think of and with data as part of their learning are limited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with &#39;open science&#39; through blogging</title>
      <link>/posts/getting-started-with-open-science-through-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/getting-started-with-open-science-through-blogging/</guid>
      <description>Through a few different projects and people (such as SIPS and rOpenSci and conversations with friends / colleagues both online and offline), I have been exposed to the idea of open science.
I’m actually going to punt for the moment. Here’s a definition that sounds about right to me:
 Open science is the movement to make scientific research, data and dissemination accessible to all levels of an inquiring society, amateur or professional.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A person-in-context approach to student engagement in science (article in JRST)</title>
      <link>/posts/a-person-in-context-approach-to-student-engagement-in-science-article-in-jrst/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/a-person-in-context-approach-to-student-engagement-in-science-article-in-jrst/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few years, I have worked with Jennifer Schmidt and Patrick Beymer to explore student engagement in science using the Experience Sampling Method (ESM). Most recently, we used what scholars have referred to as a “person-in-context” approach, using both ESM and a person-oriented approach.
A figure is helpful for conveying how the person-oriented approach can be used to find common momentary engagement profiles:
We examine how common these profiles are in laboratory activities and on the basis of students’ ability to make choices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few podcasts I always listen to</title>
      <link>/posts/podcasts-i-do-not-miss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/podcasts-i-do-not-miss/</guid>
      <description>Between commuting by bicycle and working, I listen to a lot of podcasts. I listen to podcasts to learn something new, keep up with the news, and, occasionally, hear other viewpoints. I thought it would be worth sharing a few that I (almost) never miss downloading and listening to, especially those that others may not regularly hear about, are new, or are sort of niche in terms of the audience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using MPlus from R with MPlusAutomation</title>
      <link>/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run.
According to the MPlus website, the R package MPlusAutomation serves three purposes:
Creating related groups of models Running batches Extracting and tabulating model parameters and test statistics.  Because modeling involves comparing related models, (partially) automating these is compelling. It can make it easier to use model results in subsequent analyses and can cut down on copy and pasting output or results between programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A first pass at Latent Profile Analysis using MCLUST (in R)</title>
      <link>/posts/lpa-in-r-using-mclust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/lpa-in-r-using-mclust/</guid>
      <description>Note - an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA): tidyLPA Since writing this post, I have worked with colleagues to release an R package to carry out the analysis. The package is tidyLPA and is described in the following sections, through the “Original Post” header below which is the beginning of the original post.
Introduction Latent Profile Analysis (LPA) is a statistical modeling approach for estimating distinct profiles, or groups, of variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing estimates and their standard errors from mixed effects and linear models</title>
      <link>/posts/comparing-mixed-effects-and-linear-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/comparing-mixed-effects-and-linear-models/</guid>
      <description>Some background One reason to use mixed effects models is that they help to account for data with a complex structure, such as multiple responses (to questions, for example) from the same people, students grouped into classes, and measures collected over time. Often, the way they account for these complex structures is in terms of reducing their bias, which has to do with when a model comes up with an estimate that is off - too large, too small, or maybe too certain (or uncertain) relative to the true value of the thing that is estimated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted?</title>
      <link>/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</guid>
      <description>Division 15 of the American Psychological Association sponsors the Ed Psych Jobs website, which is an excellent resource for Ed Psych job seekers. I thought it would possibly be helpful to see when jobs were posted in the past in order to have a better idea about when jobs may be posted this year.
Ed Psych Jobs, Robots (.txt), and paths_allowed, oh my As this project involves a bit of web-scraping, I first checked the robots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using characteristics of rail-trails to predict how they are rated</title>
      <link>/posts/characteristics-of-rail-trails/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/characteristics-of-rail-trails/</guid>
      <description>Catching up I wrote a blog post (one that, to be honest, I liked a lot) on what the best rail-trails are in Michigan (here). A friend and colleague at MSU, Andy, noticed that paved trails seemed to be rated higher, and this as well as my cfriend and colleague Kristy’s comment about how we can use the output of the the previous post sparked my curiosity in trying to figure out what characteristics predict how highly (or not highly) rated trails are.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the best rail-trails in Michigan?</title>
      <link>/posts/michigan-rail-trails-and-pathways-through-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/michigan-rail-trails-and-pathways-through-data/</guid>
      <description>Background I was curious about what rail trails were the best in Michigan, and so to figure out an answer, I checked out the TrailLink website, sponsored by the Rails-to-Trails Conservancy. I had just purchased a copy of their book Rail-Trails Michigan and Wisconsin, and wanted to see whether I could learn more from the website.
To start, I checked whether they had a way to access the reviews on the site through an API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How many groups of Star Wars characters are there? R-squared and cross-validation approaches</title>
      <link>/posts/how-many-groups-of-star-wars-characters-are-there-r-squared-and-cross-validation-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/how-many-groups-of-star-wars-characters-are-there-r-squared-and-cross-validation-approaches/</guid>
      <description>Background How many groups, or types, of Star Wars characters are there? I’ve been wanting to use the starwars dataset built-in to the dplyr package, and at the same time, have been working hard on an R package to carry out an analysis suited to doing this. Part of the challenge of using the approach in this R package is determining how groups groups there are.
Many approaches (Latent Profile Analysis, for example) use Maximum Likelihood estimation (while the approach I’ve developed uses a two-step cluster analysis based around the geometric (and algebraic) idea of “distance”, or how close (similar) observations are).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24 months on two wheels</title>
      <link>/posts/24-months-on-two-wheels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/24-months-on-two-wheels/</guid>
      <description>Around two years ago, I was fortunate to not have to work in the summer: I had a research fellowship from May - August through the College of Education at MSU.
As a result, I didn’t buy a parking pass for the summer. I still came in to campus, but since I didn’t have any official, regularly-scheduled meetings, I thought I could bike in when I needed to. I had biked to campus before, so I was familiar with the route and where I would park my bike, but I didn’t regularly commute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>prcr update</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-05-17-prcr-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 13:48:00 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-05-17-prcr-update/</guid>
      <description>The R package for person-oriented analysis (prcr) is updated (it’s now version 0.1.4).
In particular, it was not clear how to use the profile assignments (i.e., what cluster each response is in) in subsequent analyses. So, the update now returns two different representations of the profile assignments, or which profile is associated with each observation: a) the original “data.frame” with the profile assignment added in one variable and b) the original “data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on an Introduction to R for Data Analysis</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-04-15-introduction-to-r-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 11:54:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-04-15-introduction-to-r-presentation/</guid>
      <description>I had an opportunity to present on an Introduction to R for Data Analysis to the School of Criminal Justice (at MSU).
The presentation is organized into five sections:
Background Wrangling, Plotting, and Modeling Essential Functionality Advanced Functionality Additional Resources  A link to the presentation is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Common Core and NGSS are not on the news</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 16:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</guid>
      <description>How often are curricular standards mentioned on TV news? With my friend Patrick, I was curious about using the newsflash package for something education-related. We came up with the idea of looking at mentions of the Common Core State Standards (for Mathematics and English Language Arts / Literacy) and the Next Generation Science Standards (for Science and Engineering).
 On broadcast channels We first looked at mentions across ABC, CBS, FOX, NBC, and PBS (the way newsflash works is to keyword search the closed captioning streams from the Internet Archive’s Television News Archive):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What the world is data science education? Looking back on #dsetonline</title>
      <link>/posts/what-the-world-is-data-science-education-looking-back-on-dsetonline/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/what-the-world-is-data-science-education-looking-back-on-dsetonline/</guid>
      <description>DSET A few weeks ago, I was fortunate to attend the Data Science Educational Technology (DSET) conference.
The goal for the conference was to kickstart data science education and to explore an educational technology, Concord Consortium’s Common Online Data Analysis Platform. What’s the big idea about data science education? To me, it’s a recognition that data is power, and that through asking questions, collecting and creating data, analyzing and modeling data, and making sense of and communicating what is going on can be empowering to learners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Internet Archive&#39;s Television News Archive and Newsflash</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-03-11-rock-climbing-internet-television-news-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 01:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-03-11-rock-climbing-internet-television-news-archive/</guid>
      <description>Background The Internet Archive’s Television News Archive is a cool way to search closed captions from TV shows.
Here’s a bit more information on it:
 The Internet Archive’s Television News Archive, GDELT’s Television Explorer allows you to keyword search the closed captioning streams of the Archive’s 6 years of American television news and explore macro-level trends in how America’s television news is shaping the conversation around key societal issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the flu really worse this year? Comparing the (ongoing) 2016-17 and 2015-16 flu seasons</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-02-28-comparing-cdc-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 09:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-02-28-comparing-cdc-data/</guid>
      <description>Background I was sick last week, and I think I might have had a mild case of the flu. Since it seems like a lot of people have been sick, I was curious whether the flu was really worse this year than last… and since the CDC makes the data available for each year, I put the data together and created a GIF. This project is just a first attempt but the code (it’s in R) is available in a GitHub repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>prcr: An R Package for Person-Centered Analysis</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-02-17-introducing-prcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 16:59:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-02-17-introducing-prcr/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to share that prcr (0.1.0), an R package for person-centered analysis, is now available on CRAN via install.packages(&amp;quot;prcr&amp;quot;).
Person-centered analyses focus on clusters, or profiles, of observations, and their change over time or differences across factors.
The package is designed to be “low threshold but high ceiling”, in that you can do all of the analysis with one function, create_profiles(df, n_clusters), where dfis a data.frame of the variables to cluster, and n_clusters is the specified number of clusters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much do we spend weekly on Groceries? Figuring out using R and Mint (Updated)</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-01-17-exploring-mint-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 05:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-01-17-exploring-mint-r/</guid>
      <description>We started using Mint to keep track of our spending. One of the best features of Mint is the ability to see past patterns of spending (and to use that information to not spend quite as much on, well, coffee, and for those who know me well, sandwiches from Woody’s Oasis).
I listened to an episode of the Not So Standard Deviations, in which the hosts Peng and Parker discussed using spreadsheets and R to keep track of information for taxes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing clustRcompaR v.0.1.0</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-01-07-clustrcompar-0.1.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 10:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-01-07-clustrcompar-0.1.0/</guid>
      <description>Alex Lishinski and I worked on an R package over the last year or so. We are excited that it’s now available on CRAN.
You can install the package using install.packages(&#39;clustRcompaR&#39;) (only needed first time) and load it (more on its two functions below) using library(clustRcompaR).
Here’s a description:
 Provides an interface to perform cluster analysis on a corpus of text. Interfaces to Quanteda to assemble text corpuses easily.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordpress Archive</title>
      <link>/posts/2017-01-07-wordpress-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 09:50:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2017-01-07-wordpress-archive/</guid>
      <description>I moved my Wordpress blog to Wordpress.com as an archive and so I would not need to pay to maintain the self-hosted site. The link is here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An examination of students</title>
      <link>/posts/20160415-an-examination-of-students-epistemic-considerations-with-an-automated-approach-at-narst2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 09:31:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20160415-an-examination-of-students-epistemic-considerations-with-an-automated-approach-at-narst2016/</guid>
      <description> An examination of students With Christina Schwarz, I presented on an examination of students’ epistemic considerations with an automated approach at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching Annual International Conference. Slides from the presentation are available here (PDF).
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education</title>
      <link>/posts/20160323-presentation-on-an-introduction-to-r-for-programming-and-statistical-analysis-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 08:10:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20160323-presentation-on-an-introduction-to-r-for-programming-and-statistical-analysis-in-education/</guid>
      <description> Presentation on an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education I had the opportunity to present an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education on the invitation of my colleague Mete Akcaoglu at Georgia Southern University’s College of Education. The presentation is available here.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at</title>
      <link>/posts/20160322-presentation-on-state-educational-twitter-hashtags-at-siteconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 23:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20160322-presentation-on-state-educational-twitter-hashtags-at-siteconf/</guid>
      <description> Presentation on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at #siteconf With Matthew Koehler, Mete Akcaoglu, Spencer Greenhalgh, and Erica Hamilton, I presented on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at the Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education conference. We created an interactive web application to share the findings using R and Shiny that is available here. If you check it out then please let us know what you think.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides for What Teachers and Researchers Discuss at Science Education Conferences at</title>
      <link>/posts/20151106-slides-for-what-teachers-and-researchers-discuss-at-science-education-conferences-at-aect15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 15:27:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20151106-slides-for-what-teachers-and-researchers-discuss-at-science-education-conferences-at-aect15/</guid>
      <description> Slides for What Teachers and Researchers Discuss at Science Education Conferences at #AECT15 Slides for my presentation at AECT in the graduate student panel discussion on learning analytics on what teachers and researchers discuss at science education conferences are available here (in a Google Presentation).
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides for An Examination of State Educational Twitter Hashtags at</title>
      <link>/posts/20151106-slides-for-an-examination-of-state-educational-twitter-hashtags/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 10:03:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20151106-slides-for-an-examination-of-state-educational-twitter-hashtags/</guid>
      <description> Slides for An Examination of State Educational Twitter Hashtags at #AECT15 Slides for my presentation with Meta Akcaoglu, Erica Hamilton, Spencer Greenhalgh, and Matthew Koehler at AECT on State Educational Twitter Hashtags are available here (in a Google Presentation).
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education</title>
      <link>/posts/20150804-first-article-in-jrte/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 19:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/20150804-first-article-in-jrte/</guid>
      <description>New article in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education My first article (in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education, JRTE) by me and Matthew J. Koehler is available as an advance online publication. If you’re interested in TPACK and want to see what I’ve been up to, then please check it out (or send me an email so I can send a copy your way).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/posts/2019-12-14-the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-12-14-the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code and Software</title>
      <link>/code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/</guid>
      <description>Code and Software I share most of my in-development code and code related to analyses on GitHub: https://github.com/jrosen48. Code and software associated with some example projects is below.
R packages on Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) Rosenberg, J. M., van Lissa, C. J., Beymer, P. N., Anderson, D. J., Schell, M. J. &amp;amp; Schmidt, J. A. (2019). tidyLPA: Easily carry out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA) using open-source or commercial software [R package].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home</title>
      <link>/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/</guid>
      <description>Welcome! I am an Assistant Professor of STEM Education at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking to get in touch by email, please contact me at jmrosenberg [at] UTK [dot] edu.
Upcoming Presentations
 Workshop on Developing Transparent and Reproducible Research with R at the American Educational Research Association meeting in Toronto, Canada on Sunday, April 7, 2019 - 8:00 am - 12:00 pm (register here; more info. here) Presentations at the American Educational Research Association meeting (April 4-9, Toronto, Canada)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joshua M. Rosenberg</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>PDF version: 
Curriculum Vitae Contents  Contact Information Research Interests Education Professional Experience Grants Fellowships and Awards Publications  Book Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles Book Chapters Conference Proceedings Papers Editor-Reviewed Publications Pre-Prints and Unpublished Manuscript  Presentations  Peer-Reviewed Conference Presentations Invited Talks Other Presentations Workshops  Outreach Teaching Service Software Miscellaneous    Contact Information Assistant Professor, STEM Education
Department of Theory and Practice in Teacher Education</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/</guid>
      <description>Research Research Statement My research statement is available here.
Publications and Other Products Visit this page here for information about and links to pre-prints and other resources associated with publications (peer-reviewed journal articles, book chapters, and conference proceedings) and other products (R packages and simulations for learners).
National Science Foundation-funded projects PI, Understanding the development of interest in computer science: An experience sampling approach ($346,688). National Science Foundation. (National Science Foundation Grant No.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sundry</title>
      <link>/sundry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sundry/</guid>
      <description>Google Scholar BiBTeX Google Scholar BiBTeX: https://scholar.googleusercontent.com/citations?view_op=export_citations&amp;amp;user=nxVowRQAAAAJ&amp;amp;citsig=AMD79ooAAAAAXgJl-er18rHvDjfeA4IfaQKVbKm5ceFk&amp;amp;hl=en
My Packages my_packages &amp;lt;- tibble::tribble( ~Package, &amp;ldquo;abind&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;acepack&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;acs&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ada&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;afex&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;anytime&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;apaTables&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ape&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;arm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;AsioHeaders&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;askpass&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;assertthat&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;attempt&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;audio&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;backports&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;base&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;base64enc&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bayesplot&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bayestestR&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;beepr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;beeswarm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;BH&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bibtex&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bit&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bit64&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bitops&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;blob&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;blogdown&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bookdown&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;boot&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;brew&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bridgesampling&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;brms&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Brobdingnag&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;broom&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;broom.mixed&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bupaR&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;BWStest&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;callr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;carData&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;caret&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;caTools&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;CCA&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;CCP&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cellranger&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;checkmate&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;choroplethr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;choroplethrMaps&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;citr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;class&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;classInt&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cli&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;clipr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;clisymbols&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cluster&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cmm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;coda&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;codetools&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;coin&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;colorspace&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;colourpicker&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;commonmark&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;compiler&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;compute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>My teaching statement is available here
This page contains: a list of courses I have taught, including course descriptions and links to course websites (when available); information on workshops and outreach.
TPTE 110/TPTE 120 (Combo)  Step 1 and Step 2 are highly collaborative, hands-on classes in which you learn about teaching through observation, practice, and professional mentoring. Each course consists of (a) classes at UTK and (b) field experiences at a local elementary or middle school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology I use</title>
      <link>/tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tech/</guid>
      <description>Technology I Use Web  The Hugo static website generator The xmin theme for Hugo A GitHub repository for the website Netlify to render the website and host the files  I use the same tools for my Making Data Science Count research group website, except I use the academic theme for Hugo.
Communication  Slack Keybase (for some communication; it&amp;rsquo;s purported to be more secure and private than Slack) Outlook on my personal computer for email Fantastical for calendar (paid)  Writing and editing  Sublime text editor (not paid, but can be) Evernote for taking notes and for saving PDFs to read across devices (paid) Google Docs Microsoft Word (paid) R Markdown for writing reports LaTeX and BibTeX for writing particular documents Mendeley for references Boomerang for Outlook to schedule emails to arrive in bulk every two hours  Coding and data analysis  R Studio R with these packages git/GitHub Anaconda Python distribution  Keeping track  Todoist for managing tasks (paid) Trello for keeping track of projects Pocket Casts for subscribing to podcasts Pocket for keeping track of articles/webpages Feedly RSS reader  Miscellaneous  Dark Sky weather app (paid) 1 Password password manager (paid) RescueTime time tracker (paid)  Hardware  Android phone Mac computer  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>