<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A brief presentation for the AERA Div C New Faculty Mentoring Program</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/04/10/a-brief-presentation-for-the-aera-div-c-new-faculty-mentoring-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/04/10/a-brief-presentation-for-the-aera-div-c-new-faculty-mentoring-program/</guid>
      <description>I am (virtually) sharing a brief presentation at the American Educational Research Association (AERA), Division C (Learning &amp;amp; Instruction) New Faculty Mentoring Program.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here: https://tiny.utk.edu/dftD5</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meeting #1 — Committee on Developing Competencies for the Future of Data and Computing: The Role of K–12</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/04/09/meeting-1-committee-on-developing-competencies-for-the-future-of-data-and-computing-the-role-of-k-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/04/09/meeting-1-committee-on-developing-competencies-for-the-future-of-data-and-computing-the-role-of-k-12/</guid>
      <description>The first meeting for the National Academies’ Committee on Developing Competencies for the Future of Data and Computing: The Role of K–12 is today. I wrote about the committee earlier (here). The open session is from 1-2 pm. Details including the Zoom link are here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gratitude </title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/02/14/gratitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2024/02/14/gratitude/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New years reflections and hopes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/12/30/new-years-reflections-hopes-and-prayers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/12/30/new-years-reflections-hopes-and-prayers/</guid>
      <description>One of my favorite days of the new year is the winter solstice, a day filled with hopes and wishes for brighter days ahead&#xA;Our family traveled to Asheville to meet friends for a two-night trip, returning just last night.&#xA;Asheville is where Katie and I had lived and met&amp;mdash;at a Halloween party around 2009, less than a mile from where we stayed in our AirBnb. I was student teaching biology and chemistry at a high school in Swannanoa, just outside of the city, and Katie was running an after school program at a YWCA in the city.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dear Colleagues, Dear Friends, Dear Family</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/12/09/dear-colleagues-dear-friends-dear-family/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/12/09/dear-colleagues-dear-friends-dear-family/</guid>
      <description>Dear Friends, Dear Colleagues, Dear Family,&#xA;This has been hard to write, but it felt a bit easier to write if I thought of it as a letter. First of all, it’s a letter to friends: two friends encouraged me to share my thoughts, and this post is chiefly a response to their encouragement (thanks David &amp;amp; Christa). It’s also a letter to colleagues I’ve agreed and disagreed with, been thankful for, and on occasion a little surprised and even (not intentionally) hurt by.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Letter in support of our colleagues in NARST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/10/24/letter-in-support-of-our-colleagues-in-narst/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/10/24/letter-in-support-of-our-colleagues-in-narst/</guid>
      <description>Here is the letter:&#xA;Dear NARST colleagues,&#xA;We are writing to support our friends and colleagues who wrote to respond in strong terms to NARST’s “In Memoriam” message on this listserv on Oct 18, 2023. Our colleagues are grieving the murder of a member of the NARST community, Yasmin Zohar, and her family (her two daughters, her father, and her husband), and of Dr. Marcel Frailich Kaplon and the kidnapping of Dr.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A joyful two seconds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/10/08/a-joyful-two-seconds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/10/08/a-joyful-two-seconds/</guid>
      <description>I made a comment to family that a photo of my son, our dog, and baby A was joyful for around two seconds &amp;mdash; until the dog jumped off the couch and woke up the baby, who started to cry. A joyful two seconds is apt for how the last six weeks have been, with a lot of joy interrupted often with a lot of crying.&#xA;I think my favorite thing I wrote about baby A included an off-hand thought that I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the language of good and bad babies; they&amp;rsquo;re people, small but their own, and also dependent on us.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reminder - Search for an Assistant/Associate Prof. of Educational Data Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/27/reminder-search-for-an-assistant-associate-prof-of-educational-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/27/reminder-search-for-an-assistant-associate-prof-of-educational-data-science/</guid>
      <description>I thought this morning to just post a reminder for those who may have not yet seen the advertisement about the search for an Assistant or Associate Professor of Educational Data Science at my institution.&#xA;The position description and information on applying can be found at this link: https://apply.interfolio.com/129607&#xA;Broadly, we are trying to build a world-class data science team. The search is broad and part of a three faculty member cluster hire.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first month with baby - unedited, unscripted, and very tired</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/26/the-first-month-with-baby-unedited-unscripted-and-very-tired/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/26/the-first-month-with-baby-unedited-unscripted-and-very-tired/</guid>
      <description>The first month with baby has been rocky and joyous. Here is a silly, unedited, unscripted video about it. I am very tired.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labor, delivery, and the first few days with baby</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/15/the-first-few-days-with-baby/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/09/15/the-first-few-days-with-baby/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m going to share about the first few days with baby. Women (rightfully so) often share birth stories. Men don&amp;rsquo;t often because it&amp;rsquo;s not clear what men&amp;rsquo;s roles when it comes to labor and delivery are or because such experiences aren&amp;rsquo;t considered inately important. It can be really important for men to be good support people for their spouses and experiencing a birth can be among the important moment of one&amp;rsquo;s life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for an Assistant or Associate Professor of Educational Data Science at UTK</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/31/search-for-an-assistant-or-associate-professor-of-educational-data-science-at-utk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/31/search-for-an-assistant-or-associate-professor-of-educational-data-science-at-utk/</guid>
      <description>My college - the College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville - is searching for an Assistant or Associate Professor of Educational Data Science position.&#xA;The position description and information on applying can be found at this link: https://apply.interfolio.com/129607&#xA;We have the opportunity to build a world-class educational data science and learning analytics faculty here, and I hope interested candidates from a wide variety of disciplines, locations, backgrounds, and career stages apply.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to baby Ayla</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/28/welcome-to-baby-ayla/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/28/welcome-to-baby-ayla/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to baby Ayla! She just arrived. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what more to say or how or what to share. This may sound silly, but when I think about her, I think, simply, that I think she&amp;rsquo;s great and that I love her.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - Facebook post data - A primer for educational research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/23/new-article-facebook-post-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/23/new-article-facebook-post-data/</guid>
      <description>With my colleagues Conrad Borchers and Rita Swartzengruber, I published an article in Educational Technology Research and Development on using public Facebook post data for research. The article is titled Facebook post data: a primer for educational research. Here&amp;rsquo;s its abstract:&#xA;Facebook is widely used and researched. However, though the data generated by educational technology tools and social media platforms other than Facebook have been used for research purposes, very little research has used Facebook posts as a data source—with most studies relying on self-report studies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A four-part module on machine learning in STEM education research using R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/01/a-four-part-open-access-module-on-machine-learning-in-educational-research-using-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/08/01/a-four-part-open-access-module-on-machine-learning-in-educational-research-using-r/</guid>
      <description>For the NSF-funded LASER Institute, I developed the initial materials last year on machine learning in STEM education research using R. The materials consist of four parts - what we called learning labs. Here are what each of the four are about:&#xA;= Learning Lab 1: Prediction &amp;mdash; How is prediction different from explanation?&#xA;Learning Lab 2: Interpretation &amp;mdash; How do we interpret the accuracy of a machine learning model? Learning Lab 3: Feature Engineering &amp;mdash; How can we improve our better?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pushing farther, taking shelter: more parenting thoughts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/pushing-farther-taking-shelter-more-parenting-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/pushing-farther-taking-shelter-more-parenting-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>Pushing further One of the most important events for me as a parent was when my neighbor, Zach, invited me to join him, his son, his friend, and his friend&amp;rsquo;s daughter, on a camping trip. The location was Frozen Head State Park, Jonah had just turned two, and we had never camped before. More broadly, Katie had, simply and frankly, taken on more responsibilities as a parent than I had. Reasons indefensible or partially defensible, that was the case, and I am thankful that we addressed this since then.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On chatGPT&#39;s Code Interpreter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/19/on-chatgpt-s-code-interpreter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/19/on-chatgpt-s-code-interpreter/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr: What chatGPT did for text, the Code Interpreter add-on does for data analysis.&#xA;Everyone has heard something about chatGPT, but there is a beta feature that is less well-known, Code Interpreter. It is not free &amp;ndash; it is a beta feature enabled for anyone who pays for chatGPT Plus. It&amp;rsquo;s sort of hard to find information on it, though the NY Times has an article on it. Here is another article with some instructions on how to enable and use it (if you have access to chatGPT Plus).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - Champions of Transparency in Education: What Journal Reviewers Can Do to Encourage Open Science Practices</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/18/new-article-champions-of-transparency-in-education-what-journal-reviewers-can-do-to-encourage-open-science-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/18/new-article-champions-of-transparency-in-education-what-journal-reviewers-can-do-to-encourage-open-science-practices/</guid>
      <description>I contributed to an article on how peer reviewers can take small steps to encourage the authors of manuscripts (and editors, indirectly) to encourage open science practices.&#xA;The paper is with Rachel Renbarger, Jill Adelson, Sondra Stegenga, Olivia Lowrey, Pamela Buckley, and Qiyang Zhang.&#xA;Champions of Transparency in Education: What Journal Reviewers Can Do to Encourage Open Science Practices&#xA;As the field of education, and especially gifted education, gradually moves toward open science, our research community increasingly values transparency and openness brought by open science practices.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To LeConte (with kiddos)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/13/to-leconte-with-kiddos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/13/to-leconte-with-kiddos/</guid>
      <description>My wife reminded me when my son and I returned from a hike to the top of Mt. LeConte that this was something I talked about doing since we moved to Knoxville. It took awhile, but we finally did it! Thanks to Sam and Levi for being great hiking buds.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What the heck is paternity leave?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/09/what-the-heck-is-paternity-leave/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/09/what-the-heck-is-paternity-leave/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to answer this question. For Moms, even the most extreme position recognizes the demands of childbirth and the first few days and weeks of a young infant&amp;rsquo;s life. A more enlightened view recognizes that it isn&amp;rsquo;t just the first few days or weeks of an infant&amp;rsquo;s life that are demanding, but the first few months, if not a whole year (hello, my dear German friends!).&#xA;Paternity leave is a bit of a different story.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working with me: a guide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/08/working-with-me-a-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/08/working-with-me-a-guide/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neighbors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/02/neighbors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/07/02/neighbors/</guid>
      <description>There is nothing like family, nor is there anything like close friends, but there is also nothing like neighbors, who can be a little bit like both family and friends.&#xA;We had a somewhat impromptu shower for the baby (due date in eight weeks, +- a standard deviation of around one week) last night in our cul-de-sac last night. It was the kind of event that made me feel sincerely happy and thankful for neighbors.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does tenure mean to me?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/29/pre-tenure-angst-but-not-for-long/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/29/pre-tenure-angst-but-not-for-long/</guid>
      <description>In my mind, I&amp;rsquo;ve drafted a lot of blog posts about how tenure - in short - stinks.&#xA;My complaints center on how too few faculty seem to take advantage of the amazing opportunity that tenure represents. I also have, on occasion, resented how tenure is taken advantage of by some in a different way &amp;ndash; as a means to being complacent, in so doing allowing graduate students and younger faculty to take on a greater workload.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving on, looking ahead, remaining open</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/moving-on-looking-ahead-remaining-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/moving-on-looking-ahead-remaining-open/</guid>
      <description>I didn’t know it then but my life had turned a page I tried several weeks ago to capture the past few years in a song. I wasn’t sure what the right song was, but I thought it was Molly Tuttle’s Grass Valley.&#xA;I didn’t know it then,&#xA;Sometimes, life operates on a gradient, with things being or becoming a little more good or bad. Other times it is punctuated and spiky, with moments of consequence entering and exiting.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My favorite kids book</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/24/my-favorite-kids-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/24/my-favorite-kids-book/</guid>
      <description>Is Hike, by Pete Oswold. It has no words. It is about a Dad and his son going on a hike&amp;mdash;from the start to the finish. It is perfectly evocative of the awesome experience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A hodgepodge of thoughts, summer camp edition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/18/a-hodgepodge-of-thoughts-summer-camp-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/18/a-hodgepodge-of-thoughts-summer-camp-edition/</guid>
      <description>The last few weeks have felt like summer camp, with work, but a lot of time not at work, too: visiting family and friends. I keep intending to blog random thoughts, but haven&amp;rsquo;t been motivated enough too&amp;mdash;until now. Here goes!&#xA;Biking and soccer Our son has been super into biking and soccer, to the point that I am struggling to keep up with his energy - two-three or more bike rides per day, interspersed with soccer games (and some basketball).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few additional thoughts on traveling to Amsterdam and Dublin (and working with the JASP team)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/10/a-few-additional-thoughts-on-traveling-to-amsterdam-and-dublin-and-working-with-the-jasp-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/10/a-few-additional-thoughts-on-traveling-to-amsterdam-and-dublin-and-working-with-the-jasp-team/</guid>
      <description>I mentioned in a post from a few weeks ago that I was working with the JASP statistical software team. Here are just a few notes following up from that productive working meeting.&#xA;Right now, JASP is used primarily by undergraduate and graduate students in psychology and the social sciences It could have utility for high school-aged students interested in carrying out statistical data analysis, particularly as it is free, open-source, and low-barrier but high-ceiling in its capabilities; it could make for a very nice complement to other tools that teachers use, including spreadsheets and graphing calculators One big potential barrier to its use is that it is, for practical purposes, laptop-computer-based&amp;mdash;there isn&amp;rsquo;t a very user-friendly web-based version, and the Chromebook installation is a chore The plan is to add a Teaching Science module to JASP, focused for now on two standards in the Next Generation Science Standards: Measuring and comparing biodiversity (NGSS LS2-1) Analyzing data on force and motion (NGSS PS2-1) There is good documentation for contributing a module to JASP; see here and here for the &amp;ldquo;server&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;UI&amp;rdquo; sides of the module, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First thoughts and reflections on Amsterdam and Dublin</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/04/first-thoughts-and-reflections-on-amsterdam-and-the-netherlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/06/04/first-thoughts-and-reflections-on-amsterdam-and-the-netherlands/</guid>
      <description>I am traveling to collaborate with colleagues in Amsterdam and Dublin. The funding comes from the National Science Foundation. To a program designed to encourage collaboration between European Research Council and the National Science Foundation, I applied for a supplement to an NSF grant. The original grant was on using the Experience Sampling Method to understand the experiences of students in undergraduate computer science and life science classes; the supplement turns the table by introducing the data analytic technique - Bayesian methods - to learners as a tool for them to understand scientific data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A hodgepodge of notes on applying for an NSF CAREER grant</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/30/a-hodgepodge-of-notes-on-applying-for-an-nsf-career-grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/30/a-hodgepodge-of-notes-on-applying-for-an-nsf-career-grant/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I&amp;rsquo;ve spoken with two friends over the last few weeks about applying for an NSF CAREER grant, and I thought to share a few notes here, mostly so I can build on them and flesh this out at some point in the future (and so I don&amp;rsquo;t lose them!). Here is a recent blog post on the project I&amp;rsquo;m starting this fall.&#xA;This is really rough, mostly just notes, and shared very humbly; I recognize the high degree of good luck I had in my proposal, and so please consider these notes with that foremost in mind.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The best trail for kids in the Smokies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/25/the-best-trail-for-kids-in-the-smokies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/25/the-best-trail-for-kids-in-the-smokies/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using iNaturalist data to understand species diversity in the GSMNP</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/18/using-inaturalist-data-to-understand-species-diversity-in-the-gsmnp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/18/using-inaturalist-data-to-understand-species-diversity-in-the-gsmnp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serving as an AE for JSDSE</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/17/serving-as-an-associate-editor-for-jsdse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/17/serving-as-an-associate-editor-for-jsdse/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to begin serving as an Associate Editor for the Journal of Statistics and Data Science Education. It&amp;rsquo;s a great fit for what I&amp;rsquo;m interested in and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to serve in an editorial capacity. It&amp;rsquo;s an American Statistical Association journal published by Taylor &amp;amp; Francis, but it&amp;rsquo;s also entirely open-access! If you&amp;rsquo;re doing data science education-related research&amp;mdash;in K-12 education, generally, and in science education, especially&amp;mdash;I&amp;rsquo;d love to very humbly invite you to submit your work to the journal or to reach out to me to gauge your work&amp;rsquo;s fit in the journal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A little write-up of Project CREDIBLE</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/16/a-little-write-up-of-project-credible/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/16/a-little-write-up-of-project-credible/</guid>
      <description>My College (the College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences) prepared a write-up of Project CREDIBLE. It&amp;rsquo;s linked here through the college website. Thanks Doug for doing this!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What my Spotify Top Songs say about me and what comes next</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/10/stuck-or-what-s-next-isn-t-about-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/05/10/stuck-or-what-s-next-isn-t-about-me/</guid>
      <description>Spotify creates a year-end playlist of my most-played songs for the previous year, and revisiting what I listened to awhile ago was fun and edifying for me.&#xA;In 2016, I was young and falling in love with Katie and our lives in Michigan&amp;hellip;&#xA;Later, I grew more confident and listened to music that was spunky and energetic - maybe I was too, you decide&amp;hellip;&#xA;2019 and 2020 were different. They were hard.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NSF CAREER - Project CREDIBLE</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/30/new-post-nsf-career-project-credible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/30/new-post-nsf-career-project-credible/</guid>
      <description>I started to cautiously speak about this as a possibility with friends and colleagues as early as mid-January, after which I spent a few weeks responding to clarifying questions about the proposal I submitted the previous July sent by an NSF program officer.&#xA;I waited, made some changes, waited, made some changes, and when on a canoe with my wife and son yesterday checked my email (for the first time in a few hours &amp;mdash; in this particular instance, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t anxiously checking!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tales from the Smokies backcountry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/27/tales-from-the-smokies-backcountry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/27/tales-from-the-smokies-backcountry/</guid>
      <description>We headed out late, not arriving until around 7:30 pm. We still had some packing to do there, where we stuffed food into the sides of our packs, looking for headlamps and extra clothes given that it was a little chilly, having been cold at the Smokies&amp;rsquo; crest as we drove to the Kephart Prong trailhead.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at NARST 2023</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/19/presentations-at-narst-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/19/presentations-at-narst-2023/</guid>
      <description>The last time I presented at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST) conference was 2016 - in Baltimore! This year, it is in Chicago, and I am presenting several projects with doctoral students and colleagues.&#xA;A Bayesian Approach to Making Sense of Uncertainty in the Science Classroom Uncertainty and Sensemaking in Science Classrooms, 1:00-2:30pm Wednesday, 19 April, 2023 (with Marcus Kubsch, Mine Dogucu, and E.J. Wagenmakers&#xA;A Curriculum Analysis of The Sources of Data and Data Engagements of Science Students, 10:30am-12:00pm Thursday, 20 April, 2023 (with Amanda Garner)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at AERA 2023</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/12/presentations-at-aera-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/12/presentations-at-aera-2023/</guid>
      <description>Last night, I recollected that the last American Educational Research Association (AERA) conference I attended was four years ago - during April 2019 in Toronto, Canada. I remember walking down a busy road from my hotel to the location of a presentation when I received an email from the Taylor &amp;amp; Frances editor for Data Science in Education Using R indicating that they were moving to accept our proposal to publish the book - which was eventually published in October, 2020&amp;mdash;this event approaching being three years ago!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My favorite part of Passover</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/06/my-favorite-part-of-passover/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/06/my-favorite-part-of-passover/</guid>
      <description>I think my favorite part of Passover - the Jewish holiday that focuses on the Jews escape or emancipation from slavery in ancient Egypt, followed by their exodus in the Sinai desert - is about an expression of gratitude. There&amp;rsquo;s a song, dayenu, that means (and is about) &amp;ldquo;it would have been enough&amp;rdquo;. What&amp;rsquo;s enough? This question is so hard to answer. What if I have an incredible life partner? A family I love; a job I like?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New pre-print - The Design and Implementation of a Bayesian Data Analysis Lesson for Pre-Service Mathematics and Science Teachers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/05/new-pre-print-the-design-and-implementation-of-a-bayesian-data-analysis-lesson-for-pre-service-mathematics-and-science-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/05/new-pre-print-the-design-and-implementation-of-a-bayesian-data-analysis-lesson-for-pre-service-mathematics-and-science-teachers/</guid>
      <description>With Mine Dogucu and Sibel Kazak, I have written a paper that intends to make Bayesian data analysis accessible and practical for science and mathematics teachers at the high school level. The paper is The Design and Implementation of a Bayesian Data Analysis Lesson for Pre-Service Mathematics and Science Teachers.&#xA;The abstract is here:&#xA;With the rise of the popularity of Bayesian methods and accessible computer software, teaching and learning about Bayesian methods are expanding.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing a blurb for a CAREER grant (and all the work that goes into and accompanies it)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/04/before-and-after-i-first-started-to-think-about-the-core-idea-in-my-nsf-career-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/04/04/before-and-after-i-first-started-to-think-about-the-core-idea-in-my-nsf-career-proposal/</guid>
      <description>Last summer, I wrote a proposal to the NSF CAREER program, which provides grant funding to early career researchers. The proposal was submitted in July and I&amp;rsquo;m still awaiting the results of the review and award process.&#xA;Related, this semester, I am teaching a one-credit class for Ph.D. students; part of the class focuses on creating a really early record of one&amp;rsquo;s ideas - a brief &amp;ldquo;blurb&amp;rdquo; to pitch the core idea of the proposal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sports!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/24/sports/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/24/sports/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I watched Michigan State University (my alma mater) play Kansas State University in the NCAA tournament (aka, &amp;ldquo;March Madness&amp;rdquo;). After this game, the University of Tennessee played Florida Atlantic University. The Michigan State University game was so fun, but anxiety-producing. I watched with my son, who got really into it. As the game entered overtime, he was a bit of a mess&amp;mdash;as I was, too.&#xA;Michigan State lost. So did Tennessee (both teams were favorites, but Tennessee was a heavy favorite!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Learning Analytics in STEM Education Research Institute is Accepting Applications for the 2023 cohort</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/24/learning-analytics-in-stem-education-research-institute-is-accepting-applications-for-the-2023-cohort/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/24/learning-analytics-in-stem-education-research-institute-is-accepting-applications-for-the-2023-cohort/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to share that the NSF-funded Learning Analytics in STEM Education Research (LASER) Institute for early- and mid-career educational researchers is now recruiting for the 2023 annual cohort! This year&amp;rsquo;s summer workshop will run from July 17-21 and be hosted in Raleigh, NC on the campus of North Carolina State University. A reimbursement allowance of $1,500 will be provided for travel, lodging, and evening meals (breakfast and lunch will be provided each day) to support participation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An update on Little Kids, Big Adventures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/16/an-update-on-little-kids-big-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/16/an-update-on-little-kids-big-adventures/</guid>
      <description>My wife Katie and I are working on a hiking book in our abundant free time. It&amp;rsquo;s tentatively titled: Little Kids, Big Adventures Around Knoxville, Tennessee: Learning About and Experiencing the Tennessee Valley, Cumberland Plateau, and the Great Smoky Mountains. I&amp;rsquo;ve blogged about it before here. I love working with Katie on it &amp;mdash; my best collaborator!&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example chapter on one of our favorite places close to Knoxville, Seven Islands State Birding Park.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An update on Educational Data Science at UTK course offerings</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/10/educational-data-science-at-utk-course-offerings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/10/educational-data-science-at-utk-course-offerings/</guid>
      <description>The Educational Data Science Graduate Certificate is off and running. There are several modifications regarding the course codes (e.g., STEM 580 is now STEM 680) and names. The four courses that make up the certificate and when they will be offered are as follows:&#xA;STEM 680 Foundations of Educational Data Science I (3 credits): Every Fall STEM 685 Foundations of Educational Data Science II (3): Every Spring STEM 691 Visualizing Data Using R (3): Every Spring STEM 695 Capstone in Educational Data Science (3): Every other Fall (beginning Fall &amp;lsquo;24) If interested, please reach out!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proceedings from the NAS Foundations of Data Science for Students in Grades K-12 Workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/10/proceedings-from-the-foundations-of-data-science-for-students-in-grades-k-12-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/10/proceedings-from-the-foundations-of-data-science-for-students-in-grades-k-12-workshop/</guid>
      <description>The Proceedings from the National Academy of Science&amp;rsquo;s Foundations of Data Science for Students in Grades K-12 were published this week. They&amp;rsquo;re available here.&#xA;I blogged about the workshop previously here and here.&#xA;I hope these proceedings influence the conversation about K-12 data science education in the years ahead. Kudos to the organizers and editors of the proceedings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What religious feeling is to me - making the everyday special and feeling grateful</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/04/what-religious-feels-look-like-to-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/03/04/what-religious-feels-look-like-to-me/</guid>
      <description>I have been peppering my recent posts with religious elements&amp;mdash;but not speaking to religion directly. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll speak to religion directly.&#xA;Last night, my wife and I said thanks for our (sick with a nasty virus!) child. We also expressed thanks for the growing child in Katie&amp;rsquo;s belly for doing well in there. These expressions of thanks were a way to make an everyday Friday night special.&#xA;Over the last few weeks, I have also been almost overwhelmed with gratitude.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Google Scholar results through serpAPI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/23/accessing-google-scholar-results-through-serpapi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/23/accessing-google-scholar-results-through-serpapi/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in open science and open access for awhile and I&amp;rsquo;m presently working on a project with my colleague Dr. Enilda Romero-Hall and Dr. George Veletsianos on these topics. We have a chance to share some some early findings on the state of open access in education at this Spring&amp;rsquo;s Open Education Conference.&#xA;One part of the the work has involved usign a third-party serice that provides automated (i.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning to welcome a baby girl this August</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/23/planning-for-a-baby/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/23/planning-for-a-baby/</guid>
      <description>I am happy that my wife Katie and I are planning to welcome a baby girl to the world this August. Katie is doing well and our son is excited to become a big brother. I&amp;rsquo;ll be sure to share more as the pregnancy progresses, but now only have a deep sense of gratitude and awe about Katie.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I didn&#39;t know it then, but my life had turned a page</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/21/i-didn-t-know-it-then-but-my-life-had-turned-a-page/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/21/i-didn-t-know-it-then-but-my-life-had-turned-a-page/</guid>
      <description>When I lived in Lansing, I listened to what I thought of at the time as deep, dark music, especially in the darkness of winter months. Here is an example. In the darkness, I feel like I grew something bright and joyous, different from the music and the day to day of living in a dark, slushy, cold place.&#xA;Over the last three years, I played this song on repeat. In my mind, it captures the twinned tedium and challenge of life during COVID.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How strong am I? And how able to accept what happens am I?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/19/how-strong-am-i-and-how-accepting-am-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/19/how-strong-am-i-and-how-accepting-am-i/</guid>
      <description>I gashed open one thumb and slammed the other in my trunk, got lost in the woods, and dealt with some big and complex emotions, and together these experiences have made me realize over the past few months that I have been asked to answer the question: How strong am I? And how able to accept what happens am I?&#xA;I briefly passed out when I accidentally slammed my thumb in the trunk after organzing it for a trip to the garden nursey.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lost in Honey Creek during a flood</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/19/lost-in-honey-creek-during-a-flood/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/19/lost-in-honey-creek-during-a-flood/</guid>
      <description>Honey Creek is one of the most outstanding hiking trails in the Southeast and it may even validly be on a list of the most outstanding hiking trails in the country.&#xA;It is hard to find good summaries of it. AllTrails is one source of information on it, but neither the summary nor any one review describes the experience. I&amp;rsquo;ll try:&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s an around five-mile loop hike with a half-mile, 200-foot cliff line, an overlook of the free-flowing Big South Fork, a portion in a valley that seems primordial, where the trail goes in the creek, through and over boulders, past 100 foot, 50 foot, 10 foot, and little slate waterfalls, around what seem like amphitheaters carved from the rock, and down several steep portions that involve using a rope.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another post on MSU - a meditation, dream, and gift</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/16/another-post-on-msu-a-dream-and-a-gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/16/another-post-on-msu-a-dream-and-a-gift/</guid>
      <description>A colleague shared this article, Requieum for the Spartans by an MSU graduate (now a journalist). It is good and worth reading.&#xA;It makes the case that college is a gift, but that MSU is now a different place. It resonated with me as I was thinking over the past few days about how my time there feels like a meditation or a dream in retrospect, repetitive and tedious in the best possible way, like how weathering can turn a rock into something special.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The mass shooting at MSU</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/14/the-mass-shooting-at-msu/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/02/14/the-mass-shooting-at-msu/</guid>
      <description>When I heard that a man shot and killed three Michigan State University students in the Student Union, I thought of the time I spent in that building&amp;mdash;one of the two where students were shot. Absurdly, I remember filling my presentation poster&amp;rsquo;s tube with snacks at the end of the CREATE for STEM mini-conference there. I also remember getting my graduation hood and robe sized; absurdly for a different reason, I remember how my initials were incorrectly embroidered on the robe as &amp;ldquo;RHM&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Story in Education Week on teachers and chatGPT</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/30/story-in-education-week-on-teachers-and-chatgpt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/30/story-in-education-week-on-teachers-and-chatgpt/</guid>
      <description>Alyson Klein published a story late last week on teachers and chatGPT&amp;mdash;a &amp;ldquo;large language model&amp;rdquo; I played around with a bunch last week in preparation for sharing a few thoughts on this new technology. I had talked with Alyson before about the potential privacy risks to students associated with schools and districts social media activity.&#xA;The story is here. I tried to see things from the teacher perspective while recognizing the potential usefulness of chatGPT and tools like over a longer time horizon.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few more poems and haikus (with assistance from AI)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/25/a-few-more-poems-and-haikus-with-assistance-from-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/25/a-few-more-poems-and-haikus-with-assistance-from-ai/</guid>
      <description>Here are a two more sets of haikus and poems I wrote today, with much assistance from chatGPT (here&amp;rsquo;s a bit of background on this).&#xA;1. A quiet winter break 1. In response to this prompt:&#xA;Please write a Haiku based on the following blog post: Around 2015, my wife and I didn&amp;rsquo;t leave Lansing, Michigan, during the winter break. It was cold, snowy, dark, and one of the best and most special breaks I remember.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Haiku, with help from AI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/25/three-haiku-with-help-from-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/25/three-haiku-with-help-from-ai/</guid>
      <description>Based on several conversations and ideas from friends, I copy-pasted several recent blog posts into chatGPT with a prompt like the following: Please write a Haiku based on the following blog post: (followed by the entire unedited text of the post).&#xA;(Aside: What&amp;rsquo;s chatGPT? Here is a decent overview with a focus on education)&#xA;I first used a predecessor of chatGPT, GPT-3, in April as part of a presentation on ML and AI at the LEAD Graduate School at the University of Tuebingen.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>At the end of the winter break</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/17/at-the-end-of-the-winter-break/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/17/at-the-end-of-the-winter-break/</guid>
      <description>In my mind, the winter break began around the Winter Solstice, when I blogged about the joy in the year&amp;rsquo;s shortest day. Today feels sort of like the end of the winter break. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working more or less consistently, but the pace has been slower, interspersed with family time in a way that has felt good. The break was rocky, but suitably joyous, ending on a day when I feel thankful for the slow, quiet break filled with family time and time with our good friends.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observing MLK day</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/16/observing-mlk-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/16/observing-mlk-day/</guid>
      <description>This is the very minimum &amp;mdash; reading MLK&amp;rsquo;s writing.&#xA;This opart of Letter from a Birmingham Jail abrades my growing sense of moderation.&#xA;I must confess that over the past few years I have been gravely disappointed with the white moderate. I have almost reached the regrettable conclusion that the Negro&amp;rsquo;s great stumbling block in his stride toward freedom is not the White Citizen&amp;rsquo;s Counciler or the Ku Klux Klanner, but the white moderate, who is more devoted to &amp;ldquo;order&amp;rdquo; than to justice; who prefers a negative peace which is the absence of tension to a positive peace which is the presence of justice; who constantly says: &amp;ldquo;I agree with you in the goal you seek, but I cannot agree with your methods of direct action&amp;rdquo;; who paternalistically believes he can set the timetable for another man&amp;rsquo;s freedom; who lives by a mythical concept of time and who constantly advises the Negro to wait for a &amp;ldquo;more convenient season.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To the wild</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/13/to-the-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/13/to-the-wild/</guid>
      <description>When my family and I were moving to Tennessee, our son was around three months old. It felt like a big, slightly scary adventure. We had lived in Michigan for six years. My parents were an hour from Lansing. I knew&amp;mdash;or at least it felt like I knew&amp;mdash;every park, lake, city, and bike path around. We had close friends we loved.&#xA;This song was one I listened to to gear up for the move.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basking in a beautiful, sad song</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/05/a-beautiful-sad-song/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/05/a-beautiful-sad-song/</guid>
      <description>Around 2015, my wife and I didn&amp;rsquo;t leave Lansing, Michigan, during the winter break. It was cold, snowy, dark, and one of the best and most special breaks I remember. It was a time of quiet reflection, much like this winter break when my family didn&amp;rsquo;t leave (Knoxville, Tennessee).&#xA;I am still basking in the quiet (and the cold &amp;mdash; and the pretty dark evenings!). I found this song by one of my favorite groups, Mandoling Orange, on YouTube and it captured my current mood.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New pre-print - The Design and Effects of Data Science Workshops for Educational Researchers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/05/new-pre-print-the-design-and-effects-of-data-science-workshops-for-educational-researchers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/05/new-pre-print-the-design-and-effects-of-data-science-workshops-for-educational-researchers/</guid>
      <description>My colleague Bret Staudt-Willet and I have a new pre-print (a not peer-reviewed paper that we are sharing now in advance of submitting the paper for review). It is entitled The Design and Effects of Data Science Workshops for Educational Researchers. Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&#xA;Though there is growing interest in using novel methods to analyze novel sources of educational data, numerous barriers and challenges exist for researchers and analysts seeking to learn to use educational data science methods in their work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signs of spring</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/02/signs-of-spring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/02/signs-of-spring/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on the last year</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/01/reflecting-on-the-last-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2023/01/01/reflecting-on-the-last-year/</guid>
      <description>This year has been full of challenges that provoked growth from the start to the finish. This was a humbling year, too. It was a year in which I grew mentally and, in a little way, faithfully. It was a year in which I learned that successes can be followed by failures and that that process doesn&amp;rsquo;t stop&amp;mdash;and that there may never be a single moment when absolutely everything is set, finished, done, complete, and joyful.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Happy Winter Solstice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/12/20/happy-winter-solstice/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/12/20/happy-winter-solstice/</guid>
      <description>Happy Winter Solstice&amp;mdash;the most joyous day of the year.&#xA;My Mom listened to the album this song is on when I was growing up. I think it captures the spirit of the winter solstice, the shortest and darkest but also the day with the greatest potential for things getting better. For these reasons, I look forward to the solstice all year.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The identical output of lm() and aov() and lm() and t.test() in R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/21/the-identical-output-of-lm-and-aov-and-lm-and-t.test-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/21/the-identical-output-of-lm-and-aov-and-lm-and-t.test-in-r/</guid>
      <description>This one hardly counts as a blog post; it is more a reference for myself.&#xA;For some time, I’ve known on a conceptual level that a linear regression model (one “fit” using lm() in the statistical software and programming language R), ANOVA (aov()), and t-test (t.test()) can be conceptualized as being closely-related—though they’re often taught as separate techniques.&#xA;I’m going to add the code now, hoping to return to and expand on this later.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Education Using R is updated!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/data-science-in-education-using-r-is-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/data-science-in-education-using-r-is-updated/</guid>
      <description>The Data Science in Education Using R book has been updated based on issues in the code and writing that we have become aware of (in many cases thanks to people who have submitted issues via GitHub &amp;mdash; and thanks to people who contacted us in other ways). Also, we had some edits leftover from the copy editing process that we hadn&amp;rsquo;t integrated into the web-based version of the book; those are also now synchronized between the Routledge and web-based version of the book.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing Michigan, finding home in Tennessee</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/songs-for-colder-weather/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/songs-for-colder-weather/</guid>
      <description>A song came on a randomly selected playlist over the second, Half Acre by Hem.&#xA;I am holding half an acre&#xA;Torn from the map of Michigan&#xA;And folded in this scrap of paper&#xA;Is a land I grew in&#xA;The song takes me back to Michigan.&#xA;Biking with my wife Katie at Hawk Island. Biking on the rail-trail near Saranac, 30 minutes from Lansing but a world away. Night, absolutely freezing bike rides a campfire and beers at Rose Lake.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Please subscribe to or follow my blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/please-subscribe-to-or-follow-my-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/14/please-subscribe-to-or-follow-my-blog/</guid>
      <description>Blogging is (arguably, still) cool More than six months ago, I stepped away from using social media, and it has been fine, but the primary way I communicate is via blogging&amp;mdash;arguably an out-of-date medium, but, at the same time, maybe a valuable one:&#xA;You own the content &amp;mdash; not a social media platform with a possibly impetus owner You can write longer pieces You are not as tied to what people like/dislike as indicated by social media interactions My friend Enilda Romero-Hall recently mentioned the importance of blogging in a seminar presentation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not defeated, still living - a brief and informal review of A Heartbreak at Wounded Knee</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/12/a-little-review-of-a-heartbreak-at-wounded-knee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/12/a-little-review-of-a-heartbreak-at-wounded-knee/</guid>
      <description>The book My friend Spencer Greenhalgh recommended A Heartbreak at Wounded Knee, a history of the people who lived in what is now America. The thesis is simple: the Indians1 were deceived, lied to, managed by corrupt officials, and destroyed by pandemics and war and all that accompanies pandemics, wars, deceit, lies, and corruption, but the Indian people endure and in cases thrive.&#xA;This is a powerful thesis to me because it acknowledges a reality while also pointing to a new, less evident reality, namely that Indian culture has&amp;mdash;in many but not all places&amp;mdash;been kept, protected, and shared.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in Educational Researcher - Posts about students on Facebook</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/02/new-article-in-educational-researcher-posts-about-students-on-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/02/new-article-in-educational-researcher-posts-about-students-on-facebook/</guid>
      <description>With my great colleagues Conrad Borchers, Macy Burchfield, Sondra Stegenga, Daniel Anderson, and Christian Fischer, I recently wrote a brief report that was published in the AERA journal Educational Researcher on posts about students on the social media platform Facebook. The article is entitled Posts About Students on Facebook: A Data Ethics Perspective. The abstract highlights some of the key findings:&#xA;Public schools and districts use social media to share announcements and communicate with parents and the community, but alongside such uses run risks to students’ privacy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in Phi Delta Kappan - How to respond to community concerns about critical race theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/02/new-article-in-phi-delta-kappan-how-to-respond-to-community-concerns-about-critical-race-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/02/new-article-in-phi-delta-kappan-how-to-respond-to-community-concerns-about-critical-race-theory/</guid>
      <description>With Emily A. Hodge and Francesca A. López, I am proud to share an article that involved looking at some district communication in the wake of last summer&amp;rsquo;s contentious discussions about the contents of the school curriculum. Specifically, we examined the posts on Facebook by school districts, detailing some ways these messages could potentially be strengthened.&#xA;The core of the article draws on research about political messaging that points out that messages that are effective for achieving political means have the following features (drawing on work primarily by [Haney López]https://books.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Very off-trail, lost on the Cosby Nature Trail</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/01/very-off-trail-lost-on-the-cosby-nature-trail/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/11/01/very-off-trail-lost-on-the-cosby-nature-trail/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been having some more fun with recording and editing video - this one a short-ish (two minute) video from a fun night hike with my son and his friend near Cosby Campground in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park.&#xA;I didn&amp;rsquo;t shoot this video using 4K - this was with 1080p and I think the difference is notable, but it still looks fun for this purpose.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graduate-level course in data visualization (Spring 2023) at UTK</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/21/graduate-level-course-in-data-visualization-spring-2023-at-utk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/21/graduate-level-course-in-data-visualization-spring-2023-at-utk/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m offering a graduate-level course in data visualization to be offered for the first time this spring, STEM 591: Visualizing Data Using R. The course will be offered on Mondays from 12:00 – 2:30 pm. The modality will be online and synchronous. Please see the flyer below for several additional details.&#xA;![spring 2023 data viz class](images/STEM 591 - Visualizing Data Using R - Spring 2023.png)&#xA;This course is part of the Educational Data Science Graduate Certificate program, consisting of four courses that current graduate students and individuals interested in completing a stand-alone program complete.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Having fun with 4k video</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/20/having-fun-with-4k-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/20/having-fun-with-4k-video/</guid>
      <description>I purchased a camera around four months ago and I have had fun taking photos and learning to take better photos. At first, I thought it was not much of an improvement on my phone, but with a few better lenses, improved technique, and a few attempts to print pictures at larger sizes, I can see the advantages in favor of using a dedicated camera.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s perhaps the best (in my view) photo I&amp;rsquo;ve taken with the camera (from my little one at a fun run last weekend).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tearing down goal posts was not cool</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/17/tennessee-should-not-allow-students-to-tear-down-goal-posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/17/tennessee-should-not-allow-students-to-tear-down-goal-posts/</guid>
      <description>This is a post about celebrating the recent win by the University of Tennessee, Knoxville&amp;rsquo;s football team.&#xA;I think the University of Tennessee, Knoxville&amp;rsquo;s Chancellor, Donde Plowman has done an excellent job. I watched the University of Tennessee, Knoxville and the University of Alabama football game over the weekend with excitement. When the University of Tennessee kicked a field goal as time ran out to win the game, I was thrilled.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many people have struggled with having children</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/13/many-people-have-struggled-with-having-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/13/many-people-have-struggled-with-having-children/</guid>
      <description>Several friends shared with me storyies about their struggles with having children after I shared yesterday about my wife Katie&amp;rsquo;s miscarriage yesterday (here). These were challenges with infertility, miscarriage, and difficult births. There are others, too. It was heartbreaking; not in some saint-like - but rather in a clarifying - way, it is hard to read about the loss and heartache of others. Two comments stuck out; both were from friends who described their experiences as the hardest and darkest days of their lives.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Materials for my tenure and promotion bid</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/12/materials-for-my-tenure-and-promotion-bid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/12/materials-for-my-tenure-and-promotion-bid/</guid>
      <description>I like sharing I&amp;rsquo;m not a hero here, but one small step I&amp;rsquo;ve taken at previous stages in my career to share materials that are conventionally kept private has been useful to others - and me, as a reference, especially:&#xA;Academic Job Market Resources (including the cover letter I used in 2017 to apply for my current job and my research, teaching, and diversity statements) Materials for an NSF Building Capacity in STEM Education Research grant proposal that was awarded funding in 2019 In that spirit, after completing the materials I needed for my tenure and promotion &amp;ldquo;bid&amp;rdquo; (application?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tragedy and experiencing loss</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/12/tragedy-and-experiencing-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/10/12/tragedy-and-experiencing-loss/</guid>
      <description>Around a year ago I listened to a song by bluegrass/classical music-minded musician I have listened to before in the group Mandolin Orange (now named Watchhouse Duo, for reasons I&amp;rsquo;ll mention), Fire &amp;amp; Fury by Andrew Marlin. The song is nice but not extraordinary, except for a small part that I thought was: around one minute into the song, you hear a toddler quietly, happily talking, maybe to theirself or maybe to their mother or father.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coverage in Wired of research on school and district posts about students and student privacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/23/coverage-in-wired-of-research-on-students-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/23/coverage-in-wired-of-research-on-students-privacy/</guid>
      <description>I was surprised and happy to see my colleagues and my research covered in a (really good) story on Wired, The Tricky Ethics of Being a Teacher on TikTok. A link to the story is here.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s an except of the story that I think sets up the dilemma well:&#xA;The hashtags #teacher and #teachersoftiktok have a combined 72.1 billion views on TikTok. While many of these videos feature educators simply discussing their job, others take place inside the classroom and include children’s voices, faces, and schoolwork.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Happy Autumnal Equinox</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/22/happy-autumnal-equinox/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/22/happy-autumnal-equinox/</guid>
      <description>Today is the Autumnal Equinox &amp;mdash; one of two days on which the sunrise and sunset are around 12 hours apart around the world (humble former science teacher note: it&amp;rsquo;s actually not 100% clear to me why it&amp;rsquo;s not precisely 12 hours apart). From here through the Winter Solstice, on December 21st, the period of daylight will be getting shorter, but at a slower rate each day. Thus, for me, today is both an optimistic and a pessimistic day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backpacking with kids: The third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/19/backpacking-with-kids-the-third-times-a-charm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/19/backpacking-with-kids-the-third-times-a-charm/</guid>
      <description>I returned home from a frenetic week of travel with a funeral and a workshop to take my son to school. He asked me before drop off when we could walk in the woods to go sleep: he wanted to backpack and so did I. We arranged plans with a friend and his son and headed out for an approximately 1.5 mile, mostly flat hike in to a backcountry site in the Smokies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on day 1 of the foundations of data science for K-12 students workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/14/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-foundations-of-data-science-for-k-12-students-nasem-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/14/reflections-on-day-1-of-the-foundations-of-data-science-for-k-12-students-nasem-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Background There is a two-day workshop on The Foundations of Data Science for Students in Grades K-12 hosted at the National Academies. The workshop is in-person and online; if you registered (or if you did not!), you can watch a livestream here: https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/09-13-2022/foundations-of-data-science-for-students-in-grades-k-12-a-workshop-days-1-and-2&#xA;Reflections I&amp;rsquo;ll keep these short, as I might not otherwise share them (and I&amp;rsquo;d rather share something rather than nothing!).&#xA;I thought the three commissioned papers others wrote (on critical data literacies, the national implementation landscape, and tools to support data science) were .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commissioned paper on K-12 data science learning for a National Academies workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/09/commissioned-paper-on-k-12-data-science-learning-for-a-national-academies-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/09/09/commissioned-paper-on-k-12-data-science-learning-for-a-national-academies-workshop/</guid>
      <description>I had blogged a few weeks ago about a National Academies workshop on K-12 data science education; briefly the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Mathematics is planning a workshop on Data Science Education on September 13-14. The workshop is in-person and online; you can register to attend it here.&#xA;I co-authored one of four commissioned papers on K-12 data science learning. That paper and three others are available from the homepage for the workshop.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loss and reflecting on loss</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/31/loss-and-reflecting-on-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/31/loss-and-reflecting-on-loss/</guid>
      <description>This has been a week of loss and reflecting on loss, a hard one without a respite apart from in the comfort of family and friends. Before this week, I was listening to the Watchhouse song titled Echo, and it is more appropriate for this week. It is a sad song, with no comfort apart from that offered by experiencing the sadness as it comes. I&amp;rsquo;ll note - my family and I are safe and well - so don&amp;rsquo;t worry about us!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering from failure (soccer, academia, life)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/30/recovering-from-failure-soccer-academia-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/30/recovering-from-failure-soccer-academia-life/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Special section on data science across the disciplines is published!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/22/special-section-on-data-science-across-the-disciplines-is-published/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/22/special-section-on-data-science-across-the-disciplines-is-published/</guid>
      <description>The special section of the British Journal of Educational Technology on Data Science Education Across the Disciplines is officially published here. There are nine articles that broadly explore the topic of what data science education is or can be across subject matter disciplines&amp;mdash;from art education to science education. There is one editorial, two review papers, and six empirical papers; five of these articles are &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo; or open access. It was great to work with Shiyan Jiang and Victor Lee to co-edit this; it was a great editorial experience working with these two excellent scholars and the team of article authors.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parenting, reprised</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/21/parenting-reprised/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/21/parenting-reprised/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a post about a year ago about how it was hard to understand the Smokies. I realize now&amp;mdash;in part from reading my wife&amp;rsquo;s copy of the book Braiding Sweetgrass&amp;mdash;that was because my focus was too narrow. I was trying to understand facts: their scientific, geographical, and even human history/sociological sides.&#xA;That book argued that understanding these parts of some place are immensely valuable, but they&amp;rsquo;re also far from the complete picture.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>National Academies Workshop on Data Science Education (DSE) - Call for DSE Challenges</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/20/national-academies-workshop-on-data-science-education-dse-call-for-dse-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/20/national-academies-workshop-on-data-science-education-dse-call-for-dse-challenges/</guid>
      <description>The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Mathematics is planning a workshop on Data Science Education on September 13-14. The workshop is in-person and online; you can register to attend it here.&#xA;With my colleague Seth Jones, I am writing one of four commissioned papers for the workshop; ours is on learning data science. An outline for our paper is here in Google Docs; we definitely welcome any input on our plan for the (brief!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Announcing the Graduate Certificate in Educational Data Science (at UTK)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/17/announcing-the-graduate-certificate-in-educational-data-science-at-utk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/17/announcing-the-graduate-certificate-in-educational-data-science-at-utk/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been teaching classes on educational data science and learning analytics this past year, and I&amp;rsquo;ve shared about those courses as they&amp;rsquo;ve been offered (for instance, here&amp;rsquo;s some information on the introductory course).&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m jazzed to now be announcing the Graduate Certificate in Educational Data Science at UTK. This is available to graduate students in any program at UTK and individuals not yet enrolled in a UTK graduate degree program. The intended audience for the program includes graduate students, educational analysts, and other professionals, and individuals newer to education looking to bolster their ability to access and use complex, varied sources of educational data and to become capable with newer methodologies, including network analysis, machine learning, and text analysis.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Thoughts on the Open Scholarship in Education (OSE) Working Meeting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/12/some-thoughts-on-the-open-scholarship-in-education-ose-working-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/12/some-thoughts-on-the-open-scholarship-in-education-ose-working-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Background With my colleague Cynthia D&amp;rsquo;Angelo, I presented a webinar on analyzing educational data from an open science perspective through the Center for Open Science. The organization (unsurprisngly!) advocates for openness in research; they created and maintain the fairly widely-used (across research fields) Open Science Framework platform for sharing.&#xA;The Center for Open Science invited people from across educational research to join a working meeting this week on open science in educational science&amp;mdash;wait, scratch that, in educational scholarship!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on work</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/09/thoughts-on-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/09/thoughts-on-work/</guid>
      <description>I had a hard time titling this post and so I settled on the lowest common denominator to the titles I was considering: This is a post with thoughts on work!&#xA;I started my Ph.D. almsot exactly 10 years ago. I was not very well prepared for graduate school, but I had some strengths. I had been a teacher; my first publication - on the role of context in ed tech research (TPACK, specifically) came directly from what I noticed as a teacher, namely that context mattered more than the ed tech field seemed to acknowledge.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - A framework for augmenting human analytic power with machine learning in science education research in JRST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/03/new-article-a-framework-for-augmenting-human-analytic-power-with-machine-learning-in-science-education-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/03/new-article-a-framework-for-augmenting-human-analytic-power-with-machine-learning-in-science-education-research/</guid>
      <description>My co-authors Marcus Kubsch and Christina (Stina) Krist and I have been discussing and thinking about using machine learning in science education research&amp;mdash;the primary field in which we work. The result of the many discussions (and projects!) we engaged in was this position paper in which we intend to spark a conversation about how we can use machine learning in ways that augment our work and capabilities as researchers&amp;mdash;and not only to automate existing processes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - Characterizing Whole Class Discussions About Data and Statistics - in JMB</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/02/new-article-characterizing-whole-class-discussions-about-data-and-statistics-in-jmb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/02/new-article-characterizing-whole-class-discussions-about-data-and-statistics-in-jmb/</guid>
      <description>In May 2018, Seth Jones, a faculty member at Middle Tennessee State University, connected on Twitter over the topic of students in math and science classes working with data. I mentioned that we were moving to Tennessee, and we then connected over email. I had to search an old email account to find our correspondence:&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;d love to have the chance to meet up (virtually) - and hopefully F2F at state events.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uneven Access - How Academic Journal Articles Are Shared in the Open</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/02/uneven-access-how-academic-journal-articles-are-shared-in-the-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/08/02/uneven-access-how-academic-journal-articles-are-shared-in-the-open/</guid>
      <description>I submitted an abstract for a proposal to the OpenEd conference. Unfortunately, the proposal was not accepted, and so I am sharing the proposal here to gauge others&amp;rsquo; interests and reactions to this work.&#xA;The motivation for this work was finding that many authors (including, occasionally, me) share PDFs of their published articles. Though technically a copyright violation, the practice is widespread. I wanted to see how widesread this was; the intended outcome of this is to start a conversation about why we are compelled to violate copyright to share our work and whether we might consider new ways of sharing our work that do not rely on publishers (and violating copyright in ways that may result in uneven benefits for authors who are and are not willing to post copyrighted work!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Staying cool in the Smoky Mountains</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/22/staying-cool-in-the-smoky-mountains/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/22/staying-cool-in-the-smoky-mountains/</guid>
      <description>It has been hot and humid here - as hot and humid as it was in late summer-early fall 2019, when it felt like it would never cool down; it was above 90F for most of September. It has been around or above 90F for much of the past month, less atypical for July, but still challenging. With humidity in the picture, the heat index has consistently topped 100F, occasionally approaching 110F.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Will we be back to Michigan one day?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/22/i-will-be-back-one-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/22/i-will-be-back-one-day/</guid>
      <description>Katie created an Instagram reel with some pictures from our time in Michigan earlier this month (and late the previous month). It was a hectic trip &amp;mdash; our son was exposed to COVID right before we went, so we delayed, and then my aunt and uncle visiting there tested positve, and we thought my Mom had COVID&amp;hellip; &amp;mdash; but a very good one, especially looking back. It was an eye-opening one.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New podcast episode! Not good, not bad - A discussion about social media in education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/21/new-podcast-episode-not-good-not-bad-a-discussion-about-social-media-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/21/new-podcast-episode-not-good-not-bad-a-discussion-about-social-media-in-education/</guid>
      <description>For the first time in some time, there&amp;rsquo;s a new episode of my podcast with Ryan Estrellado, About Practice. Here&amp;rsquo;s an overview of the podcast:&#xA;In this episode, Ryan and Josh speak with Jeff Carpenter and Catharyn Shelton about their recent article on education influencers (co-authored with Stephanie Schroeder). Jeff, Catharyn, and Stephanie&amp;rsquo;s article is &amp;ldquo;The education influencer: A new player in the educator professional landscape&amp;rdquo; and was published in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education earlier this year: https://www.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper - intro to a special section of on data science education across the disciplines in the journal BJET</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/13/new-paper-introduction-to-a-special-section-on-data-science-education-across-the-disciplines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/13/new-paper-introduction-to-a-special-section-on-data-science-education-across-the-disciplines/</guid>
      <description>More than a year ago, Shiyan Jiang and Victor Lee and I came together and chose to propose a special section on data science education across disciplines (like a special issue, but slightly different, and primarily for journals that are online only). We wrote a proposal that was accepted and then shared a call for papers (here). The central tenet was that there is a need for (and value in) understanding and supporting teaching and learning data science across fields - not only in, for instance, mathematics education settings, but also in science and even English/language arts and art education contexts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coverage in EdWeek of a recent article on uncertainty in science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/coverage-in-edweek-of-a-recent-article-on-uncertainty-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/coverage-in-edweek-of-a-recent-article-on-uncertainty-in-science/</guid>
      <description>I was caught off guard when I received a message around two weeks ago from a reporter at EdWeek, one of if not the largest organizations for news related to education. A reporter, Sarah Sparks, came across my recent article with Marcus Kubsch, E.-J. Wagenmakers, and Mine Dogucu. That article is available open-access here: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11191-022-00341-3. I can&amp;rsquo;t help but wonder whether its accessibility played a role in the article being noticed by EdWeek and Sarah Sparks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My favorite YouTube channel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/my-favorite-youtube-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/my-favorite-youtube-channel/</guid>
      <description>When my fam and I moved to Knoxville, I began to explore the outdoors options around the city. I ended up, of course, reading about Great Smoky Mountains National Park, in addition to the Cumberland Mountains. In the course of this research, I learned about the Adventure Archives YouTube channel - they had taken a rainy hike in the Smokies several years back&amp;mdash;two more since.&#xA;I loved their latest video so much that I wanted to support them, almost buying a t-shirt before realizing&amp;hellip; I don&amp;rsquo;t need another t-shirt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New chapter - Data Representations and Visualizations in Educational Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/new-chapter-data-representations-and-visualizations-in-educational-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/07/05/new-chapter-data-representations-and-visualizations-in-educational-research/</guid>
      <description>With Ting Dai and Michael Lawson, I wrote a chapter on data visualization. It is fr the Routledge Encyclopedia of Education. We actually wrote this a long time ago - way back in 2019!&#xA;In the chapter, we reviewed research on data visualizations, shared example visualizations, and provided R code to reproduce all of the graphs.&#xA;The Encyclopedia was on hold for awhile, and so we had to wait something we were proud to share.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New IES-funded project - Quantifying the Robustness of Causal Inferences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/24/new-ies-funded-project-quantifying-the-robustness-of-causal-inferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/24/new-ies-funded-project-quantifying-the-robustness-of-causal-inferences/</guid>
      <description>This project is still a ways off from starting, but I&amp;rsquo;m beginning a new IES-funded methodological project. This work is on quantifying the robustness of causal inferences in educational research. It builds on work that Ken Frank at Michigan State University did to develop a widely-used approach for doing just that: quantifying how sensitive an inference about an effect is to sources of bias. My role on this work has been to develop statistical software, including the konfound R package and Konfound-It!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New NSF-funded project - Investigating Self-Assessment Practices for Increasing Student Learning and Self-Efficacy in Two Institutional Contexts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/24/new-nsf-funded-project-investigating-self-assessment-practices-for-increasing-student-learning-and-self-efficacy-in-two-institutional-contexts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/24/new-nsf-funded-project-investigating-self-assessment-practices-for-increasing-student-learning-and-self-efficacy-in-two-institutional-contexts/</guid>
      <description>A new NSF-funded project led from start to finish by Alex Lishinski at UTK was awarded funding this week. This project involves designing and studying the use of self-assessment in undergraduate CS settings. A cool feature of the project is that it takes place at both UTK and PSSU, an outstanding community college with close relations with UTK. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to carry out this work and to see what we learn!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catching a fish after many attempts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/23/catching-a-fish-after-many-attempts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/23/catching-a-fish-after-many-attempts/</guid>
      <description>Around two years ago, my family and I saw someone fishing in the Tennessee River at the park and playground near our house. My son was interested, and though I am far from the most engaged parent indoors, I am happy to try to follow his outdoor interests where they lead. I was also interested in fishing.&#xA;My Dad had purchased a Ronco Pocket Fisherman a few years back, thinking we could use it while camping or even backpacking.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unexpected bear encounter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/20/bear-chase/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/20/bear-chase/</guid>
      <description>On a whim, we drove to the Elkmont Campground in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Our intent was to see the Synchronous Fireflies that mate - alight and in synchronicity - from around the last week of May through the middle of June. On the drive there, we decided that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t too far to drive to park at Clingman&amp;rsquo;s Dome (the highest point in the Smokies and the second-highest point in the Eastern United States) but to head away from the short trail to Clingman&amp;rsquo;s Dome itself, down the approximately 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in Science &amp; Education: Making sense of uncertainty in the science classroom</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/15/new-article-in-science-education-making-sense-of-uncertainty-in-the-science-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/15/new-article-in-science-education-making-sense-of-uncertainty-in-the-science-classroom/</guid>
      <description>With Marcus Kubsch, Eric-Jan (E-J) Wagenmakers, and Mine Dogucu, I wrote an article that has been in the works for awhile - it&amp;rsquo;s Making sense of uncertainty in the science classroom: A Bayesian approach published in the journal Science &amp;amp; Education.&#xA;Coming to this topic and writing this paper were both journeys. Some papers come together quickly and easily&amp;mdash;those that are at the end of a long chain of projects, collaborations, and papers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in BJET - the tech and data sources used in science classrooms</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/14/new-article-the-tech-and-data-sources-used-in-science-classrooms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/06/14/new-article-the-tech-and-data-sources-used-in-science-classrooms/</guid>
      <description>My colleagues Elizabeth Schultheis, Melissa Kjelvik, Aaron Reedy, and Omiya Sultana and my article, Big data, big changes? The technologies and sources of data used in science classrooms, was published in the British Journal of Educational Technology. This work involved surveying more than 300 science teachers&amp;mdash;predominantly but not exclusively users of the Data Nuggets resources that Elizabeth and Melissa have developed and the DataClassroom tool Aaron developed.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s the short take-away from quantitative (descriptive) and qualitative analyses: Teachers predominantly involve their students in analysing relatively small data sets that they collect.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parenting, care, grieving for others&#39; loss</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/27/parenting-care-grieving-for-others-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/27/parenting-care-grieving-for-others-loss/</guid>
      <description>Last Saturday, Katie attended the graduation for the high sc3hool at which she works. I woke up with my son around 7 am, puttering at home, and then riding our bikes around the neighborhood. We then went to an event at the World&amp;rsquo;s Fair Park in Knoxville&amp;mdash;a festival of books. We played in the splash pad, bought a snowcone, listened to an author share how she develops characters for her books (&amp;ldquo;Can you all name one thing you are scared of?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The OA fees are too damn high</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/23/the-oa-fees-are-too-damn-high/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/23/the-oa-fees-are-too-damn-high/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a paper with three great colleagues and a doctoral student here, and I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled to share it soon. It&amp;rsquo;s entitled Big Data, Big Changes? The Technologies and Sources of Data Used in Science Classrooms and it will be published in a special issue of the British Journal of Educational Technology on Data Science Across the Disciplines. The publishing process was good; reviews were constructively critical, making the work better, and the editors handling the paper were helpful and constructively critical, too (note: this special issue is co-edited by my colleagues Victor Lee and Shiyan Jiang; I was not involved with editing the article I co-authored to safeguard the review process).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exciting times for STEM education at UTK</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/16/exciting-times-for-stem-education-at-utk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/16/exciting-times-for-stem-education-at-utk/</guid>
      <description>I started at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville (UTK) in the fall of 2018. I had a funny title - Assistant Professor of STEM/Science. Indeed, the official title of my position has a backslash! There was not a clear definition of my role, but that suited me fine, allowing me to explore a range of science-, technology-, and data science-related interests.&#xA;But, there have been some frustrating elements of my position, too.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Little Kids, Big Adventures to be published by UT Press</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/06/little-kids-big-adventures-to-be-published-by-ut-press/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/06/little-kids-big-adventures-to-be-published-by-ut-press/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share that Little Kids, Big Adventures: Exploring the Cumberland Plateau, Tennessee Valley, and Great Smoky Mountains With Kids will be published by the University of Tennessee Press!&#xA;For some background, my wife Katie and I started to discuss writing a book that we wished existed&amp;mdash;one about exploring the many outdoors options around Knoxville with kids. We put up a website (linked above) and worked on a few chapters, sharing them with friends and family and generally having fun writing about what we&amp;rsquo;ve learned, imagining someone new to Knoxville while doing so.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More reflections on traveling to Germany</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/02/more-reflections-on-traveling-to-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/05/02/more-reflections-on-traveling-to-germany/</guid>
      <description>This is something like Part 3 of 3 (or, maybe Part 3 of more!). Here are Part 1 and Part 2, neither long.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m journeying home from Germany after a week away from home. It was an enriching trip, educational, enjoyable, even a bit restful (though I miss my son and wife very much).&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep this one short, mostly because I&amp;rsquo;m quite tired. Some reflections:&#xA;Traveling can be an incredible way to learn; what I learned in a week about Germany and Europe (and their history), food, and myself is hard to sum I am not really into museums, and I think that is okay; what I learned the most from were: ordering bread at bakeries; asking butchers which sausage are good for hiking; going to a football game; walking around a beautiful city around 5:00 pm I think the learning-related elements of travel can be augmented by reading (or watching videos about) about the region and country one to which one is traveling In general I want to reserve conference travel for trips to different (from what I know) places in the US&amp;mdash;and international trips I was surprised anxious about speaking German; I feel (over-)confident speaking Spanish, and was more confident speaking some Italian because of its similarities to Spanish, but I never had a single stressful moment around speaking German (I learned a little bit, but practically everyone with whom I interacted spoke English or was familiar with English-speaking travelers) Maybe this is due to COVID, but I can hardly recall a more rewarding week of travel.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on traveling to Germany</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/28/reflections-on-traveling-to-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/28/reflections-on-traveling-to-germany/</guid>
      <description>I had the opportunity to travel to Germany this past week. The cause was presenting at the LEAD Graduate School and Research Network at the University of Tuebingen&amp;rsquo;s bi-annual retreat. My friend and colleague at that university, Christian Fischer, invited me, and I was excited to accept the invitation. I presented one of five keynote presentations.&#xA;In the weeks and days before traveling, I had some mixed feelings about travel. Our son has had a cold for the past few weeks, which taxed us; the weather in Knoxville was beautiful; and it was a lot to ask my wife to do while I traveled.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New chapter of Little Kids, Big Adventures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/26/new-chapter-of-little-kids-big-adventures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/26/new-chapter-of-little-kids-big-adventures/</guid>
      <description>A new draft chapter of Little Kids, Big Adventures is available. It is on Seven Islands State Birding Park, near Knoxville. See much more here: https://littlekidsbigadventures.com/seven-islands-loop-trail.html</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at the LEAD Graduate School and Research Network Retreat</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/26/presentation-at-the-lead-graduate-school-and-research-network-retreat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/26/presentation-at-the-lead-graduate-school-and-research-network-retreat/</guid>
      <description>I am happy to be able to join and present at the LEAD Graduate School and Research Network retreat.&#xA;Slides for my presentation are here: https://joshuamrosenberg.com/lead-retreat-presentation-2022-04-27.pdf</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A social media reset</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/18/resetting-how-i-use-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/18/resetting-how-i-use-social-media/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr (too long didn&amp;rsquo;t read) I&amp;rsquo;m going to step back from social media: Facebook and Twitter I&amp;rsquo;m still going to post on my blog and you can stay in touch through subscribing via RSS or via e-mail The negatives Several things came together in my mind to make me decide that I needed to reset how I use social media:&#xA;Observing a friend quietly step back from social media Trying multiple times over the past year to take breaks from Twitter, to return days or weeks later Talking with friends/colleagues who studied social media, which made me think about how my social media feeds had inadvertently become &amp;ldquo;highlight reels&amp;rdquo; Noticing that when I took a few days off from social media, I seemed to be able to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; fairly quickly, though had I not taken that break, I would have checked many more times Noticing that I started to think about personal or professional achievements or milestones in the context of being able to share about them on Facebook or Twitter (in contrast to enjoying the achievement or milestones independent of sharing) Constantly checking my notifications after posting Discussing social media with my spouse and realizing that social media had become a source of anxiety (and even dread!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taking a Social Media Break</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/15/taking-a-social-media-break/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/15/taking-a-social-media-break/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m currently taking a social media break; I deactivated my Facebook and Twitter accounts. I&amp;rsquo;ve been tempted to post, but it also feels rejuvenating to be off for a bit. My plan is to revisit in early May - May 11 will have been one month.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Launching a Microcredential in Educational Data Analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/08/launching-a-microcredential-in-educational-data-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/08/launching-a-microcredential-in-educational-data-analytics/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be launching a microcredential (a non-credit bearing credential granted by the University) in educational data analytics with my colleague at UTK, Louis Rocconi. A nice description of microcredentials is available here; in brief:&#xA;A micro-credential is a short, competency-based recognition that allows an educator to demonstrate mastery in a particular area.&#xA;These don&amp;rsquo;t just apply to educators; a common microcredential in the data science world is the Data Science Specialization offered through Johns Hopkins University/Coursera; many data scientists got their start with the statistical software and programming language R through these (awesome) courses that lead to a non-credit bearing certificate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the role of data science in K-12 teaching and learning?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/03/24/what-is-the-role-of-data-science-in-k-12-teaching-and-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/03/24/what-is-the-role-of-data-science-in-k-12-teaching-and-learning/</guid>
      <description>Slides for my presentation on &amp;lsquo;What is the role of data science in K-12 (pre-collegiate) teaching and learning?&amp;rsquo; for the Mathematics Department&amp;rsquo;s Statistics and Data Science seminar are available here: https://joshuamrosenberg.com/data-sci-role-in-edu.pdf</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who&#39;s reading Data Science in Education Using R?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/12/30/who-s-reading-data-science-in-education-using-r-google-analytics-as-a-lens/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/12/30/who-s-reading-data-science-in-education-using-r-google-analytics-as-a-lens/</guid>
      <description>When my co-authors Ryan, Emily, Isabella, and Jesse and I wrote a book, Data Science in Education Using R, we were inspired by the authors of other books (e.g., R4DS) within the R universe who made their contents freely-available&amp;mdash;in addition to publishing a version that could be purchased in print or eBook formats.&#xA;Routledge/Taylor &amp;amp; Francs&amp;ndash;specifically our wonderful editor Hannah Shakespeare&amp;ndash;supported us in doing this, something for which we were grateful.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at Knox County Schools DLD - Analyzing and Interpreting Scientific Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/11/02/presentation-at-knox-county-schools-district-learning-day-analyzing-and-interpreting-scientific-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/11/02/presentation-at-knox-county-schools-district-learning-day-analyzing-and-interpreting-scientific-data/</guid>
      <description>With Aaron Reedy, I worked with Knox County Schools teachers on the practice of analyzing and interpreting scientific data.&#xA;Presenters: Joshua Rosenberg (University of Tennessee) and Aaron Reedy (DataClassroom)&#xA;Session Title: Analyzing and Interpreting Scientific Data With DataClassroom&#xA;Description: While there are many technology tools that are suitable for analyzing and interpreting scientific data, not all are ideal for teaching and learning—especially science teaching and learning. In this session, we will introduce some general strategies you can use to help your students to analyze and interpret data regardless of the tool you use.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Programs in educational data science and learning analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/29/programs-in-educational-data-science-and-learning-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/29/programs-in-educational-data-science-and-learning-analytics/</guid>
      <description>Here is a list of programs in educational data science and learning analytics (and/or related disciplines):&#xA;M.S., Learning Analytics, Teachers College: https://www.tc.columbia.edu/human-development/learning-analytics/ Graduate Certificate, Learning Analytics, University of Florida: https://education.ufl.edu/educational-technology/online-certificates/learning-analytics/ (starts F22) Graduate Certificate, Learning Analytics, North Carolina State University: https://ced.ncsu.edu/graduate/programs/certificate/learning-analytics/ M.S., Education Data Science, Stanford Graduate School of Education: https://ed.stanford.edu/eds M.S., Learning Analytics, University of Texas at Arlongton: https://www.uta.edu/academics/schools-colleges/science/departments/psychology/degree-programs/graduate/ms-in-learning-analytics Specialization, Educational Data Science, University of Oregon: https://education.uoregon.edu/specialization-educational-data-science M.S., Educational Psychology: Learning Analytics, University of Wisconsin: https://learninganalytics.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Powers&#39; Bewilderment </title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/28/review-of-powers-bewilderment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/28/review-of-powers-bewilderment/</guid>
      <description>I finished reading Richard Powers&amp;rsquo; novel Bewilderment. It was, I think, the first fiction book I&amp;rsquo;ve read in years. I read it on the targeted, spot-on recommendation of Katie (my wife!). Reading it, I found myself saying noticing that I was experiencing some things that I almost never experienced reading non-fiction&amp;mdash;what I typically read. There were several points at which I think I literally said WOW out loud (something I definitely have done not when reading non-fiction).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Against U.S. News and World Report&#39;s Educational Rankings</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/13/against-u-s-news-and-world-report-s-educational-rankings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/13/against-u-s-news-and-world-report-s-educational-rankings/</guid>
      <description>The U.S. News and World Report has long-produced rankings of post-secondary educational institutions in the U.S. and they recently have created rankings for high schools and&amp;mdash;this year&amp;mdash;elementary and middle schools.&#xA;On 10/8, I thought UTK Chancellor Donde Plowman struck the right note regarding the release of the 2022 rankings of post-secondary institutions:&#xA;We are not a great university because of our high-ranking programs. We have high-ranking programs because we are a great university.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;ve been reading: Crazy for the Storm and Called Again</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/07/what-i-ve-been-reading-crazy-for-the-storm-and-called-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/10/07/what-i-ve-been-reading-crazy-for-the-storm-and-called-again/</guid>
      <description>My wife Katie recently bought two books for me at our library&amp;rsquo;s annual sale. I loved both and am ever-briefly reviewing them here.&#xA;Crazy for the Storm: A Memoir of Survival by Normal Ollestad&#xA;This is a book about an 11-year-old who was in a plane crash and about his survival of the crash - and the loss of his father and his father&amp;rsquo;s girlfriend. I can sum the story up succinctly or better by stating that it is a book about parenting.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Article in Phi Delta Kappan on what schools should know about social media and student privacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/28/article-in-phi-delta-kappan-on-what-schools-should-know-about-social-media-and-student-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/28/article-in-phi-delta-kappan-on-what-schools-should-know-about-social-media-and-student-privacy/</guid>
      <description>With Macy Burchfield (undergraduate at UTK), Conrad Borchers and Christian Fischer (undergraduate and faculty at the University of Tubingen), Benjamin Gibbons (underraduate at Emory), and Daniel Anderson (faculty at the University of Oregon), I wrote a short article building on our International Conference on Educational Data Mining presentation (that won the Best Poster Award for the conference). The article is intended primarily for administrators/educational leaders. It is secondarily for researchers and analysts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Cumberland Plateau</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/27/understanding-the-cumberland-plateau/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/27/understanding-the-cumberland-plateau/</guid>
      <description>I taught at a high school (and went to college) in North Carolina and the drive from North Carolina to my family in Michigan usually took me through the highway that winds down from around Asheville, past Candler, and through the heart of the outhern Appalachian mountains. The Appalachian Trail crosses the highway - I-40 - and at different points along the drive one is between a few and five or so miles from the Smokies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New comment in JRST: Open for whom?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/26/new-comment-in-jrst-open-for-whom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/26/new-comment-in-jrst-open-for-whom/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a comment with my colleagues Aaron Kessler and Rasheda Likely on open science in science education. The paper is titled Open for whom? The need to define open science for science education. The paper takes a constructively critical stance on open science, arguing that open science reforms need to advance in such a way that they meet the aims of the science education research&amp;ndash;and the wider science education&amp;ndash;communities/systems.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated pre-print: Toward a Bayesian perspective for science learners</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/23/updated-pre-print-toward-a-bayesian-perspective-for-science-learners/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/23/updated-pre-print-toward-a-bayesian-perspective-for-science-learners/</guid>
      <description>With Marcus Kubsch, E.-J. Wagenmakers, and Mine Dogucu, I&amp;rsquo;ve updated our pre-print that argues that a Bayesian perspective can be used by science teachers and learners, especially when science learners are engaged in reasoning / arguing / analyzing and interpreting data in light of uncertainty.&#xA;The pre-print&amp;ndash;Why and How a Bayesian Approach Supports Science Educators and Learners to Reason Under Scientific Uncertainty&amp;ndash;is here: https://osf.io/aznyq/&#xA;In this version, we focused on steps to make a Bayesian approach practical.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward winter!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/21/toward-winter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/21/toward-winter/</guid>
      <description>Today - specifically, 3:20 pm EST - is the autumnal equinox. For every day between now and the winter solstice (at 10:58 am EST), the days are becoming shorter, but by a smaller and smaller amount each day. I am not typically excited about winter, but I a this year, maybe in light of the challenges of this summer and fall. Last fall I ran with a friend from the Elkmont trailhead in the Smokies - at around 2,000 feet - to Clingman&amp;rsquo;s Dome, the highest point in the Smokies and the second highest point in the Eastern U.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use RStudio Cloud for Teaching With Caution</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/14/use-rstudio-cloud-for-teaching-with-caution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/14/use-rstudio-cloud-for-teaching-with-caution/</guid>
      <description>This past June, we used RStudio Cloud for the LASER Institute, an NSF-funded &amp;ldquo;institute&amp;rdquo; for early- and mid-career researchers interested in data science and learning analytics techniques.&#xA;On the first day, we experienced - and heard from participants about their experiences with a &amp;ldquo;getting started&amp;rdquo; task concerning - an issue with using RMarkdown documents within RStudio Cloud. In short, RMarkdown documents cannot be used interactively within RStudio Cloud. More specifically, if you re-run a code chunk in an RMarkdown document - think something like clicking the green arrow to the right of the code chunk twice - there stands a chance that the R session will disconnect.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on possibly, maybe contracting COVID (while vaccinated)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/12/possibly-maybe-contracting-covid-while-vaccinated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/09/12/possibly-maybe-contracting-covid-while-vaccinated/</guid>
      <description>This is a strange post for me following a strange series of days. On Thursday of last week, I felt a bit off, noticing that I had coughed a few times during the day, had a bit of a headache and a runny nose and just the slightest congested in my chest. I also couldn&amp;rsquo;t/didn&amp;rsquo;t sneeze, which is weird for me (don&amp;rsquo;t laugh!). The way the symptoms came on was such that I didn&amp;rsquo;t consider it was COVID until I noticed what all of the symptoms together might suggest.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why it can be hard to understand the Smokies (and a bit on my understanding of them)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/21/a-bunch-of-thoughts-on-the-tennessee-side-of-the-great-smoky-mountains-national-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/21/a-bunch-of-thoughts-on-the-tennessee-side-of-the-great-smoky-mountains-national-park/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to work on Little Kids, Big Trips in Knoxville, an open book, for awhile, but like for several (work-related and other) things, I have dropped the ball a bit. To get the ball rolling, I&amp;rsquo;m going to share a few thoughts on why it can be hard to understand the Smokies as well as a bit of what I&amp;rsquo;ve come to understand about them.&#xA;Why it can be hard to understand the Smokies The Smokies can be a bit hard to get one&amp;rsquo;s head around at first.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at ICER 2021</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/20/presentation-at-icer-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/20/presentation-at-icer-2021/</guid>
      <description>With Alex Lishinski, I presented at the International Computing Education Research conference on a recent study we carried out using our take on the use of the Experience Sampling Method (ESM).&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&#xA;There are significant participation gaps in computing, and the way to address these participation gaps lies not simply in getting students from underrepresented groups into a CS1 classroom, but supporting students to pursue their interest in computing further beyond CS1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working on a new project on analyzing data from . . . low-earth satellites</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/20/working-on-a-new-project-on-analyzing-data-from-low-earth-satellites/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/20/working-on-a-new-project-on-analyzing-data-from-low-earth-satellites/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interview for Tennessee News Service on Students&#39; Privacy and Facebook</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/16/short-interview-for-tennessee-news-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/16/short-interview-for-tennessee-news-service/</guid>
      <description>I was interviewed for a short news update for Tennessee News Service on my study of how school&amp;rsquo;s posts on Facebook could threaten student privacy that was shared on public radio in Tennessee. Audio for the story is here: https://www.publicnewsservice.org/cuts/75/rss-75345-1.mp3</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BJET Special Section CFP - Data Science Education Across the Disciplines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/13/bjet-special-section-cfp-data-science-education-across-the-disciplines/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/13/bjet-special-section-cfp-data-science-education-across-the-disciplines/</guid>
      <description>With Shiyan Jiang and Victor Lee, I am editing a special section of the British Journal of Educational Technology on Data Science Education Across the Disciplines.&#xA;Here is an overview:&#xA;Data science is often described as the integration of computational and technological tools, statistical knowledge, and disciplinary expertise, and is a rapidly growing topic for dedicated study during post-secondary education (e.g., National Academies of Science, Engineering, &amp;amp; Medicine, 2018). Increasingly, we are seeing new efforts are underway in many places to bring data science to primary and secondary education.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roan Mountain Magic</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/13/roan-mountain-magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/13/roan-mountain-magic/</guid>
      <description>Back in April, I ended up camping and backpacking a bunch, especially with our little one, and it was great. Then summer stress began, and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t made it out much from June - July. But, I&amp;rsquo;ve now been out four times in the last month, including to Roan Mountain, which was reinvigorating in a way that past trips were not.&#xA;It is, in short, a magical place, and that&amp;rsquo;s really all I have to say for now.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Practice Episode 7 - Move Close to Your Router (Dr. Ji Son, Part 1)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/09/about-practice-episode-7-move-close-to-your-router-dr-ji-son-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/09/about-practice-episode-7-move-close-to-your-router-dr-ji-son-part-1/</guid>
      <description>In this episode that is part one of a two-part interview, Josh and Ryan speak with Dr. Ji Son (@cogscimom on Twitter) at California State University, Los Angeles about learning through finding connections between concepts - and how ideas generated through research could be translated into practical forms for education. They also discuss hijinks at a large educational research conference.&#xA;Listen to the episode/interview here: https://anchor.fm/about-practice/episodes/7-Move-Close-to-Your-Router-Dr--Ji-Son--Part-1-e15ko40&#xA;(Please listen, subscribe, and share!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Workshop on a LASER Focus on Understanding and Improving STEM Education on August 11—No Fee, Register Now</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/06/workshop-on-a-laser-focus-on-understanding-and-improving-stem-education-on-august-11-no-fee-register-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/06/workshop-on-a-laser-focus-on-understanding-and-improving-stem-education-on-august-11-no-fee-register-now/</guid>
      <description>This is via AERA.&#xA;Instructors Shaun B. Kellogg, North Carolina State University Shiyan Jiang, North Carolina State University Hollylynne S. Lee, North Carolina State University Rob Moore, University of Florida Joshua M. Rosenberg, University of Tennessee, Knoxville About the Workshop This workshop will introduce participants to the Learning Analytics (LA), an emerging research and teaching field sitting at the intersection of Learning (e.g. educational technology, learning and assessment sciences), Analytics (e.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summer stress</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/05/summer-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/05/summer-stress/</guid>
      <description>We moved around two weeks ago, which is really thrilling. Also, Katie began a school librarian position at L&amp;amp;N STEM Academy, a fantastic and unique public magnet school in Knox County Schools last week, which is also really thrilling. And, so . . . this summer has been so good! And it has been stressful.&#xA;Last weekend, I took our little camping while Katie worked at home to set up the house.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The privilege of the tenure track for some</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/04/the-privilege-of-the-tenure-track-and-going-one-s-own-way-when-one-can/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/04/the-privilege-of-the-tenure-track-and-going-one-s-own-way-when-one-can/</guid>
      <description>Tenure is a privilege, perhaps one that cannot be sustained indefinitely in its present form in our current society (at the University of Tennessee, we presently have a posttenure review process), but being on the tenure track is also a privilege, especially if one is privileged in other (financial and identity-related) ways, as I am.&#xA;This is to say that as I begin my fourth year as a pre-tenure (but tenure track) faculty member, I commit to doing more of the following:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on Students&#39; Work With Data at the Knox County Schools District Learning Day</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/03/presentation-on-students-work-with-data-at-the-knox-county-schools-district-learning-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/03/presentation-on-students-work-with-data-at-the-knox-county-schools-district-learning-day/</guid>
      <description>From 10:15 - 11:15 am, I&amp;rsquo;ll be at the Knox County Schools District Learning Day for Science Teachers presenting on Tools and Strategies to Work with Data in the Science Classroom&#xA;This session will be focused on a need all science teachers have …relevant data for the science classroom. Using CODAP, Common Online Data Analysis Platform, teachers will learn how to use this platform so we can access tools and relevant data for our science classrooms.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I have learned about how I use social media</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/01/what-i-have-learned-about-how-i-use-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/08/01/what-i-have-learned-about-how-i-use-social-media/</guid>
      <description>When we moved from Lansing, MI, to Knoxville, TN, in 2018, I started exploring ways of using social media that were less distracting and more rewarding. The first thing I tried was drastic - I deleted almost all of my social media accounts. Having had the same Facebook account since my first year of college (in 2006), and a Twitter and LinkedIn account from roughly the same time, I figured I was ready for a fresh start.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loving Knoxville</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/22/loving-knoxville/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/22/loving-knoxville/</guid>
      <description>Our fam just crossed the three-year mark for living in Knoxville. This is half the time that Katie and I lived in Lansing, which we loved. Moving to Knoxville has been good. The last three years have been years of maturing, challenge, and accomplishment, especially for Katie, but also for me. After traveling to Michigan to visit family last month, I have been thinking a lot about Knoxville - what I like about it, what I do not like about it, and what our plans are here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Natural Language Processing in Science Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/19/an-introduction-to-natural-language-processing-in-science-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/19/an-introduction-to-natural-language-processing-in-science-education/</guid>
      <description>I presented a short workshop today on &amp;lsquo;An Introduction to Natural Language Processing in Science Education&amp;rsquo; at IPN – Leibniz Institute for Science and Mathematics Education. This follows on the workshop I carried out in early May at the Machine Learning and Computer-Based Text Analysis conference.&#xA;Thank you Marcus Kubsch for the invitation and thank you to Christina Krist for helping to plan this and presenting the next workshop in this three-part series.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s the point of Krishnamurthi and Fisler (2020)?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/12/what-s-the-point-of-krishnamurthi-and-fisler-s-2020-paper-on-data-centricity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/12/what-s-the-point-of-krishnamurthi-and-fisler-s-2020-paper-on-data-centricity/</guid>
      <description>This post is alt peer review. I describe my rationale for exploring alt peer review in a previous post; consider checking that out, first. In that post about what I mean by the question, &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s the point?&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s not pejorative!&#xA;The paper I read and am writing about is:&#xA;Krishnamurthi, S., &amp;amp; Fisler, K. (2020). Data-centricity: a challenge and opportunity for computing education. Communications of the ACM, 63(8), 24-26.&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s available from the ACM here and as a pre-print here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alt peer review (via blogs and newsletters)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/11/alt-peer-review-via-blogs-and-newsletters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/07/11/alt-peer-review-via-blogs-and-newsletters/</guid>
      <description>This post serves as an introduction to my interest in an alternative model of peer review; alt peer review.&#xA;First, I like peer review. Really! I can&amp;rsquo;t say how many times a paper I reviewed ends up being a paper I draw from in my work. That thought makes me think I should read and engage with more papers. Also, I like publishing papers. It&amp;rsquo;s a rewarding, if not (too) long process, and having one&amp;rsquo;s work be published in a journal&amp;mdash;especially one that others or many in one&amp;rsquo;s professional field peruse or read&amp;mdash;is an accomplishment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taking a work (and social media) break</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/06/26/taking-a-social-media-break/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/06/26/taking-a-social-media-break/</guid>
      <description>I have so much to be grateful for, and also this year has been hard, and I am going to try to take as much of a work (and social media) break as I can in July. That is all for now!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do people think about the NGSS and what can public sentiment tell us about how the NGSS are being implemented?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/06/17/what-do-people-think-about-the-ngss-and-what-can-public-sentiment-tell-us-about-how-the-ngss-are-being-implemented/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/06/17/what-do-people-think-about-the-ngss-and-what-can-public-sentiment-tell-us-about-how-the-ngss-are-being-implemented/</guid>
      <description>With my colleagues Conrad Borchers, Elizabeth Dyer, Daniel Anderson, and Christian Fischer, I published a paper on understanding public sentiment about the NGSS (and contrasting this with public sentiment about another large-scale reform in education, the Common Core State Standards.&#xA;The paper is Understanding Public Sentiment About Educational Reforms: The Next Generation Science Standards on Twitter and is published open-access (accessible by anyone - thanks to support from the UTK Libraries Open Publishing Support Fund!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A grab-bag of thoughts for a first-time NSF panelist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/12/a-grab-bag-of-thoughts-for-a-first-time-nsf-panelist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/12/a-grab-bag-of-thoughts-for-a-first-time-nsf-panelist/</guid>
      <description>This is an informal post; as much a reflection as something that may actually be useful to others. This post is on some thoughts on being an NSF panelist for a review panel. It&amp;rsquo;s written after having served on three panels - one face-to-face, and two online - and feeling like I have something to say, though I&amp;rsquo;m unsure what, just yet. This is sort of written for someone interested in serving as a panelist or someone serving for the first time looking for some thoughts from someone relatively new to the process (and so aware of the questions/concerns I had).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and parenting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/07/structure-and-parenting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/07/structure-and-parenting/</guid>
      <description>What an odd title for a post! Moreover, sometimes I know that I&amp;rsquo;m writing something that is not even half-baked and that I&amp;rsquo;ll look back on in embarrassment. Nevertheless . . .&#xA;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve been noodling on this past semester is how different structures - having to be somewhere at a particular time or for a certain duration of time or taking responsibility for something, for example - require me to do certain things.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Workshop on Machine Learning in Science Education Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/05/workshop-on-machine-learning-in-science-education-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/05/05/workshop-on-machine-learning-in-science-education-research/</guid>
      <description>I was invited by my colleague Marcus Kubsch at IPN in Kiel, Germany to lead a workshop on machine learning in science education research as part of the Machine Learning and Computer-Based Text Analysis conference.&#xA;The workshop description is here:&#xA;Machine learning includes a wide range of methods and software tools, but it is possible to get started with applying machine learning methods in relatively short order through the use of R.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prep a CSV from an Otter.AI transcript exported as a plain text file</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/28/prep-a-csv-from-an-otter-ai-transcript-exported-as-a-plain-text-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/28/prep-a-csv-from-an-otter-ai-transcript-exported-as-a-plain-text-file/</guid>
      <description>Otter is a service for transcribing audio. It works pretty well as a starting point for transcription (though definitely needs some careful checking). I’ve been using it for an interview-based research project.&#xA;One feature that could be added is the ability to export the transcript in a more usable form; particularly, as a CSV file - one which can easily be opened using spreadsheet and other software (e.g., R, if one wanted to carry out an automated/an NLP analysis).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A difference between backpacking with and without little ones</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/18/a-difference-between-backpacking-with-and-without-little-ones/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/18/a-difference-between-backpacking-with-and-without-little-ones/</guid>
      <description>Two weeks ago, I backpacked with my three-year-old for the first time. It was exhuberant and exhausting. This weekend, I backpacked with friends. It was amazing in that we got along well and hiked more than twice as far - and many multiples greater elevation (yesterday, we hiked from Cade&amp;rsquo;s Cove to Spence Field/Rocky Top/Thunderhead, and camped at the Spence Field shelter; with my little one, we hiked from Abrams Ranger Station to Backcountry Site #17, Little bottoms).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brief presentation on data science in and for education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/16/brief-presentation-on-data-science-in-and-for-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/16/brief-presentation-on-data-science-in-and-for-education/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m presenting on data science in and for education&amp;mdash;the former being a methodology, and the latter more of a context for learning (like science education).&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s for the Dean&amp;rsquo;s Advisory Board Meeting today.&#xA;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Cs8g4EnPygDQyVb26KjTE1bhm2Pr4fbDL_mQXmMEN18/edit?usp=sharing</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A very good example of Bayes in science education - Kubsch et al. (2021)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/15/a-very-good-example-of-bayes-in-science-education-kubsch-et-al-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/15/a-very-good-example-of-bayes-in-science-education-kubsch-et-al-2021/</guid>
      <description>I recently read Kubsch and colleague&amp;rsquo;s (2021) paper in Practical Assessment, Research, and Evaluation, and it is revelatory. It not only introduces Bayesian statistical methods in the context of science education research, it shows: a) a case in which prior knowledge can be meaningfully brought to bear upon the analysis and b) how the use of a prior can be critiqued/compared with the effects of a less informative prior. It also compares the analysis to the frequentist approach nicely.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posts on Facebook by Schools and Districts and the Potential Risks to Students’ Privacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/13/request-for-feedback-posts-on-facebook-by-schools-and-districts-and-the-potential-risks-to-students-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/13/request-for-feedback-posts-on-facebook-by-schools-and-districts-and-the-potential-risks-to-students-privacy/</guid>
      <description>Based on work by UTK student Macy Burchfield, my colleagues and I have written an article targeted toward administrators and educators working in schools and districts on the findings from our research and what we recommend can be done to reduce the risks to students&amp;rsquo; privacy.&#xA;We posted a pre-print of this here: https://osf.io/ujyg2/&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s the abstract:&#xA;For many if not posts schools and districts around the United States, the use of Facebook has emerged as a novel communication practice that serves several purposes, including sharing timely information, building a sense of community, and highlighting staff and students.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Workshop and presentations at NARST, AERA, and LAK</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/12/workshop-and-presentations-at-narst-aera-and-lak-oh-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/12/workshop-and-presentations-at-narst-aera-and-lak-oh-my/</guid>
      <description>Our research group had a number of presentations at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching (NARST), American Educational Research Association (AERA), and Learning Analytics and Knowledge (LAK) conferences over the past few weeks. Some details on those presentations (and, when pertinent, links to materials) are below. Kudos to students who presented during a very unusual conference seasons. And, thank you to the organizers of each of these for putting them on (again, during an unsual-and difficult-time for a conference).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ups and downs of parenting - summarizing an &#34;up&#34;!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/09/the-ups-and-downs-of-parenting-summarizing-an-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/09/the-ups-and-downs-of-parenting-summarizing-an-up/</guid>
      <description>This isn&amp;rsquo;t a new idea, but one thing I&amp;rsquo;ve thinking about parenting is that in some ways it accentuates normal activities. A car ride isn&amp;rsquo;t just a car ride; it&amp;rsquo;s a rollicking sing along or a chance to see a &amp;ldquo;BUS!&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;CHOO CHOO TRAIN!&amp;rdquo;. A hike isn&amp;rsquo;t just a two-mile walk; it&amp;rsquo;s an epic adventure, leading to trips and falls and adventures near/into the river. And, relaxing isn&amp;rsquo;t relaxing. It&amp;rsquo;s&amp;hellip; something got on my shirt!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dayenu</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/04/hiking-dayenu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/04/04/hiking-dayenu/</guid>
      <description>This spring has been challenging in many ways. The Jewish holiday of Passover was during a busy, challenging part of a busy, challenging spring. It was timely for me in that my family connected and we had the chance to think a bit about things for which we are thankful (sorry, matzo is not one of them).&#xA;One part of the Passover dinner and service - the Sedar - is, for my family, singing the song Dayenu.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - #Mathathome during the COVID-19 Pandemic - Exploring and Reimagining Resources and Social Supports for Parents</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/03/18/new-article-mathathome-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-exploring-and-reimagining-resources-and-social-supports-for-parents/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/03/18/new-article-mathathome-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-exploring-and-reimagining-resources-and-social-supports-for-parents/</guid>
      <description>My colleague Frances Harper led a survey and data mining study of how parents and caretakers helped their children to continue to learn at home during the pandemic. Frances involved me in the analysis of social media data, and it was a great opportunity for me to work with Frances as well as a talented and fun research team.&#xA;We found through our analysis of responses from a moderately large number of parents that they worked to continue to engage their children in learning mathematics, especially through engaging with mathematics in everyday life, and that they used resources that their children&amp;rsquo;s teachers provided and those they identified on their own.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What administrators and educators should consider considering when posting from institutional Facebook accounts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/03/13/what-administrators-and-educators-should-consider-considering-when-posting-from-institutional-facebook-accounts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/03/13/what-administrators-and-educators-should-consider-considering-when-posting-from-institutional-facebook-accounts/</guid>
      <description>Background/Context The title of this post is joking, but is a reflection of my hesitancy to make strong recommendations about, well, anything education-related. But I&amp;rsquo;ll try to make a moderately strong case here. The quick back story is that Macy Burchfield, an undergraduate student at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, led the analysis of data and the writing up of a study on students&amp;rsquo; privacy in the context of K-12 schools&amp;rsquo; and districts&#39; posts on Facebook.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New paper - Balancing open science and privacy in the context of learning analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/25/new-paper-balancing-open-science-and-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/25/new-paper-balancing-open-science-and-privacy/</guid>
      <description>Background I recently co-authored a response to a valuable paper by Ifenthaler and Schumacher (2016) as a part of a special issue of Educational Technology Research &amp;amp; Development on &amp;ldquo;Shifting to Digital&amp;rdquo; in light of the COVID-19 pandemic with Bret Staudt Willet.&#xA;Here is a succinct description of the aims of the special issue:&#xA;This Special Issue is unique in that it will focus on multiple perspectives where respondent authors write about the implications of scholarship on addressing current challenges related to an increased focus of digital learning.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-COVID reflections</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/17/post-covid-reflections/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/17/post-covid-reflections/</guid>
      <description>It has been a weird last few weeks (since COVID got us!), but, thankfully, we&amp;rsquo;re all doing fine (with no lingering symptoms), and this post is an attempt to quickly reflect a bit on the last few weeks.&#xA;As time went on after Katie tested positively for COVID, I continued to take rapid tests (through CVS), repeatedly testing negative. Over this last weekend, my son and I both took rapid tests&amp;mdash;and tested negative, again.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My efforts at keeping up with educational research, development, and news</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/15/my-efforts-at-keeping-up-with-educational-research-development-and-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/15/my-efforts-at-keeping-up-with-educational-research-development-and-news/</guid>
      <description>My colleague and book co-author Ryan Estrellado and I have a new podcast, About Practice. It&amp;rsquo;s a podcast about the divide between research and practice in education and how those on either side of the divide can build bridges to the other. Check it out if you&amp;rsquo;re interested!&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s the first episode:&#xA;In an upcoming episode, we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss how we each keep up with educational research, development efforts and initiatives, and news.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making sense of COVID - it got us! But it won&#39;t get us</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/03/making-sense-of-covid-in-our-family/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2021/02/03/making-sense-of-covid-in-our-family/</guid>
      <description>One theme of this blog has been posting about things that I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to post about.&#xA;These are occasionally political, often professional (and maybe not that important), and fairly often personal. This one is in the last category and is an effort at making sense of COVID, specifically COVID in our family, with one big caveat that we are okay and are going to be okay. Posting here made more sense to me than posting on social media; that&amp;rsquo;s not to say this will be fleshed out or necessarily worthy of being a post, but here goes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elkmont Campground to Clingman&#39;s Dome</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/12/24/elkmont-campground-to-clingman-s-dome/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/12/24/elkmont-campground-to-clingman-s-dome/</guid>
      <description>Beginning late last week, I started to plan a hike-run to Mount LeConte for the holiday break with friends. We settled on Tuesday, because the weather was clear and relatively warm, with a high of around 45F in Knoxville (and around 30-35F in the National Park). On Monday, we learned that the main (in fact, I believe the only) road to take you to the top of the mountains, Newfound Gap road (highway 441), was closing due to high winds.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New chapter - Making data science count in and for education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/12/02/new-chapter-making-data-science-count-in-and-for-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/12/02/new-chapter-making-data-science-count-in-and-for-education/</guid>
      <description>Enilda Romero-Hall edited the book Research Methods in Learning Design and Technology (LDT), which was recently published by Routledge (available for purchase here).&#xA;I co-wrote a chapter led by Spencer Greenhalgh on considerations for using social media data in LDT research (available open-access from the book site here).&#xA;I also wrote a chapter on making data science count in and for education with Michael Lawson, Daniel Anderson, Seth Jones, and Teya Rutherford.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kituwa, NC</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/20/kituwa-nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/20/kituwa-nc/</guid>
      <description>My last post was about a fall outdoors. This post builds on that a bit. I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading three books that relate to the outdoors and this place:&#xA;An Indigenous Peoples&amp;rsquo; History of the United States On Trails Mountains of the Heart Each educated me. All three focus on the region in which I know find myself; one, On Trails, noted that many of the Cherokee people who lived here for centuries consider a place south of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Kituwa, to be their ancestral homeland.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A fall outdoors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/16/a-fall-outdoors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/16/a-fall-outdoors/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a blog post more than a week ago on feeling like we’ve (started to) arrive to Knoxville; a big part of the reason why has been the chance to spend time as a family outdoors—a silver lining of a difficult year. I think one or two of these dates may be inaccurate by a day or two (I mainly used pictures and recordings from Strava to recall them), but, I spent a bit of time capturing our walks and hikes, all except for three (Mt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moving to Knoxville, somewhere new</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/06/arriving-in-knoxville/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/11/06/arriving-in-knoxville/</guid>
      <description>A repeated theme of my blog is that I use it to share what I think, whether its political, personal, or . . . something else entirely. This post - like many! - is personal.&#xA;For whatever reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reflecting this fall on a specific winter from when we lived in Lansing, Michigan, when it was super, duper cold. There was a polar vortex, and temperatures were regularly (I remember in early January) -20F or colder.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book published! Data Science in Education Using R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/28/book-pub-lished-data-science-in-education-using-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/28/book-pub-lished-data-science-in-education-using-r/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve likely heard me post, talk, or share about the book that is now published, Data Science in Education Using R. I just wanted to compile a few things here:&#xA;The book is always available open-access here: https://www.datascienceineducation.com/ The book is available for purchase in soft or hardcover versions through Routledge (here) (use code BSE20 for 20% off); you can always find it on Amazon (here) or-we hope-your local and independent bookstore Third, a recording of our book launch from this past Monday is here A blurb on the book is here:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using a Shiny app to securely collect data for research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/19/using-a-shiny-app-to-securely-collect-data-for-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/19/using-a-shiny-app-to-securely-collect-data-for-research/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve used Shiny apps (interactive web application which you can create with R that use R code/packages) a number of times.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of one: http://konfound-it.com/&#xA;For a new project, it seemed like collecting data from people who use the app would be useful, and this seemed easy enough to do, and, in short, it is, especially if using an excellent tool like {shinylogs}. But there are a few challenges to overcome; one key one was that I was unable to find an existing package or technique that would work for apps hosted by RStudio&amp;rsquo;s hosting service, shinyapps.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impodster Syndrome podcast archive</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/15/impodster-syndrome-podcast-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/15/impodster-syndrome-podcast-archive/</guid>
      <description>When my graduate school friend Spencer Greenhalgh and I started our current positions more than two years ago, we began a podcast. Then, we became busy and stopped, and stopped paying for hosting. Just so these didn&amp;rsquo;t disappear forever, we archived them in a public Google Drive folder: https://drive.google.com/drive/u/4/folders/1fwSaEKt9QzJPUlf-CYVVwPgN-pKBaAkW&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ve often listened to these multiple times - it has been a fun way for me to remember back (not too long ago&amp;mdash;but still!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JRST Special Issue on Digital Ecologies to Appear, Reader Comments and Criticism Are Invited</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/15/jrst-special-issue-call/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/15/jrst-special-issue-call/</guid>
      <description>This message about a call for comments and criticisms on the recent special issue of JRST on digital ecologies for science learning was sent by NARST.&#xA;NARST, a global organization for improving science education through research, announces the publication and release of the Journal of Research in Science Teaching’s special issue: “Science Teaching, Learning, Assessment with 21st Century, Cutting-edge Digital Ecologies.”&#xA;The special issue is set to appear online Wednesday, October 14, 2020 as the November issue of JRST (57n9).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New course on data science methods in education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/08/new-course-on-data-science-methods-in-education-at-utk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/08/new-course-on-data-science-methods-in-education-at-utk/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be offering a new course on data science methods in education next semester.&#xA;A flyer for the course is here; some key deets:&#xA;TPTE 595 (MA) and TPTE 695 (PhD) Day/time: Thursday, 2:50 - 4:05 pm Modality: Online, partially synchronous Designed for students with no prior experience with R or data science Focused on education, but open to any graduate student in TPTE, CEHHS, and across the University Here is a bit more information from the proposal for the course:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brief presentation for the UTK STEM Education Research Community of Scholars</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/05/brief-presentation-for-the-utk-stem-education-research-community-of-scholars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/05/brief-presentation-for-the-utk-stem-education-research-community-of-scholars/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Lynn Hodge is leading a STEM Education Research Community of Scholars (see more, including how to join in and participate here.&#xA;With Dr. Frances Harper and Dr. Liz Derrberry, I am presenting a brief research update; here are my slides for that:&#xA;Thanks to UTK&amp;rsquo;s Office of Research and Engagement (and Dr. Diana Moyer) for supporting this new Community of Scholars!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in JRST: Idle chatter or compelling conversation? The potential of the social media‐based #NGSSchat network</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/28/new-article-in-jrst-idle-chatter-or-compelling-conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/28/new-article-in-jrst-idle-chatter-or-compelling-conversation/</guid>
      <description>This article is a long-time coming, and is one I&amp;rsquo;m very proud of. It is an analysis of the #NGSSchat network, one which involved qualitatively coding 1000s of posts sent to the hashtag (and 100s of profiles of those who posted to the network) and using social network analysis techniques namely multi-level selection models (and models for social influence) to show what many people who have participated in #NGSSchat may already know: It&amp;rsquo;s a good place to learn and share about science education and the new science education standards.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Almost) 30 months in the Smokies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/22/almost-30-months-in-the-smokies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/22/almost-30-months-in-the-smokies/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been saying for around a year that we&amp;rsquo;ve lived in Knoxville for two years, but we&amp;rsquo;re now less than a month from two-and-a-half years, or 30 months, in Knoxville. The thing I like most about living in Knoxville is the proximity to the Smoky Mountains and Great Smoky Mountain National Park. Knoxville is only 45 minutes from the National Park (at least the beginning of the Tremont and Abrams Creek areas; an hour to the Cosby area; and an hour and change to the Elkmont area).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A shana tova wake-up call</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/20/a-shana-tova-wake-up-call/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/20/a-shana-tova-wake-up-call/</guid>
      <description>Rosh Hashanah is a Jewish holiday for reflecting on the last year. We say L&amp;rsquo;shana Tova, happy new year, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a happy holiday, more a reflective one. Since around my Bar Mitzvah, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to think of Rosh Hashanah as a chance to take comfort, usually at an otherwise busy time of the year. This year is no different in both ways.&#xA;The high point of Rosh Hashanah is when the shofar (literally a ram&amp;rsquo;s horn) is sounded.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article on combining machine learning and qualitative methods to study students&#39; involvement in science practices</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/15/new-article-on-combining-machine-learning-and-qualitative-methods-to-study-students-involvement-in-science-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/15/new-article-on-combining-machine-learning-and-qualitative-methods-to-study-students-involvement-in-science-practices/</guid>
      <description>My colleague Christina Krist and I recently published an article on our efforts to combine machine learning and qualitative methods to study students&amp;rsquo; involvement in science practices. This work emerged from work that we began wayyy back 2015 (!!!), when we were both graduate students. At a meeting for the Science Practices project for which we were graduate students, Christina presented the results of a text-based automated analysis of written responses from students.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using the State-by-State Spending on Kids Dataset (and tidykids)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/08/using-the-state-by-state-spending-on-kids-dataset-and-tidykids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/08/using-the-state-by-state-spending-on-kids-dataset-and-tidykids/</guid>
      <description>The Urban Institute released a comprehensive dataset on state-by-state spending on kids from 1997-2016. That data is here. The authors of it deserve all of the credit for creating it and for releasing it in such an easy-to-use, accessible way. They also licensed it with a creative commons-like license that allows use- and re-use, including modification, with attribution. Therefore, I want to say (as I say in the documentation for the package that I describe a bit below) that the data was made available by and is attributable to Julia Isaacs, Eleanor Lauderback, and Erica Greenberg under the under the ODCAttributionLicense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Educational researchers responded pretty well to COVID-19, but maybe we could respond even better</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/05/educational-researchers-responded-to-covid-19-but-perhaps-we-could-respond-even-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/09/05/educational-researchers-responded-to-covid-19-but-perhaps-we-could-respond-even-better/</guid>
      <description>The provocation/thesis of this short post is that educational researchers responded pretty well to COVID-19, but perhaps we could respond even better.&#xA;I was surprised to hear that special issue calls for proposals for COVID-19-related research were inundated with proposals.&#xA;As two examples that I am familiar with:&#xA;The Journal of Technology and Teacher Education (JTATE) received more than 250 proposals, from which they published 35.&#xA;The Spencer Foundation received &amp;ldquo;a record-breaking 1,369 submissions&amp;rdquo;, from which they funded 20.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My experience with getting started with high-performance computing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/31/getting-started-with-a-high-performance-computing-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/31/getting-started-with-a-high-performance-computing-service/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I blog about things I&amp;rsquo;ve done a lot, like biking. Other times, this blog serves as as chance to try out new ideas, or to document how something worked one time, with the hope of building on it later, like in this post. This post is definitely in the latter category. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to use the high-performance computing service at my institution for around a year or more, but I was never able to really get the basics down to the point that I could reliably do what I wanted.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Participating in a new NSF-funded project - LASER (Learning Analytics in STEM Education Research) Institute ⚡</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/17/participating-in-the-laser-learning-analytics-in-stem-education-research-institute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/17/participating-in-the-laser-learning-analytics-in-stem-education-research-institute/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be collaborating with Shaun Kellogg, Hollylynne Lee, Shiyan Jiang, Rob Moore, and Mark Samberg. Specifically, I&amp;rsquo;m involved as a senior personnel member for the LASER (Learning Analytics in STEM Education Research) Institute. I&amp;rsquo;ll primarinly be involved in planning for and teaching during the weeklong summer institute.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m especially excited by the prospect of working with other STEM education researchers around the use of R. I&amp;rsquo;ll admit that learning analytics as a term and research discipline is new to me, but I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll have the ability to contribute in other ways (along the lines of the data science community with which I do identify).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Participating in a new NIH-funded project on enhancing STEM education in rural Appalachia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/09/participating-in-a-new-nih-funded-project-on-stem-education-in-rural-appalachia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/09/participating-in-a-new-nih-funded-project-on-stem-education-in-rural-appalachia/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be participating as a co-investigator^[NIH has atypical roles for those involved in grants] for a new NIH-funded project, Imagining Possibilities in post-secondary education and STEMM in rural Appalachia.&#xA;The co-principal investigators for the five-year project are Melinda Gibbons and Erin Harden, and this project extends an earlier NIH-funded project they led.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ll be contributing to the design of lessons that align with the Next Generation Science Standards (and the Tennessee Academic Standards for Science) and to planning summer research/investigation/science practice-focused (okay, we still have a lot of time to plan!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annual meeting presentation for our PICSUL project</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/07/annual-meeting-presentation-for-our-picsul-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/08/07/annual-meeting-presentation-for-our-picsul-project/</guid>
      <description>We had our annual meeting for our Pursuing Interest in Undergraduate Computer Science Learners (PICSUL) project. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to share as much of the project in an open way as possible, including all of the materials from the proposal.&#xA;In that spirit, a link to the presentation (Google Docs) is here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do we know about thinking, learning, and Bayesian methods? A short review of the literature</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/29/what-do-we-know-about-thinking-learning-and-bayesian-methods-a-short-review-of-the-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/29/what-do-we-know-about-thinking-learning-and-bayesian-methods-a-short-review-of-the-literature/</guid>
      <description>By Nathan Kenner and Joshua Rosenberg, University of Tennessee, Knoxville&#xA;Note: This is a first blog post in what we plan to be a series of posts on early-stage work on Bayesian methods in education by Nathan Kenner, Isabella Velásquez, [Marcus Kubsch](Marcus Kubsch), and me. It emerged from discussions with and incorporating feedback from Isabella Velásquez and Marcus Kubsch. It is a bit more formal than typical posts on this blog, but we intend for this to serve as a foundation for our later work (including shorter blog posts on similar topics and other products), and we hope that it elicits feedback and conversation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balancing student privacy with benefits to society? An informal pre-print for and request for feedback a response to a study by Ifenthaler and Schumaker</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/23/balancing-student-privacy-with-benefits-to-society-an-informal-pre-print-for-a-response-to-a-study-by-ifenthaler-and-schumaker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/23/balancing-student-privacy-with-benefits-to-society-an-informal-pre-print-for-a-response-to-a-study-by-ifenthaler-and-schumaker/</guid>
      <description>I am writing a short (around 1,000 word) response to a great study by Ifenthaler and Schumaler (2016) on student perceptions of privacy principles for learning analytics. I think the article is available here without a paywall: https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11423-016-9477-y&#xA;In the spirit of the article, I wanted to post the article for anyone to provide feedback on it. Since it&amp;rsquo;s such a short piece, posting it as a Google Doc (instead of on a server, like the one hosted by the Open Science Framework) seemed like it would suffice.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proposal for an educational data science course - request for feedback</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/22/proposal-for-an-educational-data-science-course-request-for-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/22/proposal-for-an-educational-data-science-course-request-for-feedback/</guid>
      <description>Building from a crowdsourced list of educational data science-related courses, I wrote a proposal for a course I hope to teach at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Data Science in Education Using R.&#xA;A description/roposal for the course is here: https://joshuamrosenberg.com/proposal-ds-in-edu-utk.pdf&#xA;I welcome feedback, especially at this stage where it could impact the likelihood that the course is offered&amp;mdash;or, if offered, useful to students. If you do have any feedback or suggestions, please message me at jmrosenberg AT utk dot edu&amp;hellip; or otherwise reach out!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some K-5 computing education resources (draft)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/08/some-k-5-computing-education-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/08/some-k-5-computing-education-resources/</guid>
      <description>Background This post includes some K-5 computing education (or computer science education or computational thinking- or coding-focused) resources. I&amp;rsquo;ll use the term computing education in this post to refer to these terms, recognizing that there are distinctions between them that matter a great deal for many purposes. This list is just a starting point and it is not exhaustive; there are likely better compendia; and, this is a new(ish) area for me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on the last six months</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/05/take-a-break/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/07/05/take-a-break/</guid>
      <description>This spring and the beginning of summer felt (and this year feels) impossible to summarize.&#xA;It started off a little personally tumultuous; beginning in October (of last year), our little one started to get colds&amp;mdash;we think from daycare. In mid-December, he had an ear infection, which started one of the most challening (in the context of everything ultimately being alright&amp;mdash;we were safe, cared for, and we had our jobs/incomes) periods&amp;hellip; at least of adulthood.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Participating (and presenting) in the 2020 ICLS Early Career Workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/18/participating-in-the-2020-icls-early-career-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/18/participating-in-the-2020-icls-early-career-workshop/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m participating in the 2020 International Conference of the Learning Sciences (ICLS) Early Career Workshop.&#xA;It has been great. Kudos to the organizers for still carrying out the workshop virtually.&#xA;Part is presenting on an in-progress project; I&amp;rsquo;m presenting on a project that is at a very early stage - trying to explore what role Bayesian methods may have for K-2 science teaching and learning. I prepared a short presentation (below).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basic {sf} functionality for analyzing and plotting geospatial data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/08/basic-sf-functionality-for-analyzing-and-plotting-geospatial-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/08/basic-sf-functionality-for-analyzing-and-plotting-geospatial-data/</guid>
      <description>This post has some information on using the {sf} (or simple features) R package for analyzing and plotting geospatial data. It is mostly for myself to reference in the future. A lot of this is from the Geocomputation With R book.&#xA;Loading packages, setting up Load the {sf} and {tidyverse} packages:&#xA;library(sf) library(tidyverse) Creating test data Create some test data. Here are five longitudes and latitudes. Two are special</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Healing from a broken heart</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/02/healing-from-a-broken-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/06/02/healing-from-a-broken-heart/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;re likely reading, seeing, or experiencing what is on the news, and feeling heartbroken.&#xA;I have only a little to add, but I do have something to.&#xA;Getting better is hard; healing from a serious injury is hard. One way to think about, America and the Constitution (the and Bill of Rights) is as a promise, or a dream. From the start, that promise was compromised. Enslaved men and women built America, and Americans killed the men and women who lived on the land on which the nation started.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practice, injustice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/29/practice-justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/29/practice-justice/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve struggled with words the past few days, feeling incapable of saying something that captured what I felt-perhaps because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to think. What is clearer to me now is that there are injustices that are alive and present and that I have a role in righting.&#xA;There are a number of practices I do that I&amp;rsquo;m proud of, but righting injustices has not been an active, present one.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Materials for an NSF BCSER proposal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/22/materials-for-nsf-bcser-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/22/materials-for-nsf-bcser-proposal/</guid>
      <description>To share in a neat and fairly-comprehensive proposal library from my institution, I gathered materials from the National Science Foundation&amp;rsquo;s Building Capacity in STEM Education Research program proposal I submitted (in last June; it was awarded soon after - in August).&#xA;I wrote a post on the project then (here).&#xA;The proposal library had examples from a number of disciplines (and for a number of funders), but did not have any for educational research.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-secondary courses related to data science in education - a crowdsourced list of sorts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/14/post-secondary-courses-related-to-data-science-in-education-a-crowdsourced-list-of-sorts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/14/post-secondary-courses-related-to-data-science-in-education-a-crowdsourced-list-of-sorts/</guid>
      <description>I solicited information baout courses related to data science in education, and ended up with more than I expected. This is a crowdsourced list, with courses spanning data science education (data science as a new context for teaching and learning) and the application of different data science methods to learning analytics and educational data mining:&#xA;Applied Social Network Analysis in Education (Bodong Chen) Learning Analytics: Theory and Practice (Bodong Chen) Carpe Datum (Yoav Bergner) Theoretical Foundations of Learning Analytics and Learning Analytics in Practice (forthcoming) (Nia Dowell and Shayan Doroudi) Data Science Specialization (five courses) (Daniel Anderson) Big Data and Education (Ryan Baker) Core Methods in Educational Data Mining (Charles Lang) Learning Analytics Fundamentals (George Siemens and colleagues) Data Science Education (and Data Science Education for pre-service teachers) (Victor Lee) Foundations of Learning Analytics and Educational Data Science (Alyssa Wise) Building Learning Analytics Applications (Alyssa Wise) Certificate Program in Learning Analytics (four courses) (Shaun Kellogg) Massive Open Online Course on Building Legitimate Predictive Analytics With Learning Design and Theory (forthcoming) (Erkan Er) Data Analysis, Simulation, and Programming in R (James Pustejovsky) Machine Learning in Education (Zach Pardos) Programming and Educational Data Science (forthcoming) (Fernando Rodriguez) Data Visualization (Cynthia D&amp;rsquo;Angelo) There are also a few compendia of courses:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Informal, Open Introduction to Using R Markdown in Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/10/a-free-open-workshop-on-using-r-markdown-for-data-science-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/10/a-free-open-workshop-on-using-r-markdown-for-data-science-in-education/</guid>
      <description>Like many things posted to the #rstats hashtag on Twitter, a recent post requesting resources related to using R Markdown led to a number of helpful ones. The post was in the context of learning R and R Markdown for research- related projects in education.&#xA;I shared many of the resources (and the post) with a graduate research assistant and thought about meeting one-on-one to review and walk through them. But, there are a few others at my institution who are also interested in learning R.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article on understanding engagement in out-of-school STEM programs using an experience sampling method to study youths&#39; experiences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/09/new-article-on-engagement-in-out-of-school-stem-programs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/09/new-article-on-engagement-in-out-of-school-stem-programs/</guid>
      <description>With Jen Schmidt, Patrick Beymer, Neil Naftzger, and Lee Shumow, I recently published an article on youth&amp;rsquo;s engagement in one of nine out-of-school, STEM- focused summer programs. The study uses an experience sampling method (or ESM) to study youth&amp;rsquo;s experiences, in which participating youth were asked multiple, short surveys &amp;ldquo;in- the-moment&amp;rdquo;, rather than one (or more) longer surveys at less-regular intervals. The logic is that such surveys can assess something like engagement in a qualitatively (and subjectively, for youth) different way than a traditional survey can.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article on exploring the validity of assessment items for the NGSS using machine learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/07/new-article-on-exploring-the-content-related-validity-of-assessment-items-for-the-ngss-using-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/07/new-article-on-exploring-the-content-related-validity-of-assessment-items-for-the-ngss-using-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>Daniel Anderson, Brock Rowley, Sondra Stegenga, and Shawn Irvin, and I published a paper on the role of a text-based machine learning technique - topic models - can be used to provide content validity evidence for Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS)-related assessment items.&#xA;While I have some experience with topic modeling, as well as experience with NGSS-related assessments, the measurement focus of this work was new to me, and so was a great opportunity for me to learn more; Dan and his colleagues conceptualized and carried out this work in an impressive way, and I was happy to contribute to it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Videos in the 2020 STEM For All Video Showcase</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/06/videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/05/06/videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase/</guid>
      <description>My colleagues submitted videos to the 2020 STEM for All Video Showcase for two projects:&#xA;Theory-based Computational Analysis of Classroom Video: https://stemforall2020.videohall.com/presentations/1667&#xA;![tca2-screenshot](/post/2020-05-06-videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase_files/Screen Shot 2020-05-06 at 9.19.28 AM.png)&#xA;Computer Science for Appalachia: https://stemforall2020.videohall.com/presentations/1730&#xA;![cs-for-appalachia-screenshot](/post/2020-05-06-videos-in-the-2020-stem-video-showcase_files/Screen Shot 2020-05-06 at 9.19.53 AM.png)&#xA;They&amp;rsquo;re short (three minutes or less) and intended to provide an overview of their respective projects. I&amp;rsquo;m proud of them and the work that went into them. Both projects are finishing their first year this summer, and so there will be (a lot) that I hope to share over the coming years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An update to how U.S. school districts are responding to COVID-19</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/04/25/update-to-how-u-s-school-districts-are-responding-to-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/04/25/update-to-how-u-s-school-districts-are-responding-to-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, I wrote about an attempt to understand how United States (U.S.) school districts are responding to COVID-19 (link here). A big part of that earlier work was a map depicting the number of districts within states mentioning COVID-19.&#xA;With inspiration, ideas, and help from Teya Rutherford, [Daniel Anderson](Daniel Anderson), Alex Lishinski, and Ha Nguyen), the underlying data is more trustworthy and the map is now interactive (and is at the district, rather than the state, level) and is available here (or by clicking the screenshot below):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Education Using R by (and a little beyond) the numbers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/data-science-in-education-using-r-by-and-beyond-the-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/data-science-in-education-using-r-by-and-beyond-the-numbers/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R is done!&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s us (with a few of us a bit in the dark), right around when we clicked &amp;ldquo;send&amp;rdquo; on an email with links/attachments for what was a two-year project.&#xA;Data Science in Education Using R by the numbers The project involved a lot of steps, and it is possible, particularly because of the way in which we wrote the book in the open, to describe the process by the numbers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How are U.S. school districts responding to COVID? A first look at 12,500 districts&#39; websites</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/how-are-u-s-school-districts-responding-to-covid-a-first-look-at-12-500-districts-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/how-are-u-s-school-districts-responding-to-covid-a-first-look-at-12-500-districts-websites/</guid>
      <description>Like many educational researchers (and teachers, parents, administrators . . . and kids), I have been wondering about how U.S. school districts are responding to the COVID-19 pandemic. There seemed to be a lot of variation, not only across U.S. states, but also within districts within states, and even within districts (and even within schools in districts!).&#xA;Exploring how districts in Tennessee (and, soon, other states) are responding to COVID-19 One way I&amp;rsquo;m pursuing this is through a project wherein we are trying to document what every district in the state of Tennessee (and, possibly, soon, in other states) are doing to respond: Whether they are completely closed or they are still providing opportunities for students to learn; what kinds of teaching and learning and/or resources are provided to students (and their parents); and, how districts are supporting students who might very reasonably not have, for instance, reliable Internet access at their home, or a computer that they can use to access resources (not to mention Zoom).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is your state still planning to carry out end-of-course testing in light of COVID-19? Crowdsourcing information</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/is-your-state-still-planning-to-carry-out-end-of-course-testing-crowdsourcing-information/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/is-your-state-still-planning-to-carry-out-end-of-course-testing-crowdsourcing-information/</guid>
      <description>State testing My colleague Isabella Velasquez and I were wondering what states were doing with respect to end-of-course testing, and found that no comprehensive (of which we were aware) yet existed. As a result, we decided to try to crowdsource this information.&#xA;Has your state announced whether they are postponing end-of-course (or other planned) tests this year in light of COVID-19? Please take a minute or so to add this information to this Google Sheets spreadsheet: https://docs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual KnoxData presentation (via Zoom) on reproducible, scalable research with drake in R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/virtual-via-zoom-knoxdata-presentation-on-reproducible-scalable-research-with-drake-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/virtual-via-zoom-knoxdata-presentation-on-reproducible-scalable-research-with-drake-in-r/</guid>
      <description>KnoxData is hosting a virtual (Zoom-based) presentation tonight (Thursday, Mar. 19) from 6:30 - 7:30 pm EST on Reproducible, scalable research: an example with drake in R. D&#xA;Here is some information on the presentation; more is available on the group&amp;rsquo;s Meetup page.&#xA;We all start out using things like Excel to analyze data. Sometimes we progress to entering commands in languages like R and python, then save our commands into a script and run that.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In support of JOSS for not accepting new article submissions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/in-support-of-joss-for-not-accepting-new-article-submissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/in-support-of-joss-for-not-accepting-new-article-submissions/</guid>
      <description>The Journal of Open Source Software announced last week (via email and on Twitter) that:&#xA;Submissions to JOSS are suspended for 30 days to provide relief to authors, editors, and reviewers dealing with the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic.&#xA;The attached image from the Tweet is an elaboration of this announcement:&#xA;I think this is a good idea, and support it. Setting the expectation from the &amp;ldquo;top-down&amp;rdquo; can support individuals&amp;rsquo; decision (necessary or forced) to slow their pace of non-urgent work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Help request - bookdown figure numbers out of order</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/help-request-bookdown-figure-numbers-out-of-order/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/help-request-bookdown-figure-numbers-out-of-order/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R co-author Isabella posted in RStudio Community about a strange issue encountered when adding figure numbers to the book: they are regularly out of order. The post in RStudio Community is here.&#xA;As one example, in Chapter 5, the figure numbering begins with 5.1 . . . but then proceeds to 0.1, and then picks up (correctly) with 5.3 through the last figure, 5.10.&#xA;After trying to figure out whether there was an issue with that figure (source code for Chapter 5), we looked at other chapters, like Chapter 9, for which the numbering is even more dramatically out or order.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Requesting your feedback: Data Science in Education Using R is almost ready!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready/</guid>
      <description>The Data Science in Education Using R book is almost ready to be sent to the publisher.&#xA;You can view the latest version of the book (as of this morning!) at the following URL:&#xA;https://datascienceineducation.com/&#xA;The screenshot below shows how to suggest a revision through GitHub; this functionality exists for every chapter of the book.&#xA;![](/post/2020-03-11-requesting-your-feedback-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-almost-ready_files/Screen Shot 2020-03-11 at 10.08.18 AM.png)&#xA;If you prefer, you can email us with any suggested edits at authors@datascienceineducation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sickness and gratitude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/sickness-and-gratitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/sickness-and-gratitude/</guid>
      <description>As this post&amp;rsquo;s title indicates, this isn&amp;rsquo;t a typical blog post for me; it&amp;rsquo;s on (much) a personal note. I&amp;rsquo;ll preface this post by saying that I&amp;rsquo;m fundamentally healthy (and so is my fam): that is sort of the thesis of the post.&#xA;Starting in December, our son came down with a bad ear infection that continued through the holiday break (and the new year). He got better - we got sick - and we moved on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More confidently uncertain? Teaching learners to apply Bayesian methods to make sense of scientific phenomena</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/more-confidently-uncertain-teaching-learners-to-apply-bayesian-methods-to-make-sense-of-scientific-phenomena/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/more-confidently-uncertain-teaching-learners-to-apply-bayesian-methods-to-make-sense-of-scientific-phenomena/</guid>
      <description>This is a new area for me, one that I proposed to explore in the ICLS Early Career Workshop:&#xA;More confidently uncertain? Teaching learners to apply Bayesian methods to make sense of scientific phenomena&#xA;While analyzing data is an important learning in science domains, existing methods and tools for those learning to work with data have key limitations, particularly concerning scientific modeling. This early-stage research is intended to begin a line of work on students’ data analysis that is not yet widely used in K-12 learning environments, Bayesian statistical methods, with implications for how learners use evidence in science education.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New version of konfound (v 0.2.1) for sensitivity analysis available</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-version-of-konfound-v-0-2-1-for-sensitivity-analysis-a-technique-to-support-trying-to-make-causal-inferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-version-of-konfound-v-0-2-1-for-sensitivity-analysis-a-technique-to-support-trying-to-make-causal-inferences/</guid>
      <description>A new version of konfound (v 0.2.1) for sensitivity analysis (a technique to support making causal inferences, especially in light of observational data) is available.&#xA;This version includes a new technique for non-linear models (i.e., a logistic regression).&#xA;Documentation for the package is available here: https://jrosen48.github.io/konfound/&#xA;We also updated the Shiny app associated with the package, available here: http://konfound-it.com/&#xA;Lastly, here are other blog posts on the topic:&#xA;an introduction to the R package an introduction the Shiny app </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on studying education-focused Twitter hashtags in light of state-based and national policies and practices</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-studying-education-focused-twitter-hashtags-in-light-of-state-based-and-national-policies-and-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-studying-education-focused-twitter-hashtags-in-light-of-state-based-and-national-policies-and-practices/</guid>
      <description>Supported through an SEC Travel Grant, I am presenting on Studying education-focused Twitter hashtags in light of state-based and national policies and practices as a part of the 2020 Spring Seminar Series at the Martin School of Public Policy at the University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here: https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1lNMAUGfBvnVsLEL8pbeS5On60v0vZifqeZkXsqkyFYk/edit?usp=sharing&#xA;Thank you to Annelise Russell and Spencer Greenhalgh for this awesome opportunity!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New version of tidyLPA (v 1.0.5) for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis using either open-source or commercial software</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-version-of-tidylpa-1-0-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-version-of-tidylpa-1-0-5/</guid>
      <description>There is a new version of tidyLPA (v 1.0.5) available on CRAN (see here).&#xA;The website, with a lot more information than is on the page above, is here.&#xA;Changes include:&#xA;Add function to calculate Lo-Mendell-Rubin LR test Add plot_bivariate() Set default for plot_profiles(add_line = FALSE), because the line does not convey any meaningful information Fix bug re. passing additional parameters to mplusObject() Remove messages about deprecated functions (those which were last used in v &amp;lt; 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing a recursive function in R - or, tweets on tweets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/writing-a-recursive-function-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/writing-a-recursive-function-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Background Recursion has been a topic I’ve heard about, and even read about it, but have never used. Recently, I was analyzing data for the Next Generation Science Standards hashtag on Twitter, and was puzzled to find that some of the Tweets I had accessed were replies to Tweets which were themselves not in the data set.&#xA;Fortunately, the rtweet R package returns data on which Tweet a reply is to; using these, it is possible (using rtweet) to access the original Tweet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short activities focused around trying something new - some coding and data science-related examples</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/code-bites-in-r-studio-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/code-bites-in-r-studio-cloud/</guid>
      <description>In research group meetings, we have started with short (5-10 minute) activities focused on trying something new.&#xA;So far, these activities have been focused on computer science or data science ideas. This post shares a few of those, which have been somewhat useful (I think!) so far:&#xA;Writing and &amp;ldquo;using&amp;rdquo; a recipe for making pancakes (to explore the idea of an how computers closely follow the instructions they are told, as well as algorithms, conditional logic, and functions) Exploring what one notices about weather/climate-related data Tinkering with a cool agent-based model for frog adaptation Last, today, we used code bites in R/RStudio, with the goal being to create minimally viable (and interesting) content; it worked well, I think, by lowering the motivation-related barrier to writing code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-source study - Resources related to our study of how students become interested in CS</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/open-source-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/open-source-study/</guid>
      <description>We are beginning data collection today for our study of how students become interested in computer science (our beginning of a project website is at https://picsul.utk.edu/). I&amp;rsquo;ve blogged about the project two times before:&#xA;Thoughts from submitting a grant proposal for the first time New project on understanding the development of interest in computer science One idea we have brought to the project is that we want to share as much as we possibly (ethically and based upon the Institutional Review Board applicaiton for the project) can.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - Identifying multiple learning spaces in a single educational hashtag</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-article-identifying-multiple-learning-spaces-in-a-single-educational-hashtag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-article-identifying-multiple-learning-spaces-in-a-single-educational-hashtag/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share about a second article published (today!) on how the regularly-occurring chats that take place through an education-focused Twitter hashtag are distinct from the rest of the time (i.e., non-chat times when people use the hashtag), is by Spencer Greenhalgh et al. in Computers &amp;amp; Education. Here is the abstract:&#xA;The existing work on teacher-focused Twitter hashtags typically frames each hashtag as a single, unified phenomenon, thereby collapsing or erasing differences between them (and any resulting implications for learning).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article - The effects of choice and interest in science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-articles-the-effects-of-choice-and-interest-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-articles-the-effects-of-choice-and-interest-in-science/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share a link to an article published earlier this month on the effects of (learners) being able to make choices and their learning, and how that relates to their interest in what they are learning, is by Patrick Beymer et al. and is in Learning and Individual Differences. Here is the abstract:&#xA;Having choices during learning is often touted as beneficial for student motivation. However, it is not clear whether the motivating factor is choice or the act of pursuing tasks that are of greater interest, which is often afforded by choice.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple uses for multi-level models: Examples from recent research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/multiple-uses-for-multi-level-models-examples-from-recent-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/multiple-uses-for-multi-level-models-examples-from-recent-research/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m presenting on Multiple uses for multi-level models: Examples from recent research today for the College of Education, Health, and Human Sciences Quantitative Methods Brownbag Seminar.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here: https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1nY7n4H08fVMRUQxNQl6cy0ilLhX-2j7_PCj0TGPoFsE/edit?usp=sharing</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KnoxData presentation: An introduction to using R for data science, zero prerequisites required!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/knoxdata-presentation-an-introduction-to-using-r-for-data-science-zero-prerequisites-required/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/knoxdata-presentation-an-introduction-to-using-r-for-data-science-zero-prerequisites-required/</guid>
      <description>I am presenting on Thursday, January 24th on An introduction to using R for data science (zero prerequisites required!) for the KnoxData group. The Meetup page for event is here.&#xA;A description of the event is here:&#xA;R is a freely-available, cross-platform, open-source programming language and statistical software environment that is well-suited to doing data science, but, can have an high barrier to entry. This KnoxData presentation aims to provides an introduction to using for data science, with a focus on developing a foundation in capabilities (and confidence!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First version of a research group handbook</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/first-verison-of-a-research-group-handbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/first-verison-of-a-research-group-handbook/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a first version of a research group handbook. Part of the joy of working with more students is the need to try to have greater structure around advising, carrying out projects, and meeting.&#xA;The handbook (view only via this link) is here on Google Docs: https://docs.google.com/document/d/13YmeUU4lSGWVqZfmCGljnJ4nTbD26TaY7oH3LUWo7Zk/edit?usp=sharing&#xA;Feedback is welcomed!&#xA;Thanks to Teya Rutherford for sharing the handbook for her research group. Thanks to Bodong Chen for posting his statement of graduate advising.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at the TN STEM Education Research Conference</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentations-at-the-tn-stem-education-research-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentations-at-the-tn-stem-education-research-conference/</guid>
      <description>The Making Data Science Count research group has two presentations at the upcoming TN STEM Education Research Conference:&#xA;Rosenberg, J. M.,&amp;amp; Lishinski, A. (January, 2020). Measuring what matters in-the-moment: An experience sampling approach to understanding the development of interest in computer science. Presentation at the 14th Annual Tennessee STEM Education Research Conference. Cookeville, TN.&#xA;Rosenberg, J. M., Hodge, L., Aydeniz, M., Schmidt, A. Lishinski, A., Rich, K., Longnecker, J., Mann. M.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Things I learned in the last year</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/things-i-learned-in-the-last-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/things-i-learned-in-the-last-year/</guid>
      <description>Here are some things I learned in the last year. They are all unordered.&#xA;Models and parenting and teaching A collabofriend shared &amp;ldquo;the 5 S&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; for soothing babies with me before our son was born, and this was super helpful to me. But, in the last year, our son became a toddler, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to do, and I struggled. I tried to find resources for how to parent (and discipline, something I haven&amp;rsquo;t been very good at), and found that a simple idea from the authors of No Drama Discipline clicked with me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hey AERA, what&#39;s up with that?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/hey-aera-what-s-up-with-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/hey-aera-what-s-up-with-that/</guid>
      <description>I like the American Educational Research Association; it&amp;rsquo;s my professional home.&#xA;I was pretty surprised to see this letter, advocating against open access to educational research that is funded through federal agencies (i.e., the Institute of Educational Sciences, the National Science Foundation, etc.).&#xA;Inside Higher Ed has an article on AERA&amp;rsquo;s (and other professional organization&amp;rsquo;s) opposition.&#xA;Basically, this is wrong. I think AERA is on the wrong side of a trend - driven by access to information through the Internet - toward open access.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting a grip on using BibTeX with R Markdown documents</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-bibtex-with-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-bibtex-with-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>I’m just beginning to learn BibTeX, which is, according to Wikipedia (2019), “reference management software for formatting lists of references”.&#xA;It is useful for publishing formats such as R Markdown documents and books created with bookdown, like the Data Science in Education Using R book.&#xA;I’m basically using this post to document what I’m learning.&#xA;Adding references I started with references, which are saved in plain text documents ending in .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first, rough (rough!) draft of the (web-based) version of Data Science in Education Using R is available</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/the-first-rough-draft-of-the-web-based-version-of-data-science-in-education-using-r-is-available/</guid>
      <description>The first, rough draft of the (web-based version) of the Data Science in Education Using R book written by Emily Bovee, Ryan Estrellado, Jesse Motstipak, me, and Isabella Velásquez is available from this URL: http://www.datascienceineducation.com/.&#xA;I mentioned this in an earlier post introducing the book: the publisher, Routledge, allowed us to stipulate that we retain the copyright for the web-based version, even after the book is published in print (and e-book) format.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tiny (Shiny) app: How Many (MCMC) Cores?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores/</guid>
      <description>Here is a tiny (Shiny) application to help with selecting the number of cores in the context of MCMC estimation.&#xA;How many cores? is here: https://jmichaelrosenberg.shinyapps.io/how-many-cores/&#xA;Here is a screenshot:&#xA;![](/post/2019-12-13-a-tiny-shiny-how-many-mcmc-cores_files/Screen Shot 2019-12-13 at 8.11.18 PM.png)&#xA;The source is here: https://github.com/jrosen48/how-many-cores</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using R/R Studio from a (Pixel Slate) Chromebook</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-r-studio-from-a-pixel-slate-chromebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-r-studio-from-a-pixel-slate-chromebook/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had a Pixel Slate Chromebook for a little while, and noticed in a recent update that it was possible to install Linux.&#xA;This was pretty easy to do (see here). After doing it (it took a few minutes to download Linux, but was otherwise super straightforward), I opened up the command line interface and saw this:&#xA;There are a few things I know how to do through a command line interface; one is to list all of the files and directories available, so I ran the following:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research group website - Making data science count</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/research-group-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/research-group-website/</guid>
      <description>I created a research group website, Making Data Science Count. I intend to use that website for updates on research projects and research-related updates, and this website for information about me (my teaching, CV, etc.).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taking a break from social media</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/taking-a-break-from-social-media-take-n/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/taking-a-break-from-social-media-take-n/</guid>
      <description>Since this past summer, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to moderate my use of social media. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried a number of strategies (like limiting the amount of time I spend each day), but none have been very effective, apart from a fairly dramatic step, deactivating my accounts, which was effective (until I got back on). While my accounts were deactivated, I missed keeping up with and being in touch with friends and family, but I found other ways to communciate (I actually had two phone calls!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It was a job posting on a mailing list, not a blog post on the NARST blog: A response to Mintzes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/it-was-a-job-posting-on-a-mailing-list-not-a-blog-post-on-the-narst-blog-a-response-to-mintzes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/it-was-a-job-posting-on-a-mailing-list-not-a-blog-post-on-the-narst-blog-a-response-to-mintzes/</guid>
      <description>Since mid-morning this past Friday, members of NARST have been discussing a post and a response to the organization&amp;rsquo;s mailing list.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ve written before about how I use my blog to communicate; this is an attempt to do that in the context of that discussion.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ll lay out my argument in advance, in part because it is simple:&#xA;Hazari shared a job post on a mailing list. It was not a blog post, and it certainly was not a blog post on the NARST blog.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using R with 7th-grade science students</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-with-7th-grade-science-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-with-7th-grade-science-students/</guid>
      <description>Sparked by a collaboration with Bodong Chen, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with a 7th-grade science teacher, Alex Edwards, at Tate&amp;rsquo;s School. We recently wrote about some of the take-aways from our work last year in a publication on &amp;ldquo;Tools and strategies for engaging students in analyzing and interpreting complex data sources.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;The article is going to be published in NSTA&amp;rsquo;s The Science Teacher journal (a pre-print of the article is here).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at Middle Tennessee State University: Making Data Science Count</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</guid>
      <description>I was lucky to have the chance to present at the Middle Tennessee State University Math and Science Education Seminar Series.&#xA;Presentation My presentation was on Making data science count: Exploring the integration of data science into education.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here.&#xA;Workshop I also carried out a two-hour workshop on An introduction to data science in education using R. A repository for the workshop, including a link to slides, code, and data, is here: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pre-print probs - Some thoughts after posting a pre-print of an article</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/pre-print-probs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/pre-print-probs/</guid>
      <description>I shared my grant proposal I wrote as a pre-print for a number of reasons:&#xA;The not-very-proprietary nature of this project (with its focus on individual investigator development) I didn’t face any risk of unblinding the review process (as the NSF review process already is) I was the only author, and, so, I felt like there was less risk if I made a mistake: I was the one who would face the consequences!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resources and ideas for engineers working on the design challenge of teaching elementary students about engineering</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/resources-and-ideas-for-engineers-working-on-the-design-challenge-of-teaching-elementary-students-about-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/resources-and-ideas-for-engineers-working-on-the-design-challenge-of-teaching-elementary-students-about-engineering/</guid>
      <description>I have the opportunity to speak with Dr. Courtney Faber&amp;rsquo;s engineering service-learning course.&#xA;In this course, my understanding is that students tackle a design challenge. I was asked to come to class to speak for around 30-minutes around adapting and designing activities for an engineering after school program for elementary-aged students. So, the design challenge is to teach engineering to elementary students about engineering. Cool!&#xA;But, I don&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rsquo; have expertise in engineering or elementary education.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Base group check-in questions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/base-group-check-in-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/base-group-check-in-questions/</guid>
      <description>Note. I am adding to this list throughout the Fall, 2019 semester!&#xA;Check-out/Exit ticket questions In many classes I teach, I assign students to base groups, groups of around three or four students who sit together (for most of the time) and &amp;ldquo;check-in&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;check-out&amp;rdquo; of class. The goal of base groups is to foster a kind of positive interdependence among students.&#xA;The check out questions are typically the same:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Science education resources</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/science-education-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/science-education-resources/</guid>
      <description>This list accumulated over the course of two classes and so I thought to start to archive resources here for posterity. Right now, these are unordered and have come from student recommendations and other sources:&#xA;Lessons and related resources https://nextgenscience.org/resources/examples-quality-ngss-design (examples of NGSS-aligned units and lessons) http://datanuggets.org/ (datasets from scientists for use by learners) https://www.scientificamerican.com/education/bring-science-home/?page=1 (ideas and resources for investigations) https://ngss.nsta.org/Classroom-Resources.aspx (over 800 vetted lesson plans) https://www.ngssphenomena.com/ (phenomena for planning for NGSS-aligned teaching and learning) https://orise.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Responding to the President&#39;s comments </title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/responding-to-the-president-s-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/responding-to-the-president-s-comments/</guid>
      <description>I love Israel. My spouse can testify to this: After my last trip, with a group of doctoral students and faculty from Michigan State University, I talked about it (and especially the hummus) for months after. I want to go back. Just yesterday, I put mint I cut from my yard into my water bottle, like I saw Israelis do. I have a camp stove that I bought when I first traveled to Israel, when I was 18, that I used less than a month ago on a camping trip.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New project on understanding the development of interest in computer science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-project-understanding-the-development-of-interest-in-computer-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-project-understanding-the-development-of-interest-in-computer-science/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to share that I was recently awarded funding to carry out a new project, Understanding the development of interest in computer science - an experience sampling approach. This is for the project I wrote about here.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s an excerpt from NSF&amp;rsquo;s summary (a bit more is [here] (https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1937700&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false)):&#xA;This project explores STEM interest development at the undergraduate level in computer science. It is a study of national importance that will focus on substantial differences in who pursues an interest, a major, or an occupation in computer science.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts from submitting a grant proposal for the first time</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/thoughts-from-submitting-a-grant-proposal-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/thoughts-from-submitting-a-grant-proposal-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>Note. I drafted this right after submitting the proposal but didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing it until now - almost two months later! I kept the language (around the timing) the same, as, there is still no better time than now to share&amp;ndash;though, earlier would have likely been better as the process was more fresh on my mind.&#xA;This past week, I submitted a proposal for a grant independently. I thought that there would be no better time than now to just down some thoughts, reflections, and perhaps a few lessons learned from the process of submitting a grant independently, as follows.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Data Science in Education Using R (forthcoming 2020)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/introducing-data-science-in-education-using-r-forthcoming-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/introducing-data-science-in-education-using-r-forthcoming-2020/</guid>
      <description>Data Science in Education Using R I&amp;rsquo;m super excited to share that I will be writing a book, Data Science in Education Using R. The book will be published by Routledge sometime in mid-to-late 2020, and, importantly to us, Routledge agreed to let us keep the copyright for a web-version of the book, meaning that we will publish the entire contents of the book in an open and freely-available format (along with the print and e-book versions, which will be available for sale).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on the use of mixed effects models to the KnoxData group</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-the-use-of-mixed-effects-models-to-the-knoxdata-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-the-use-of-mixed-effects-models-to-the-knoxdata-group/</guid>
      <description>data-science-ish I presented yesterday on Data Science-Ish: The Use of Mixed Effects Models for Analyzing Complex Data at the KnoxData group.&#xA;Abstract Here is an abstract for the talk:&#xA;Mixed effects (or multilevel) models are extensions of linear models (regressions) that are commonly used in experimental research and policy and evaluation contexts, but are less widely-used by data scientists. In this talk, I aim to introduce mixed effects model as a data science-ish statistical method that can be useful and is easy to estimate and interpret.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent publications on an online experiment platform, creatively focused technology fluency, and a computational science simulation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/recent-publications-a-virtual-experiment-platform-a-creatively-focused-technology-mindset-and-students-use-of-a-computationa-science-simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/recent-publications-a-virtual-experiment-platform-a-creatively-focused-technology-mindset-and-students-use-of-a-computationa-science-simulation/</guid>
      <description>I realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about a few exciting manuscripts that I have co-authored or authored that have been published in the past year! The following pubications are on the design of virtual experiment platform, a creatively focused technology mindset, and students’ use of a computational science simulation, respectively.&#xA;Blondel, D. V., Sansone, A., Rosenberg, J. M., Yang, B. W., Linennbrink-Garcia, L., &amp;amp; Schwarz-Bloom, R. D. (advance online publication). Development of an online experiment platform (Rex) for high school biology.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on &#39;Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</guid>
      <description>This past week, I presented a workshop, Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education. for Educational Psychology and Educational Technology PhD students (and a few others) with Emily Bovee.&#xA;Here is the description:&#xA;R is a freely-available, cross-platform, open-source programming language and statistical software environment that is well-suited to data analysis and data science, but, can have an high barrier to entry. This workshop provides an introduction to R in education, with a focus on developing a foundation in capabilities (and confidence!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Little Bitty Steps Toward a More Open Education Research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/little-bitty-steps-toward-more-open-educational-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/little-bitty-steps-toward-more-open-educational-research/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of productive discussion around open education research (or science).&#xA;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed some examples of what I think are good open education research.&#xA;Though I think of these as good examples and models for the rest of us to follow, I think some of them are not always appreciated as such. This matters because open education research can then seem like something that is not relevant or too onerous.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentations at AERA 2019 - Understanding changes in interest in STEM, student engagement profiles in science, and transparent and reproducible research</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentations-at-aera-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentations-at-aera-2019/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to be presenting this week (and early next week) on some ongoing work at the American Educational Research Association (AERA) 2019 Annual Meeting in Toronto, Canada.&#xA;Predictors of Momentary Student Engagement Profiles in High School Science Classrooms Sat, April 6, 10:25 to 11:55am, Sheraton Centre Toronto Hotel, Second Floor, Provincial Ballroom North&#xA;Schell, M. J., Beymer, P. N. Albert, K. M., Rosenberg, J. M., &amp;amp; Schmidt, J. A.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at NARST 2019 - An exploration of NGSSchat through social network analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-narst-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-narst-2019/</guid>
      <description>Joshua Reid presented An exploration of #NGSSchat through social network analysis on behalf of myself and our co-authors at the NARST 2019 conference (in Baltimore, MD).&#xA;The presentation is available here. A repository with the code to reproduce the analysis presented at NARST, as well as a copy of our in-progress paper, is available here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on &#39;Making Sense of Recent Advances in the TPACK Framework&#39; at the English International Congress (at UTN in Ibarra, Ecuador)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-making-sense-of-recent-advances-in-the-tpack-framework-at-the-english-international-congress-at-utn-in-ibarra-ecuador/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-making-sense-of-recent-advances-in-the-tpack-framework-at-the-english-international-congress-at-utn-in-ibarra-ecuador/</guid>
      <description>I had the opportunity to present at the English International Congress at the Universidad Tecnical de Norte in Ibarra, Ecuador.&#xA;Presenting at the Congress was a great, fun experience and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the opportunity.&#xA;Resources My presentation was on Making Sense of Recent Advances in the Technological Pedagogical Content Knowledge Framework and is available here.&#xA;The special issue on TPCK/TPACK Research and Development: Past, Present, and Future Directions that I was involved in as a guest editor is available here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on engaging students in science at the ‘Crossing Boundaries for STEM Education’ regional meeting and mini-conference</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-engaging-students-in-science-at-the-crossing-boundaries-for-stem-education-regional-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-engaging-students-in-science-at-the-crossing-boundaries-for-stem-education-regional-meeting/</guid>
      <description>I was excited to have the opportunity to present on Engaging students in science: Findings from an experience sampling method approach at the East TN STEM Hub &amp;lsquo;Crossing Boundaries for STEM Education&amp;rsquo; regional meeting and mini-conference. I liked presenting there, alongside colleagues in biology, engineering, computer science, and my home department at UTK. It reminded me of one of my favorite events at Michigan State University&amp;ndash;the Create for STEM mini-conference.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on The Role of the Twitter Hashtag #NGSSchat in the Context of Science Education Reform Efforts at ASTE 2019</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-the-role-of-the-twitter-hashtag-ngsschat-in-the-context-of-science-education-reform-efforts-at-aste-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-the-role-of-the-twitter-hashtag-ngsschat-in-the-context-of-science-education-reform-efforts-at-aste-2019/</guid>
      <description>With Joshua Reid, Matthew Koehler, Christian Fischer, and T.J. McKenna, I presented on The Role of the Twitter Hashtag #NGSSchat in the Context of Science Education Reform Efforts at ASTE 2019.&#xA;The presentation is here: https://joshuamrosenberg.com/aste-19.html And a pre-print and link to the data (and code for the analysis and a whole lot more) is here: https://osf.io/9ex7k/ </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing a CV in markdown so it can be rendered as HTML, a PDF, and a Word document</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/creating-a-cv-while-using-blogdown-pdf-html-and-word-doc-oh-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/creating-a-cv-while-using-blogdown-pdf-html-and-word-doc-oh-my/</guid>
      <description>My goal: To write a CV in one format and in a way so that it can be rendered in multiple formats I have been trying to write my CV once and have it be displayed/rendered as HTML (for this website), a PDF (for sharing), and a Word document (also for sharing - as some folks require it to be in this format).&#xA;I have something that seems to work and so thought I would share what I did as a first attempt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on Data Science Education Dilemmas (and Opportunities)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-data-science-education-dilemmas-and-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-data-science-education-dilemmas-and-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>I had the opportunity to present on Data Science Education Dilemmas (and Opportunities) to STEM Education faculty at UT. It was a short, informal presentation, but served as a chance to pull together some ideas.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using R Markdown and papaja with a LaTeX class to submit a conference proposal: A few notes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-markdown-with-a-latex-class-a-few-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-r-markdown-with-a-latex-class-a-few-notes/</guid>
      <description>With my colleagues Emily Bovee (who had the idea for the project and is the first author) and John Ranellucci, I worked on a conference proposal for a conference that provided either a Word Document template or a LaTeX class. Since I had just used (that’s a generous way to put it - I really had struggled through it) LaTeX, I proposed that we see whether we could (continue to) use R and R Markdown, which we used to analyze the data, to prepare the manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Modeling&#39; science teaching and learning - a few notes on the first day of class</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-few-notes-on-the-first-day-of-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-few-notes-on-the-first-day-of-class/</guid>
      <description>My first day of class (at UTK) was last week. I was excited that the first day went well; it was a good start to teaching in a new setting (and to teaching a class that is new - to me). Like anyone in my position, I spent a lot of time thinking about the first class. Some notes here in the case that others might find them relevant/at all useful:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quick introduction and tutorial on a cool social network analysis model for influence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/social-network-analysis-model-for-influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/social-network-analysis-model-for-influence/</guid>
      <description>Social network is increasingly common in education (Sweet, 2016). Very often, social network analysis is used to create sociograms, or depictions of a network. I did this in a paper I recently co-authored (here is a pre-print), we worked hard to create this figure:&#xA;Such figures (we thought–and I think) look nice and they are often useful for understanding the characteristics of a network and the relations that are part of it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted? An update!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</guid>
      <description>In August of last year, I wrote a post that involved looking at when educational psychology jobs (mostly, but not only, academic jobs or those related to research and teaching) were posted to the excellent Ed Psych Jobs website. As that post made (in part) the (anticipated) point that most jobs were posted in September (in which 16% of jobs were posted there) and October (14%) (followed by August, with 11%), I thought that it may be helpful to see how accurate that was over the past year.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of a data visualization (made with ggplot2)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-evolving-data-visualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-evolving-data-visualization/</guid>
      <description>Last summer, I taught the MAET Year 2 Summer Cohort with Danah Henriksen. After teaching the class, Danah realized she had taught five cohorts of (awesome) students and that we had some information available from pre- and post-course self-reported surveys to understand how students grew in terms of their confidence in using different educational (and other) technologies.&#xA;That research idea evolved into a study with Rohit Mehta that involved, among other findings, a visualization of average pre-post values for specific technologies.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My dissertation defense (and some links to resources)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-open-ish-dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-open-ish-dissertation/</guid>
      <description>I am defending my dissertation to my committee tomorrow. I have tried to make it as open as possible. One way I have done this is writing and then saving the manuscript (and code for the analysis) in a public place (here).&#xA;That repository is on GitHub and includes a PDF of my dissertation and the R Markdown files used to generate it. It also includes the PowerPoint presentation for tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s defense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning R (for data analysis and data science): Where to start</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/learning-r-where-to-start-crowdsourced-recommendations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/learning-r-where-to-start-crowdsourced-recommendations/</guid>
      <description>A friend of a friend (also in educational research) posted that he was interested in learning R.&#xA;I had a couple of ideas but knew that others might have better ideas. So, I posted (on Twitter) looking for recommendations and received some excellent talks, links, and other resources.&#xA;Here they are, in Tweet form (you may have to click on the links in tweets to see some of the resources and content)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some books, NAP reports, and other newer resources related to science education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/some-resources-on-science-teaching-and-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/some-resources-on-science-teaching-and-learning/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ll be starting a position in STEM Education at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, beginning this August. As part of this position, I&amp;rsquo;ll teach science teaching methods (and science and STEM education research-related) courses. Hearing about the first course I&amp;rsquo;ll teach sparked me to gather these.&#xA;So, this is a loosely-organized collection of some resources&amp;ndash;especially some new(er) books and National Academies Press (NAP) reports&amp;ndash;related to science teaching and learning. I leave &amp;ldquo;oldies but goodies&amp;rdquo;, like Taking Science to School (2007), the Framework for K-12 Science Education (2012), and America&amp;rsquo;s Lab Report (2006) for example.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some ideas about getting started bike commuting </title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/getting-started-bike-commuting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/getting-started-bike-commuting/</guid>
      <description>This post includes a few things about getting started bike commuting. The thesis is something like: If you have a bike and a safe route, you can probably commute right away, and then add-on other things (like a rack, fenders, or different tires) over time.&#xA;The most important thing - a safe route! The most important thing is a safe route! In my experience, roads with bike lanes, or&amp;ndash;even better&amp;ndash;greenways (for runners, walkers, and bikers) are best, followed by neighborhood roads, followed by city roads with street parking.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AERA 2018 presentation: Patterns of engagement in a flipped undergraduate class (slides, paper, &amp; code)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/aera-presentation-patterns-of-engagement-in-a-flipped-undergraduate-class-antecedents-and-outcomes-information-slides-paper-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/aera-presentation-patterns-of-engagement-in-a-flipped-undergraduate-class-antecedents-and-outcomes-information-slides-paper-code/</guid>
      <description>I’m presenting a second paper at AERA on patterns of (outside of class) engagement in a flipped undergraduate class with my colleagues You-kyung Lee, Kristy Robinson, John Ranellucci, Cary Roseth, and Lisa Linnenbrink-Garcia. The presentation is at 8:15 am (Sunday, 4/15) in the Millenium Broadway Hotel (Room 7.04) and is on a session on emotions, engagement, and technology (with some very interesting papers presented by co-presenters in the session!).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AERA 2018 presentation: How engagement during out-of-school STEM programs promotes the development of interest (slides, paper, &amp; code)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/aera-presentation-how-engagement-during-out-of-school-stem-programs-promotes-the-development-of-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/aera-presentation-how-engagement-during-out-of-school-stem-programs-promotes-the-development-of-interest/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to present a paper on how engagement during out-of-school STEM programs promotes youths’ development of interest with my co-authors Patrick Beymer and Jennifer Schmidt.&#xA;The paper is in the session “Data-Intensive Approaches to Studying Engagement in Education: Exploring Their Current Potential”. My co-presenters in the session include Eric Weibe and James Creager, Sophia Hooper, Erica Patall, Ariana Vasquez, Keenan Pituch, and Rebecca Steingut, and Eric Poitas, Tenzin Doleck, Lingyun Huang, Shan Li, &amp;amp; Susanne Lajoie.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An R package for sensitivity analysis (konfound)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-r-package-for-sensitivity-analysis-konfound/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/an-r-package-for-sensitivity-analysis-konfound/</guid>
      <description>knitr::opts_chunk$set( comment = &amp;quot;#&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, collapse = TRUE ) With Ran Xu and Ken Frank, I have worked on a Shiny interactive web application for sensitivity analysis as well as an R package for carrying out sensitivity analysis using R.&#xA;That R package is now available on CRAN! A link to the CRAN page for it is here and the website for the package is here.&#xA;Here is the description:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explorations in Markov Chain Monte Carlo - comparing results from MCMCglmm and lme4</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/explorations-in-markov-chain-monte-carlo-mcmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/explorations-in-markov-chain-monte-carlo-mcmc/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run. If you run this code, parts may not work (depending upon the version of the packages used and, potentially, other factors).&#xA;Introduction I’ve been interested in Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) for a little while, in part because of a paper by Tom Houslay and Alastair Wilson (2017) that shows how using output from models the way I have been can lead to results that overstate the impact of effects.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding the top rail-trails in each state using mixed effects models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/find-the-top-rail-trails-in-each-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/find-the-top-rail-trails-in-each-state/</guid>
      <description>Outside of education, one of my interests is cycling, and one of my favorite ways to cycle is on rail-trails, pathways and greenways that are converted from former railroad tracks.&#xA;In a side-project (and because the data source can be used for teaching and learning about complex, nested data), I collected information from the TrailLink website. I’ve blogged about this data here and here to find out what the best rail-trails in Michigan are and to find out what the characteristics of the best rail-trails are, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing tidyLPA (an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/introducing-tidylpa-an-r-package-for-carrying-out-latent-profile-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/introducing-tidylpa-an-r-package-for-carrying-out-latent-profile-analysis/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to introduce tidyLPA, an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA). This is the result of a collaborative project with Jennifer Schmidt, Patrick Beymer, and Rebecca Steingut, and is the result of a long period of learning about cluster analysis (see here) and, recently, model-based cluster analysis. Here, I introduce and describe LPA as a particular type of model-based cluster analysis.&#xA;Note: This post has been updated to reflect the latest version of tidyLPA</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming presentations at AERA, SITE, and NARST</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/upcoming-presentations-at-aera-and-narst/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/upcoming-presentations-at-aera-and-narst/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to present (or contribute to presentations) associated with a number of ongoing projects at the AERA, SITE, and NARST conferences later this semester. If you are at one of the conferences (or presentations) and would like to get in touch, please do! Here are the titles and some other information for the presentations:&#xA;Beymer, P. N., Rosenberg, J.M., &amp;amp; Schmidt, J. A. (2018, April). Investigating the effects of interest and choice: An experience sampling approach.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Shiny interactive web application to quantify how robust inferences are to potential sources of bias (sensitivity analysis)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-shiny-interactive-web-application-to-quantify-how-robust-inferences-are-to-potential-sources-of-bias-sensitivity-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-shiny-interactive-web-application-to-quantify-how-robust-inferences-are-to-potential-sources-of-bias-sensitivity-analysis/</guid>
      <description>As part of a revise and resubmit decision for a paper (that was just accepted to the Journal of Youth and Adolescence (pre-print here)), we (Patrick Beymer, Jennifer Schmidt, and I) were asked by the editor to carry out sensitivity analysis for findings. Our understanding was that, in this context, sensitivity analysis means one of two things - or both:&#xA;How results hold up under different specfications of an analyses How much bias would have to be present to invalidate an inference Over the past year or so, I had learned about sensitivity analysis from a class and then work with Ken Frank.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outcomes from a self-generated utility value intervention in science (in IJER)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-article-on-a-utility-value-intervention-in-ijer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/new-article-on-a-utility-value-intervention-in-ijer/</guid>
      <description>The Scientific Practices project, was focused on engaging middle school students in scientific and engineering practices (such as developing and using models, constructing explanations of phenomena, and analyzing and interpreting data). As part of this longitudinal project, we carried out field experiments to understand the impact of specific features of the curriculum.&#xA;In this paper published in the International Journal of Educational Research with Mete Akcaoglu, John Ranellucci, Christina Schwarz, and I examined whether asking students to generate ideas about how what they were learning about could be useful in the future.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modifying an R function to iterate (using purrr) and use non-standard evaluation (using rlang)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/modifying-an-r-function-to-use-non-standard-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/modifying-an-r-function-to-use-non-standard-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run.&#xA;Background Research in classrooms and schools can be complex because of all of the factors that matter. A question that often comes up when we say that we observed some pattern in data is, but did you control for X?&#xA;In the context of working on an approach to find out how impactful an omitted variable would need to be to invalidate an inference, we had to modify a function that worked for a single sensitivity analysis to work for many and to be easier to use.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New post on engaging students in “data practices” in online science classes (in the MVLRI Research, Policy, Innovation &amp; Networks blog)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/mvlri-blog-post-on-data-practices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/mvlri-blog-post-on-data-practices/</guid>
      <description>I have worked to design activities for students to work with authentic data sources in their science classes through a collaboration with Michigan Virtual School and the Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute.&#xA;As a part of this project, which was supported by their dissertation research fellowship, I hosted a webinar. I also wrote a post for the Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute Blog: Research, Policy, Innovation &amp;amp; Networks blog.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of &#39;What’s Worth Teaching: Rethinking Curriculum in the Age of Technology&#39; in Teachers College Record</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/review-of-what-s-worth-teaching-rethinking-curriculum-in-the-age-of-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/review-of-what-s-worth-teaching-rethinking-curriculum-in-the-age-of-technology/</guid>
      <description>I was recently requested to submit a review with Charles Logan for the book What’s Worth Teaching: Rethinking Curriculum in the Age of Technology by the incredible scholar Allan Collins. A link to the review and book on the Teachers College Record website here. A pre-print of our review is also available here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two data packages: Rail-trails and an assessment of student achievement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/two-open-datasets-rail-trails-and-an-assessment-of-student-achievement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/two-open-datasets-rail-trails-and-an-assessment-of-student-achievement/</guid>
      <description>Because of interest and the need for better examples (for teaching and for use in tools under-development), such as prcr and tidyLPA, I worked to create two data packages, data easily available through an R package.&#xA;A benefit of the data being in an R package is that it is even easier to access than other formats (in R): Just load the name of the package and type the name of the data frame, or, if the data is included as built-in data in another package (one that is loaded), just type the name of the data frame.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MVLRI webinar on engaging students in authentic &#39;data practices&#39; in online science classes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/mvlri-webinar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/mvlri-webinar/</guid>
      <description>I will be hosting a webinar on Engaging students in authentic “data practices” in online science classes with Michigan Virtual Learning Research Institute, the research organization associated with Michigan’s state-wide online school. The webinar is today (10/18) at 2pm EDT and is available via https://connect.mivu.org/mvlri&#xA;Here is a bit more information on the webinar:&#xA;Not only in science and science education but also our everyday lives, data are powerful, but opportunities for students to think of and with data as part of their learning are limited.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with &#39;open science&#39; through blogging</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/getting-started-with-open-science-through-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/getting-started-with-open-science-through-blogging/</guid>
      <description>Through a few different projects and people (such as SIPS and rOpenSci and conversations with friends / colleagues both online and offline), I have been exposed to the idea of open science.&#xA;I’m actually going to punt for the moment. Here’s a definition that sounds about right to me:&#xA;Open science is the movement to make scientific research, data and dissemination accessible to all levels of an inquiring society, amateur or professional.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A person-in-context approach to student engagement in science (article in JRST)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-person-in-context-approach-to-student-engagement-in-science-article-in-jrst/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/a-person-in-context-approach-to-student-engagement-in-science-article-in-jrst/</guid>
      <description>Over the past few years, I have worked with Jennifer Schmidt and Patrick Beymer to explore student engagement in science using the Experience Sampling Method (ESM). Most recently, we used what scholars have referred to as a “person-in-context” approach, using both ESM and a person-oriented approach.&#xA;A figure is helpful for conveying how the person-oriented approach can be used to find common momentary engagement profiles:&#xA;We examine how common these profiles are in laboratory activities and on the basis of students’ ability to make choices.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few podcasts I always listen to</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/podcasts-i-do-not-miss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/podcasts-i-do-not-miss/</guid>
      <description>Between commuting by bicycle and working, I listen to a lot of podcasts. I listen to podcasts to learn something new, keep up with the news, and, occasionally, hear other viewpoints. I thought it would be worth sharing a few that I (almost) never miss downloading and listening to, especially those that others may not regularly hear about, are new, or are sort of niche in terms of the audience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using MPlus from R with MPlusAutomation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run.&#xA;According to the MPlus website, the R package MPlusAutomation serves three purposes:&#xA;Creating related groups of models Running batches Extracting and tabulating model parameters and test statistics. Because modeling involves comparing related models, (partially) automating these is compelling. It can make it easier to use model results in subsequent analyses and can cut down on copy and pasting output or results between programs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A first pass at Latent Profile Analysis using MCLUST (in R)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/lpa-in-r-using-mclust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/lpa-in-r-using-mclust/</guid>
      <description>Note - an R package for carrying out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA): tidyLPA Since writing this post, I have worked with colleagues to release an R package to carry out the analysis. The package is tidyLPA and is described in the following sections, through the “Original Post” header below which is the beginning of the original post.&#xA;Introduction Latent Profile Analysis (LPA) is a statistical modeling approach for estimating distinct profiles, or groups, of variables.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing estimates and their standard errors from mixed effects and linear models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/comparing-mixed-effects-and-linear-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/comparing-mixed-effects-and-linear-models/</guid>
      <description>Some background One reason to use mixed effects models is that they help to account for data with a complex structure, such as multiple responses (to questions, for example) from the same people, students grouped into classes, and measures collected over time. Often, the way they account for these complex structures is in terms of reducing their bias, which has to do with when a model comes up with an estimate that is off - too large, too small, or maybe too certain (or uncertain) relative to the true value of the thing that is estimated.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</guid>
      <description>Division 15 of the American Psychological Association sponsors the Ed Psych Jobs website, which is an excellent resource for Ed Psych job seekers. I thought it would possibly be helpful to see when jobs were posted in the past in order to have a better idea about when jobs may be posted this year.&#xA;Ed Psych Jobs, Robots (.txt), and paths_allowed, oh my As this project involves a bit of web-scraping, I first checked the robots.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using characteristics of rail-trails to predict how they are rated</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/characteristics-of-rail-trails/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/characteristics-of-rail-trails/</guid>
      <description>Catching up I wrote a blog post (one that, to be honest, I liked a lot) on what the best rail-trails are in Michigan (here). A friend and colleague at MSU, Andy, noticed that paved trails seemed to be rated higher, and this as well as my cfriend and colleague Kristy’s comment about how we can use the output of the the previous post sparked my curiosity in trying to figure out what characteristics predict how highly (or not highly) rated trails are.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are the best rail-trails in Michigan?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/michigan-rail-trails-and-pathways-through-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/michigan-rail-trails-and-pathways-through-data/</guid>
      <description>Background I was curious about what rail trails were the best in Michigan, and so to figure out an answer, I checked out the TrailLink website, sponsored by the Rails-to-Trails Conservancy. I had just purchased a copy of their book Rail-Trails Michigan and Wisconsin, and wanted to see whether I could learn more from the website.&#xA;To start, I checked whether they had a way to access the reviews on the site through an API.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How many groups of Star Wars characters are there? R-squared and cross-validation approaches</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/how-many-groups-of-star-wars-characters-are-there-r-squared-and-cross-validation-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/how-many-groups-of-star-wars-characters-are-there-r-squared-and-cross-validation-approaches/</guid>
      <description>Background How many groups, or types, of Star Wars characters are there? I’ve been wanting to use the starwars dataset built-in to the dplyr package, and at the same time, have been working hard on an R package to carry out an analysis suited to doing this. Part of the challenge of using the approach in this R package is determining how groups groups there are.&#xA;Many approaches (Latent Profile Analysis, for example) use Maximum Likelihood estimation (while the approach I’ve developed uses a two-step cluster analysis based around the geometric (and algebraic) idea of “distance”, or how close (similar) observations are).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 months on two wheels</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/24-months-on-two-wheels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/24-months-on-two-wheels/</guid>
      <description>Around two years ago, I was fortunate to not have to work in the summer: I had a research fellowship from May - August through the College of Education at MSU.&#xA;As a result, I didn’t buy a parking pass for the summer. I still came in to campus, but since I didn’t have any official, regularly-scheduled meetings, I thought I could bike in when I needed to. I had biked to campus before, so I was familiar with the route and where I would park my bike, but I didn’t regularly commute.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>prcr update</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-05-17-prcr-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 13:48:00 +0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-05-17-prcr-update/</guid>
      <description>The R package for person-oriented analysis (prcr) is updated (it’s now version 0.1.4).&#xA;In particular, it was not clear how to use the profile assignments (i.e., what cluster each response is in) in subsequent analyses. So, the update now returns two different representations of the profile assignments, or which profile is associated with each observation: a) the original “data.frame” with the profile assignment added in one variable and b) the original “data.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on an Introduction to R for Data Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-04-15-introduction-to-r-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 11:54:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-04-15-introduction-to-r-presentation/</guid>
      <description>I had an opportunity to present on an Introduction to R for Data Analysis to the School of Criminal Justice (at MSU).&#xA;The presentation is organized into five sections:&#xA;Background Wrangling, Plotting, and Modeling Essential Functionality Advanced Functionality Additional Resources A link to the presentation is here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Core and NGSS are not on the news</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 16:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</guid>
      <description>How often are curricular standards mentioned on TV news? With my friend Patrick, I was curious about using the newsflash package for something education-related. We came up with the idea of looking at mentions of the Common Core State Standards (for Mathematics and English Language Arts / Literacy) and the Next Generation Science Standards (for Science and Engineering).&#xA;On broadcast channels We first looked at mentions across ABC, CBS, FOX, NBC, and PBS (the way newsflash works is to keyword search the closed captioning streams from the Internet Archive’s Television News Archive):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What the world is data science education? Looking back on #dsetonline</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/what-the-world-is-data-science-education-looking-back-on-dsetonline/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/what-the-world-is-data-science-education-looking-back-on-dsetonline/</guid>
      <description>DSET A few weeks ago, I was fortunate to attend the Data Science Educational Technology (DSET) conference.&#xA;The goal for the conference was to kickstart data science education and to explore an educational technology, Concord Consortium’s Common Online Data Analysis Platform. What’s the big idea about data science education? To me, it’s a recognition that data is power, and that through asking questions, collecting and creating data, analyzing and modeling data, and making sense of and communicating what is going on can be empowering to learners.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Internet Archive&#39;s Television News Archive and Newsflash</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-11-rock-climbing-internet-television-news-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 01:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-11-rock-climbing-internet-television-news-archive/</guid>
      <description>Background The Internet Archive’s Television News Archive is a cool way to search closed captions from TV shows.&#xA;Here’s a bit more information on it:&#xA;The Internet Archive’s Television News Archive, GDELT’s Television Explorer allows you to keyword search the closed captioning streams of the Archive’s 6 years of American television news and explore macro-level trends in how America’s television news is shaping the conversation around key societal issues.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the flu really worse this year? Comparing the (ongoing) 2016-17 and 2015-16 flu seasons</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-02-28-comparing-cdc-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 09:28:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-02-28-comparing-cdc-data/</guid>
      <description>Background I was sick last week, and I think I might have had a mild case of the flu. Since it seems like a lot of people have been sick, I was curious whether the flu was really worse this year than last… and since the CDC makes the data available for each year, I put the data together and created a GIF. This project is just a first attempt but the code (it’s in R) is available in a GitHub repository.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>prcr: An R Package for Person-Centered Analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-02-17-introducing-prcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 16:59:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-02-17-introducing-prcr/</guid>
      <description>I’m excited to share that prcr (0.1.0), an R package for person-centered analysis, is now available on CRAN via install.packages(&amp;quot;prcr&amp;quot;).&#xA;Person-centered analyses focus on clusters, or profiles, of observations, and their change over time or differences across factors.&#xA;The package is designed to be “low threshold but high ceiling”, in that you can do all of the analysis with one function, create_profiles(df, n_clusters), where dfis a data.frame of the variables to cluster, and n_clusters is the specified number of clusters.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How much do we spend weekly on Groceries? Figuring out using R and Mint (Updated)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-17-exploring-mint-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 05:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-17-exploring-mint-r/</guid>
      <description>We started using Mint to keep track of our spending. One of the best features of Mint is the ability to see past patterns of spending (and to use that information to not spend quite as much on, well, coffee, and for those who know me well, sandwiches from Woody’s Oasis).&#xA;I listened to an episode of the Not So Standard Deviations, in which the hosts Peng and Parker discussed using spreadsheets and R to keep track of information for taxes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Announcing clustRcompaR v.0.1.0</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-07-clustrcompar-0.1.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 10:16:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-07-clustrcompar-0.1.0/</guid>
      <description>Alex Lishinski and I worked on an R package over the last year or so. We are excited that it’s now available on CRAN.&#xA;You can install the package using install.packages(&#39;clustRcompaR&#39;) (only needed first time) and load it (more on its two functions below) using library(clustRcompaR).&#xA;Here’s a description:&#xA;Provides an interface to perform cluster analysis on a corpus of text. Interfaces to Quanteda to assemble text corpuses easily. Deviationalizes text vectors prior to clustering using technique described by Sherin (Sherin, B.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wordpress Archive</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-07-wordpress-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 09:50:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-01-07-wordpress-archive/</guid>
      <description>I moved my Wordpress blog to Wordpress.com as an archive and so I would not need to pay to maintain the self-hosted site. The link is here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An examination of students</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160415-an-examination-of-students-epistemic-considerations-with-an-automated-approach-at-narst2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 09:31:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160415-an-examination-of-students-epistemic-considerations-with-an-automated-approach-at-narst2016/</guid>
      <description>An examination of students With Christina Schwarz, I presented on an examination of students’ epistemic considerations with an automated approach at the National Association for Research in Science Teaching Annual International Conference. Slides from the presentation are available here (PDF).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160323-presentation-on-an-introduction-to-r-for-programming-and-statistical-analysis-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2016 08:10:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160323-presentation-on-an-introduction-to-r-for-programming-and-statistical-analysis-in-education/</guid>
      <description>Presentation on an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education I had the opportunity to present an Introduction to R for Programming and Statistical Analysis in Education on the invitation of my colleague Mete Akcaoglu at Georgia Southern University’s College of Education. The presentation is available here.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160322-presentation-on-state-educational-twitter-hashtags-at-siteconf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 23:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20160322-presentation-on-state-educational-twitter-hashtags-at-siteconf/</guid>
      <description>Presentation on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at #siteconf With Matthew Koehler, Mete Akcaoglu, Spencer Greenhalgh, and Erica Hamilton, I presented on State Educational Twitter Hashtags at the Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education conference. We created an interactive web application to share the findings using R and Shiny that is available here. If you check it out then please let us know what you think.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slides for What Teachers and Researchers Discuss at Science Education Conferences at</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20151106-slides-for-what-teachers-and-researchers-discuss-at-science-education-conferences-at-aect15/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 15:27:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20151106-slides-for-what-teachers-and-researchers-discuss-at-science-education-conferences-at-aect15/</guid>
      <description>Slides for What Teachers and Researchers Discuss at Science Education Conferences at #AECT15 Slides for my presentation at AECT in the graduate student panel discussion on learning analytics on what teachers and researchers discuss at science education conferences are available here (in a Google Presentation).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slides for An Examination of State Educational Twitter Hashtags at</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20151106-slides-for-an-examination-of-state-educational-twitter-hashtags/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 10:03:06 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20151106-slides-for-an-examination-of-state-educational-twitter-hashtags/</guid>
      <description>Slides for An Examination of State Educational Twitter Hashtags at #AECT15 Slides for my presentation with Meta Akcaoglu, Erica Hamilton, Spencer Greenhalgh, and Matthew Koehler at AECT on State Educational Twitter Hashtags are available here (in a Google Presentation).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New article in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/20150804-first-article-in-jrte/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 19:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/20150804-first-article-in-jrte/</guid>
      <description>New article in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education My first article (in the Journal of Research on Technology in Education, JRTE) by me and Matthew J. Koehler is available as an advance online publication. If you’re interested in TPACK and want to see what I’ve been up to, then please check it out (or send me an email so I can send a copy your way).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/about/</guid>
      <description>PDF version: Curriculum Vitae Contents Contact Information Research Interests Education Professional Experience Additional Professional Affiliations Fellowships and Awards Grants PI, Co-PI, and Co-I Senior Personnel Consultant and Advisory Board Member Roles Publications Books (3) Articles Published in Refereed Journals (52) Commissioned Papers and White Papers (2) Editor-Reviewed Articles Published in Journals (11) Contributions to Edited Volumes (10) Papers Published in Refereed Conference Proceedings (32) Posts in the Popular Press (1) Blog posts and reports (4) Unpublished Manuscripts (2) Presentations Invited Talks (5) Peer-Reviewed Conference Presentations (79) Other Presentations Workshops (17) Outreach and Engagement (11) Teaching Service Software Miscellaneous Contact Information Associate Professor, STEM Education</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consulting and Other Services</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/consulting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/consulting/</guid>
      <description>I regularly consult and provide workshops in the following areas:&#xA;General The statistical software R (and the Interactive Development Environment R Studio) Statistical methods Linear and generalized linear models Mixed effects (or multilevel) models Intensive longitudinal methods Computational (and data science) methods Unsupervised and supervised machine learning methods Natural Language Processing and text analysis Social network models and methods Statistical programming and software development R package development Shiny interactive web application development Contact me for rates and additional details.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consulting and Other Services</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/research/</guid>
      <description>Consulting and Other Services I regularly consult on the use of research methods and provide workshops in the following areas:&#xA;General: The statistical software R (and the Interactive Development Environment R Studio) Statistical methods: Linear and generalized linear models Mixed effects (or multilevel) models Intensive longitudinal methods Computational (and data science) methods: Unsupervised and supervised machine learning methods Natural Language Processing and text analysis Social network analysis Accessing and analyzing social media data Statistical programming and software development R package development Shiny interactive web application development Contact me for rates and additional details.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Home</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/home/</guid>
      <description>Welcome! I am an Assistant Professor of STEM Education at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking to get in touch by email, please contact me at jmrosenberg [at] UTK [dot] edu.&#xA;Upcoming Presentations&#xA;Workshop on Developing Transparent and Reproducible Research with R at the American Educational Research Association meeting in Toronto, Canada on Sunday, April 7, 2019 - 8:00 am - 12:00 pm (register here; more info. here) Presentations at the American Educational Research Association meeting (April 4-9, Toronto, Canada) </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joshua M. Rosenberg</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/about-for-cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/about-for-cv/</guid>
      <description>Curriculum Vitae Contents Contact Information Research Interests Education Professional Experience Additional Professional Affiliations Fellowships and Awards Grants PI, Co-PI, and Co-I Senior Personnel Consultant and Advisory Board Member Roles Publications Books (3) Articles Published in Refereed Journals (52) Commissioned Papers and White Papers (2) Editor-Reviewed Articles Published in Journals (11) Contributions to Edited Volumes (10) Papers Published in Refereed Conference Proceedings (32) Posts in the Popular Press (1) Blog posts and reports (4) Unpublished Manuscripts (2) Presentations Invited Talks (5) Peer-Reviewed Conference Presentations (79) Other Presentations Workshops (17) Outreach and Engagement (11) Teaching Service Software Miscellaneous Contact Information Associate Professor, STEM Education</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/software/</guid>
      <description>Software Author of R packages on Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) Rosenberg, J. M., van Lissa, C. J., Beymer, P. N., Anderson, D. J., Schell, M. J. &amp;amp; Schmidt, J. A. (2019). tidyLPA: Easily carry out Latent Profile Analysis (LPA) using open-source or commercial software [R package]. https://data-edu.github.io/tidyLPA/&#xA;Rosenberg, J. M., Xu, R., &amp;amp; Frank, K. A. (2019). konfound: Quantify the robustness of causal inferences [R package]. https://jrosen48.github.io/konfound/&#xA;Rosenberg, J. M.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sundry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/sundry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/sundry/</guid>
      <description>Google Scholar BiBTeX Google Scholar BiBTeX: https://scholar.googleusercontent.com/citations?view_op=export_citations&amp;amp;user=nxVowRQAAAAJ&amp;amp;citsig=AMD79ooAAAAAXgJl-er18rHvDjfeA4IfaQKVbKm5ceFk&amp;amp;hl=en&#xA;My Packages my_packages &amp;lt;- tibble::tribble( ~Package, &amp;ldquo;abind&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;acepack&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;acs&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ada&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;afex&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;anytime&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;apaTables&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ape&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;arm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;AsioHeaders&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;askpass&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;assertthat&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;attempt&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;audio&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;backports&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;base&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;base64enc&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bayesplot&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bayestestR&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;beepr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;beeswarm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;BH&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bibtex&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bit&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bit64&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bitops&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;blob&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;blogdown&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bookdown&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;boot&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;brew&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bridgesampling&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;brms&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Brobdingnag&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;broom&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;broom.mixed&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;bupaR&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;BWStest&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;callr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;carData&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;caret&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;caTools&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;CCA&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;CCP&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cellranger&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;checkmate&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;choroplethr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;choroplethrMaps&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;citr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;class&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;classInt&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cli&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;clipr&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;clisymbols&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cluster&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;cmm&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;coda&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;codetools&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;coin&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;colorspace&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;colourpicker&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;commonmark&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;compiler&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;compute.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/teaching/</guid>
      <description>My teaching statement is available here&#xA;This page contains: a list of courses I have taught, including course descriptions and links to course websites (when available); information on workshops and outreach.&#xA;TPTE 110/TPTE 120 (Combo) Step 1 and Step 2 are highly collaborative, hands-on classes in which you learn about teaching through observation, practice, and professional mentoring. Each course consists of (a) classes at UTK and (b) field experiences at a local elementary or middle school.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technology I use</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/tech/</guid>
      <description>Technology I Use Web The Hugo static website generator The xmin theme for Hugo A GitHub repository for the website Netlify to render the website and host the files I use the same tools for my Making Data Science Count research group website, except I use the academic theme for Hugo.&#xA;Communication Slack Keybase (for some communication; it&amp;rsquo;s purported to be more secure and private than Slack) Outlook on my personal computer for email Fantastical for calendar (paid) Writing and editing Sublime text editor (not paid, but can be) Evernote for taking notes and for saving PDFs to read across devices (paid) Google Docs Microsoft Word (paid) R Markdown for writing reports LaTeX and BibTeX for writing particular documents Mendeley for references Boomerang for Outlook to schedule emails to arrive in bulk every two hours Coding and data analysis R Studio R with these packages git/GitHub Anaconda Python distribution Keeping track Todoist for managing tasks (paid) Trello for keeping track of projects Pocket Casts for subscribing to podcasts Pocket for keeping track of articles/webpages Feedly RSS reader Miscellaneous Dark Sky weather app (paid) 1 Password password manager (paid) RescueTime time tracker (paid) Hardware Android phone Mac computer </description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
