<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:4321/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4321/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Launching a Microcredential in Educational Data Analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/08/launching-a-microcredential-in-educational-data-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2022/04/08/launching-a-microcredential-in-educational-data-analytics/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be launching a microcredential (a non-credit bearing credential granted by the University) in educational data analytics with my colleague at UTK, Louis Rocconi. A nice description of microcredentials is available here; in brief:&#xA;A micro-credential is a short, competency-based recognition that allows an educator to demonstrate mastery in a particular area.&#xA;These don&amp;rsquo;t just apply to educators; a common microcredential in the data science world is the Data Science Specialization offered through Johns Hopkins University/Coursera; many data scientists got their start with the statistical software and programming language R through these (awesome) courses that lead to a non-credit bearing certificate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book published! Data Science in Education Using R</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/28/book-pub-lished-data-science-in-education-using-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/post/2020/10/28/book-pub-lished-data-science-in-education-using-r/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;ve likely heard me post, talk, or share about the book that is now published, Data Science in Education Using R. I just wanted to compile a few things here:&#xA;The book is always available open-access here: https://www.datascienceineducation.com/ The book is available for purchase in soft or hardcover versions through Routledge (here) (use code BSE20 for 20% off); you can always find it on Amazon (here) or-we hope-your local and independent bookstore Third, a recording of our book launch from this past Monday is here A blurb on the book is here:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at Middle Tennessee State University: Making Data Science Count</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-at-middle-tennessee-state-university-making-data-science-count/</guid>
      <description>I was lucky to have the chance to present at the Middle Tennessee State University Math and Science Education Seminar Series.&#xA;Presentation My presentation was on Making data science count: Exploring the integration of data science into education.&#xA;A link to the presentation is here.&#xA;Workshop I also carried out a two-hour workshop on An introduction to data science in education using R. A repository for the workshop, including a link to slides, code, and data, is here: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presentation on &#39;Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/presentation-on-won-t-you-be-my-neighbor-an-introduction-to-r-for-data-science-in-education/</guid>
      <description>This past week, I presented a workshop, Won’t you be my neighboR? An introduction to R for data science in education. for Educational Psychology and Educational Technology PhD students (and a few others) with Emily Bovee.&#xA;Here is the description:&#xA;R is a freely-available, cross-platform, open-source programming language and statistical software environment that is well-suited to data analysis and data science, but, can have an high barrier to entry. This workshop provides an introduction to R in education, with a focus on developing a foundation in capabilities (and confidence!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using MPlus from R with MPlusAutomation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/using-mplus-from-r/</guid>
      <description>Note that due to version-related issues the code in this post is displayed but is not excecuted/run.&#xA;According to the MPlus website, the R package MPlusAutomation serves three purposes:&#xA;Creating related groups of models Running batches Extracting and tabulating model parameters and test statistics. Because modeling involves comparing related models, (partially) automating these is compelling. It can make it easier to use model results in subsequent analyses and can cut down on copy and pasting output or results between programs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Core and NGSS are not on the news</title>
      <link>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2017 16:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:4321/posts/2017-03-16-education-policy/</guid>
      <description>How often are curricular standards mentioned on TV news? With my friend Patrick, I was curious about using the newsflash package for something education-related. We came up with the idea of looking at mentions of the Common Core State Standards (for Mathematics and English Language Arts / Literacy) and the Next Generation Science Standards (for Science and Engineering).&#xA;On broadcast channels We first looked at mentions across ABC, CBS, FOX, NBC, and PBS (the way newsflash works is to keyword search the closed captioning streams from the Internet Archive’s Television News Archive):</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
