<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>web-scraping on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</title>
    <link>/tags/web-scraping/</link>
    <description>Recent content in web-scraping on Joshua M. Rosenberg, Ph.D.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/web-scraping/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted? An update!</title>
      <link>/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/in-what-months-are-educational-psychology-jobs-posted-an-update/</guid>
      <description>In August of last year, I wrote a post that involved looking at when educational psychology jobs (mostly, but not only, academic jobs or those related to research and teaching) were posted to the excellent Ed Psych Jobs website. As that post made (in part) the (anticipated) point that most jobs were posted in September (in which 16% of jobs were posted there) and October (14%) (followed by August, with 11%), I thought that it may be helpful to see how accurate that was over the past year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In what months are educational psychology jobs posted?</title>
      <link>/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/when-are-ed-psych-jobs-posted/</guid>
      <description>Division 15 of the American Psychological Association sponsors the Ed Psych Jobs website, which is an excellent resource for Ed Psych job seekers. I thought it would possibly be helpful to see when jobs were posted in the past in order to have a better idea about when jobs may be posted this year.
Ed Psych Jobs, Robots (.txt), and paths_allowed, oh my As this project involves a bit of web-scraping, I first checked the robots.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>